<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-03T19:52:01+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Book “The Dip” - review and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-the-dip" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book &quot;The Dip&quot; - review and summary" /><published>2019-09-03T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/book_summary_the_dip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-the-dip">&lt;p&gt;I read “The Dip” by Seth Godin. It definitely raised couple interesting issues (one should drop
unimportant areas to be able to reach something reasonable in more important areas).
However, how to understand what to drop was not that clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book suggests to try to understand whether what you are doing has some future and the
tough period you are getting through is just temporary. The idea is to drop everything
with no future and focus only on one the most important thing. This allows you to get through the 
dip (the time when there is little progress and everything is hard). Also quiting is fine,
one just need to quit at the right time (before sinking a bunch of time).
However, the book does not tell that well how to identify which projects have future and which do not.
I agree that it is a useful perspective (one should focus, quitting may not mean failing),
but the trickiest part for me is to assess the future of a project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 3/5 (high level ideas are good + book is very short,
but not extremely actionable. Overall, I can slightly recommend)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quiting-is-ok&quot;&gt;Quiting is ok&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winners quit all the time. They just quit the right stuff at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quit the wrong stuff. Stick with the right stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winner-takes-all&quot;&gt;Winner takes all&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our culture celebrates superstars.
#1 can get 10x of #10 or 100x of #100. This reminds of Zipf’s law. 
Marketplace loves the winner. Thus, choosing the top is less risky.
At the same time, it is hard to get to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best can be the local best (i.e. recommended by friends, cheap, best in town).
Best is subjective.
However, if there are too many (infinity) options, then it is hard to choose
and easy to go for “the best”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Average is invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In school one learns to be well-rounded. This is wrong. E.g. when you choose a doctor,
what are you looking for? Only how they do the relevant for you tasks (i.e. medicine).
Also we are taught to pick lowest hanging fruits and give up if it is too hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not going to get to #1, you might as well quit now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types-of-situations&quot;&gt;Types of situations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-dip&quot;&gt;The Dip&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start something, it is fun.
The Dip is an effort screen to keep unmotivated people out.
It is easy to be a CEO, but hard to get there. Otherwise there would be too many
of them. Scarcity is the secret to value. The Dip creates value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dips give you opportunity to get ahead of your competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dip is the reason you are here. People and organizations fight the Dip by diversification.
It is easier to be mediocre than to confront reality and quit.
Knowing that you’re facing a dip is the first step in getting through. 
Rule: if you can’t get through the dip, don’t start.
Being 98% good is not enough, your competitors are 1 click away (in the Internet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-cul-de-sac-dead-end&quot;&gt;The Cul De Sac (dead end)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You work and nothing happens (neither worse nor better).
Quit. This leads to failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-cliff&quot;&gt;The Cliff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more you smoke, the harder it is to quit.
Quit. This leads to failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/book_summary_the_dip/types.png&quot; alt=&quot;Three kinds of situations illustration.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choose-correct-dips&quot;&gt;Choose correct dips&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either don’t start or get through the dip.
The stupid thing is to waste time and money by quiting at the dip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentivized-quitting&quot;&gt;Incentivized quitting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many systems benefit from people quiting (“Neflix”, gym).
Companies can intentionally lengthen the Dip to fight new competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-through-the-dip-by-quitting&quot;&gt;Getting through the dip by quitting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quiting frees your resources to go through the dip in the other areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need strategic quitting instead of reactive and serial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting up is thrilling, but your effort pays off only when you get through
the dip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dip is flexible. It reacts to your action. Once you are ready
to quit, you have nothing to lose. This can be powerful.
Quiting usually = short term focus.
We learn “If it hurts - stop” -&amp;gt; short term pain has more impact, so it is important to
amplify long term benefits of not quiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remind yourself of life at the other end of the dip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// The author often mentions these two (from my perspective) contradicting ideas - “quitting is hard to face” and
at the same time - “not quiting at the dip is hard”. I think this can be resolved by assuming that in the first
case one continue being mediocre and does not want to accept that this does not lead anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quit dead-ends, cliffs and dips not worth the rewards. Quitting is essential for sticking to the right projects.
Alternatively you settle for being average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quitting != failing.
Failing = give up or no other options left or quiting too often (which takes all your resources).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coping never leads to exceptional performance. Coping wastes time and misdirects your energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quitting as a short-term strategy is bad. Quitting for the long-term is an excellent idea.
“Never quit something with great long-term potential just because you can’t deal with the
stress of the moment”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pride is the enemy of quitting.
But hurting one’s pride by quitting is not fatal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about quitting is already a great start.
Then think:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Am I panicking?
 Panic is never premeditated. The best quitters decide in advance
 when they are going to quit. You can always quit later, so wait until
 you’re done panicking to decide.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who am I trying to influence?
 If you consider quitting, then you likely fail to influence some party.
 One person has different “threshold” from a market (too much persistence to
 influence one person = bothering). 
 Most people in the market have never heard about you.
 Influencing one person is like scaling a wall.
 A market is more like a hill. You can make a little progress bit by bit.
 It gets easier the higher you are (e.g. people talk to each other).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What sort of measurable progress am I making?
You either move forward, fall behind or stand still.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is much cheaper and easier to build your foundation in one market than to flit from
one to another until you find a quick success. Quitting a job is not quitting your
quest to make a living. It is not giving up. It is just a tactic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persistence is good when you move through/across the market.
This doesn’t work with a bad job though.
Quiting before your start - write down under what circumstances you are willing to quit and when.
Then stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are making a decision based on how you feel at the moment, you will probably make the
wrong decision.
E.g. you can talk yourself into quitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How dare you to settle for mediocre just because you are busy with too many things on your agenda?
If it’s not going to put a dent in the world, quit. Use that void to find the energy to
assault the Dip that matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach-summary&quot;&gt;Approach summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this a dip, cliff or cul de sac? How can I change cul de sav into dip?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is my persistence going to pay off in the long run?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When should I quit?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I am going to quit anyway, is there something dramatic I could do that might change the game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What chances does this project have to be the best in the world?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who decides what best is?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can we make the “world” smaller?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If it scares you, it might be a good thing to try.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short books are hard to write, write less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We succeed when we do something remarkable. We fail when we give up too soon. 
We succeed when we are the best in the world at what we do.
We fail when we get distracted by tasks we don’t have the guts to quit.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I read “The Dip” by Seth Godin. It definitely raised couple interesting issues (one should drop unimportant areas to be able to reach something reasonable in more important areas). However, how to understand what to drop was not that clear.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book “Purple cow” - review and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-purple-cow" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book &quot;Purple cow&quot; - review and summary" /><published>2019-08-31T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-31T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/book_summary_purple_cow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-purple-cow">&lt;p&gt;I read “Purple Cow” by Seth Godin. Overall, it was quite an interesting way to approach
marketing nowadays + very motivating to be riskier and experiment more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book gives an interesting approach to doing modern marketing by being remarkable (unusual). 
The arguments are definitively anecdotal, but overall felt reasonable.
I tool a couple of ideas from it and plan to apply them in my projects.
The book also discusses early stages of a product development and 
being more risky and experimenting more. I found this quite motivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 4/5 (not bad, +1 point for being motivating.
Definitely not a waste of time, but hard to actively recommend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;old-marketing-is-no-more&quot;&gt;Old marketing is no more&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can no longer market directly to masses. Products are invisible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people can’t buy your product. Either they don’t have money, time or don’t want it. There are far more
choices nowadays and less time to sort them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are over-satisfied, so word of mouth is not that popular anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old rule was: create safe ordinary products and combine them with great marketing.
The new rule is: create remarkable products which the right people seek out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All successful marketing companies are very different. The only thing they have in common is remarkability 
(and being an outlier). People are blind to old school ads. You have to create something remarkable and be
more bold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author calls a remarkable product a Purple Cow (hereinafter, Cow).
Cow is the only way to grow your business these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author multiple times calls products which provide more value remarkable.
I personally found this weird, because the product is just better that’s what attracts people. 
It is obvious that when you have a much better product, it is easier for people to choose it
(they are incentivized to do so in some sense). Yes, you can call this remarkable, but
“make better products” mantra is obvious without calling it “remarkable”.
In particular, an elevator example. Some company was installing elevators with their own
scheduling system, which worked much better than others. This worked well for the company and the author
calls them remarkable. Technically true…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adoption&quot;&gt;Adoption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, your product gets picked up by innovators. Then early adopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/book_summary_purple_cow/adoption_curve.png&quot; alt=&quot;Adoption curve illustration. First a small number of innovators adopt your product. Then early adopters (more).
Then early and late majority (the major part of all the adopters). Finally, small portion of laggards.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one is going to eagerly adapt to your product.
You need people who like new and change. Early adopters are the ones who will “sell” it further.
Being remarkable helps to attract early adopters and helps them to spread it further
(makes it easier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;idea-virus&quot;&gt;Idea-virus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea is like a virus. You need “sneezers” (experts sharing to others) to spread it.
Create an idea virus for a small niche.
Product made for everybody is made for nobody.
When choosing the niche, consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How easy it is to spread your idea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How tight is the group you are targeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product needs to be designed virus-worthy in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertise where your customers (sneezers) are actively looking for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If no one in the market listens, you can leave or launch a series of Cows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differentiate your customers - e.g. most profitable group, most likely to sneeze and so on.
Reward sneezing group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;playing-safe-is-risky-dont-be-boring&quot;&gt;Playing safe is risky. Don’t be boring.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schools teach us to play safe - not falling behind, not standing out.
If you don’t stand out, you don’t attract criticism. We mistakenly believe that
criticism leads to failure. Criticism of project != of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t know whether Cow is going to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being boring is risky.
Following someone doing a breakthrough won’t work either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many products are built to appeal to as many people as possible.
This is not interesting for innovators and for majority either (not enough adoptance
yet for them to adopt).
Mass products are expensive to create, thus, taking risk (experimenting) with them is expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World is very turbulent, people tend to safety and this is actually more risky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider experimenting with the users changing their standard behavior to make the product work
dramatically better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If future of a product is unlikely to be remarkable, kill it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-do-with-cow&quot;&gt;What to do with Cow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have Cow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Milk” it as much as you can&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to build a replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can get benefits of Cow even when it becomes boring (your product is already popular).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selling new stuff to people who love you is easier and cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get popular, you stop being remarkable - everyone just chooses you.
This is also a way to kill Cow for profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cow is a stage in product life cycle, you can’t be there all the time
(too risky and expensive), but when you get something new or need to grow that’s what you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-cow&quot;&gt;Building Cow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Very good” is rarely remarkable.
Remarkable = bad or unexpectedly good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your product appears in parody, then likely there is Cow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either work on Cow or do nothing - mediocre half measures (e.g. rebrandings) just make harder for existing sneezers
to spread your product. You should look for people with otaku [(wiki)[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Otaku]] - actively
eager to try your product (take the risk).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no 100% recipe for Cow. Go for cutting edge (in product, pricing, packaging).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slogan helps sneezers to spread.
E.g. Pisa tower is very easy to describe, so it is popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A compromise can’t be risky. Thus, Cow can’t be built by a committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collect emails of people you impress with your Cow, to present them the next Cow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product needs to be built remarkable (i.e. built to support easy marketing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easier to develop a product if you yourself have an otaku (~obsession) for it.
Sometimes this is not enough and you need to either imagine what your fans want or iterate a lot and fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be outrageous. This can sometimes work, but mostly just annoys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remarkable != big. Rather unusual (“unsafe”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap is the last resort Cow (but tricky due to price war).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you measure something, it will improve”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cow-in-job-search&quot;&gt;Cow in job search&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can apply Cow when looking for a job.
Just sending your resume is “boring”.
Instead you should be so remarkable that you don’t even need a resume.
Do a great job while you are not looking for a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;address-the-niche&quot;&gt;Address the niche&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“South park” scored 1.5/10 with women, but the group that mattered for the series found it to be a great success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your product needs to be irresistible to a small group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explore the limits - be the most &amp;lt;some adjective&amp;gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I read “Purple Cow” by Seth Godin. Overall, it was quite an interesting way to approach marketing nowadays + very motivating to be riskier and experiment more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book “Search Inside Yourself” - review and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-search-inside-yourself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book &quot;Search Inside Yourself&quot; - review and summary" /><published>2019-08-27T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-27T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/book_summary_search_inside_yourself</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-search-inside-yourself">&lt;p&gt;I finished reading “Search Inside Yourself” by Chade-Meng Tan recently.
This was an amazing book. I enjoyed it and learned a lot. I can call it life-changing.
Here is my review and summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is very well written and organized. Overall it touches many tricky topics
(like emotional intelligence, empathy, mindfulness). Since the author is an engineer from Google,
they manage to explain everything very well (perhaps even a bit from technical perspective).
For each topic the book always considers practical aspects and there is always a link to the real life applications
(team building, leadership). This also felt like a deep dive into topics from “The science of wellbeing”
course, which I did before and here is
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;my summary&lt;/a&gt;.
The intersection is large, but the book goes much deeper and also gives more actionable advice on
what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 5/5 (amazing life-changing book, everyone should read it after taking “The science of wellbeing” course)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emotional-intelligence&quot;&gt;Emotional Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotional Intelligence (EI) is one of the best predictors of success at work and fulfillment in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salovey-Mayer definition of EI - ability to monitor one’s own and other’s feelings and emotions,
to discriminate among them and to use this information to guide one’s thinking and actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goleman’s domains of EI:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-awareness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self-regulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;motivation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;empathy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;social skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EI helps to perform better at work, makes people better leaders, creates conditions for our own 
sustainable happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To train EI, we train attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankl: “Between stimulus and response there is a space. In that space lives our freedom and our power to
choose our response. In our response lies our growth and our happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basal ganglia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basal_ganglia&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;) stores our wisdom, but it has no connectivity
to verbal cortex. Thus, instead of words, it tells us what it knows in feelings (a gut feeling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy way to experience mindfulness - bring your attention to your breathing gently for 2 minutes.
Every time your attention wanders, just bring it back to breathing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easier way - just seat without an agenda for 2 min. You can switch between easy and easier ways at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise can be rephrased as “breathing as if you life depends on it” (Kabat-Zinn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Expensive food meditation” - eating food as if it is very expensive and rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific definition of meditation (by Brefczynski-Lewis) - a family of mental training practices that
are designed to familiarize the practitioner with specific types of mental processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness meditation trains EI via attention (taking possession of the mind, in clear and vivid form)
and meta-attention (ability to know that your attention wandered away).
Meta-attention is the secret for concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happiness is the default state of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is exercise for the mind to gain more mental abilities. In both meditation and exercise
growth comes from overcoming resistance.
Every time we bring a wandering attention back, we are giving our muscles of attention an 
opportunity for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Grandmother mind”: you are perfect and grandmother loves you as you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The posture should help to be alert and relaxed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four step plan for distractions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experience without judging or reacting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you need to react, continue maintaining mindfulness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let it go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have to react during a meditation (e.g. scratch your leg) - try to take 5 breadths before reacting - to
create space between stimulus and reaction.
This gives more control in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is about inquiry like science. Attention is a tool for developing insights into the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation has been studied by Davidson and Kabat-Zinn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;benefits-of-meditation&quot;&gt;Benefits of meditation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After eight weeks of meditation subjects were measurably happier (measured in brains) and
showed an increase in developing immunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 months of training reduce attention blink (Slagter, Lutz, Davidson) - i.e. the shortest time between two acts of selective
attention (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attentional_blink&quot;&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lutz has showed that meditation has effect at rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kabat-Zinn - mindfulness accelerates psoriasis healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lazar - meditation leads to thicker cortex in attention and sensory processing areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation helps to pay attention better, e.g. in a class. It is important to integrate mindfulness in your everyday life.
We take stuff for granted (no pain, three meals, being able to walk). With mindfulness these become a source of joy,
because we no longer take them for granted. Experiences get better too, because our full attention is there.
In mindfulness, neutral experiences tend to become pleasant, pleasant experiences tend to become even more pleasant
(there is no downside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can accelerate mindfulness generalization by bringing it to activity. Every time attention wanders, gently bring
it back to the task. I.e. like sitting meditation, but the object is the task at hand rather than the breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;walking-meditation&quot;&gt;Walking meditation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best formal practice is walking meditation.
When walking - bring full moment-to-moment attention to every moment and sensation in the body
and every time it wanders away, just gently bring it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking meditation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stand still&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;experience pressure on the feet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a step forward&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lift&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;plant your feet mindfully&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a moment to experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do it with the other foot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can repeat silently “lifting, lifting, lifting”, “moving, moving, moving”,
“standing, standing, standing”. After some step you can turn “turning, turning, turning”.
You can synchronize with breathing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lifting foot - breathe in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving out and planting - breathe out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to walk slowly, thus, you can do it every time you walk.
I do this on my way to restroom and this helps me to be creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other practice - directed mindfulness - like before but object of meditation is another person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;formal-mindful-listening&quot;&gt;Formal mindful listening&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take 2 people. One has 3 minute monologue (silence is allowed), second can only acknowledge. Then switch.
Possible topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;feeling right now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;something that happened today&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anything else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informal practice - when listening in everyday life, give your full attention.
If your mind wanders, gently bring it back to other person talking.
Don’t lead the conversation, just acknowledge and don’t over acknowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our attention is the most valuable gift we can give to others. Give people you care about a few minutes
of your attention every day. They will bloom like flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindful conversation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mindful listening&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looping - say what you heard, other person can give more feedback&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dipping - self directed mindfulness during listening - acknowledging internal chatter and feelings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To practise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 minute monologue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6 minute looping &amp;amp; dipping.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can practise this informally - “left me repeat how I understand this. Let me know if I am correct.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is like an exercising. It is not sufficient to just understand the topic. You can only
benefit from it with practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sustain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find a buddy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do less than you can (so that it does not become a chore)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One mindful breath a day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focused attention - focus on a chosen object.
Open attention - willing to meet any object that arrives to the mind or the senses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;self-awareness&quot;&gt;Self-awareness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-awareness - “knowing one’s internal states, preference, resources and intuitions” (Goleman’s definition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It engages neo-cortex (the thinking brain) in the processing of emotion. The moment you can see an emotion,
you are no longer fully engulfed in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competencies of self awareness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emotional - recognizing your emotions and the effects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accurate - knowing your strengths and limits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;self confidence - a strong sense of one’s self worth and capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self awareness is mindfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formal practice - body scan - bring moment-to-moment non-judging attention to different parts of your body.
This helps to fall asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;journaling&quot;&gt;Journaling&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journaling - self-discovery by writing to yourself. You are trying to let your thoughts flow onto paper,
so you can see what comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 3 minutes, write “What I am feeling now is”. Try not to think, just write. It doesn’t matter how closely
you follow the prompt, just let all your thoughts flow onto the paper. If you run out, just write “I have
nothing to write”. Remember - you write this to yourself, you won’t have to show this to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spera et all: people writing about their feelings (20 min / day for 5 days) found a job much sooner.
Very Short List (VSL): Science -&amp;gt; students writing about experiences for 15 min a day were healthier, had higher grader, better mood and wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four minutes is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prompts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What I am feeling now is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am aware that&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What motivates me is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I am inspired by&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Today I aspire to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What hurts me is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Others are&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I made a happy mistake&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Love is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formal journaling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(Priming) 2 minutes thinking about one or more instances in which you responded positively to a challenging situation
and the outcome was satisfying. If considering more than one instance - think about connections or patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;30 seconds pause&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 minutes for each
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Things that give me pleasure are …&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;My strengths are …&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Priming as above, but for responding negatively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;30 seconds pause&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 minutes for each
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Things that annoy me are …&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;My weaknesses …&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read what you wrote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;handling-emotions&quot;&gt;Handling emotions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are what you feel, not who you are.
Emotions go from “I am” to “I feel” with mindfulness practice.
With more practice you begin to see them as psychological phenomena.
We are like sky and thoughts and emotions are clouds.
They come and go.
This allows one to have mastery over their emotions
and move them from compulsion to choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotions are like a horse. They can drive us without us knowing where. We can tame and guide this horse.
We need to understand it first (self awareness).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self regulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Self control - keeping disruptive emotions and impulses in check&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trustworthiness - maintaining standards of honesty and integrity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consciousness - taking responsibility for personal performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adaptability - flexibility in handling change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Innovation - being comfortable with novel ideas, approaches and info.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonality for all of them - choice.
We need to move from compulsion to choice to enable all of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self regulation is not about avoiding emotions and not about denying or repressing true feelings.
They are valuable info. It is not about never having certain emotions. It is about becoming skillful with them.
It is impossible to stop a thought or emotion from arising. But we have the power to let it go.
The trained mind can do it in the moment it arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;letting-go&quot;&gt;Letting go.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pain and suffering are different.
The key is to let go of grasping (mind holds onto something) and aversion (mind keeps something away). They account for 
huge percentage of suffering we experience. They are separate from sensation and perception, but arise so close together
that we don’t see the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you can distinguish them, you have an opportunity to experience pain without suffering. 
The theory is that aversion (not pain) causes the suffering. Another benefit is experiencing
pleasure without aftertaste of unsatisfactoriness.
Our clinging to experiences causes suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dealing-with-distress&quot;&gt;Dealing with distress&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know when you are not in pain.
 Be aware when you are not in pain. This makes us happier. When we are in pain we say “with no pain I will be so much happier”,
 but then we forget. The pain is not constant. Appreciating low levels of pain (even temporary, especially emotional)
 helps to start the recovery.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not feel bad about feeling bad. “Meta distress” - distress about experiencing distress. This is an act of our ego (reflection
of its image of itself). The solution is to let go of ego.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do not feed the monsters.
Anger needs repeating of angry stories. If you don’t repeat them - anger may go away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start every thought with kindness and humor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural model of emotion regulation: mindfulness increases bandwidth between emotion and regulation parts of the brain,
so that the can communicate more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To deal with triggers - identify when you are triggered (e.g. fight-or-flight response). Triggers
are based on insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice to handle triggers (or negative distressing emotions) “Siberian North Railroad”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breathe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Notice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Respond&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not react for one moment aka “Sacred pause”. This enables all other steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reflecting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;everybody wants to be happy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this person thinks that acting this way will make them happy in some way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine the kindest most positive response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can practise reflection and response step retroactively - after the triggering event is over.
This can be generalized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attention deployment (count to 10 or take deep breath or think of something else)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reframing or reinterpreting meaning of the situation:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;see positives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;kindness and compassion&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance and willingness to experience emotion
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;meshing (let emotion go through your body)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;humor and curiosity
One needs step (2), because otherwise the situation will be there and will re-trigger the person.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better self regulation = better recovery mechanism after failure -&amp;gt; more self confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, self regulation is about making friends with our emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. you can see panic as a boss and obey it or like an enemy and wish it to go away.
Instead you could be friends and just allow it to come and go at will and treat it with kindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You already know your deepest values and motivations,
you just need help in discovering them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tony Hsieh describes 3 components of happiness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pleasure (chasing the next thing)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Passion aka flow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Higher purpose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sustainability of each decreases.
We often chase (1) thinking that it is sustainable,
i.e. we spend the most effort on (1), a little on (2) and almost no on (3).
Tony suggests to do the reverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the best way to motivate yourself is to find your own higher purpose.
Then you get good at it, thus, enjoy more flow. Then gain recognition
and get bonuses and mentions, i.e. (1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three practices for motivation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Alignment: aligning our work with our value and higher purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Create a situation in which your work is fun for you, but you get paid.
 Intrinsic motivators:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Autonomy - the urge to direct our lives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mastery - the desire to get better and better at something that matters&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Purpose - the yearning to do what we do in service of something larger than ourselves.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Traditional monetary incentives work well for routine, rule-based work.
 For creative work then can even be counter productive.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Another way to clarify your values and higher purpose is to tell them to other people.
 Act of verbalizing them forces us to make them clearer and more tangible to ourselves.
 Another way is to journal:
     * my core values are …
     * I stand for …&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Envisioning: seeing the desired future for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It is much easier to achieve something if you can visualize yourself already achieving it.
 In a sense we learn from the past what to predict for the future and then live the future
 we expect. In other words - you have to expect things of yourself before you can do them.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Exercise: Discover my ideal future: if everything in my life, starting from today, meets
 or exceeds my most optimistic expectations, what will my life be in five years?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The more detailed the imagery in your mind, the better this works.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Consider in this future:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Who are you and what are you doing?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How do you feel?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What do people say about you?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Spend 1 minute in silent contemplation before writing.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Variations:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;more time (hours)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;final date (10 years)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;pretend you live there and write your daily diary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;own obituary or two (current and desired)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Talk about your ideal future with others:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The more you talk, the more real it becomes to you.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The more likely it is to find people to help you
 (especially when it is something altruistic).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Resilience: the ability to overcome obstacles in our path.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Overcome obstacles.
 Levels:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Inner calm. Deep inner calm always allows you to stay resilient. Mindfulness trains this.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Emotional. Success and failure are emotional experiences. When we become capable of containing
emotions and able to let go of grasping and aversion, we can become emotionally resilient to success
and failure.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;Meditation on resilience&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Calm mind - attention to body parts.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;4 min - failure&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;4 min - success&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Returning to calm.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cognitive. “Success is 99 percent failure”. “Failure is the mother of success”.
If you want to do something new and innovative, you often need to feel stupid as well.
“You have to be confused, upset, think you are stupid. If you are not willing to do that, you
can’t go outside the box”.
The failure is a common experience. What distinguishes successful people is their attitude
to failure and specifically how they explain their own failure to themselves.
Optimist reacts to setbacks as temporary and can be overcome by effort and abilities.
To learn optimism, become realistic &amp;amp; objective (normally we pay more attention to negative).&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;p&gt;Fredrickson has found that it takes 3 positive experiences to overcome one negative.
You life ratio can be 2 positive to 1 negative and you will feel unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We need to be aware of out strong negative experiential bias. We pay too much attention
to failures and too little to successes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mindfulness leads to objectivity toward our own experiences.
Bring attention to tendency to downplay success and to disproportionally strong effect of failure.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Transformation. Take conscious note of success and accept credit for it. This creates mental habit
of paying attention to success. When experiencing failure focus on realistic evidence 
suggesting that this setback may be temporary. If you find any evidence suggesting reasons for
realistic hope, bring attention to it.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empathy&quot;&gt;Empathy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirror neurons - cells that fire when one performs an activity or when another person is performing an activity.
When you see your loved one in pain, you share a similar affective experiences (neural foundation for compassion).
Empathy works by having you physiologically mimic the other person. Empathy relies on self awareness.
“Psychologizing” - dismissing the problem - not understanding it.
Empathy does not mean psychologizing or agreeing.
It increases with kindness and perceived similarity.
To be more empathetic, we need to instinctively respond to everyone with kindness and an automatic perception of other being
just like me -&amp;gt; we need to create mental habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We become what we think. Inviting a thought to arise in your mind is often enough and it will become
a mental habit. E.g. wishing another person to be happy -&amp;gt; you get instinctive thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informal practice - generate this thought every time you meet people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like me &amp;amp; loving kindness meditation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min breath.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bring mind to somebody you care about.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read script for
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“just like me”
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;This person has a body and a mind, just like me.
This person has feelings, emotions, and thoughts, just like me.
This person has, at some point in his or her life, been sad, disappointed, angry, hurt, or confused, just like me.
This person has, in his or her life, experienced physical and emotional pain and suffering, just like me.
This person wishes to be free from pain and suffering, just like me.
This person wishes to be healthy and loved, and to have fulfilling relationships, just like me.
This person wishes to be happy, just like me.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;“kindness”
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;I wish for this person to have the strength, the resources, and the emotional and social support to navigate the difficulties in life.
I wish for this person to be free from pain and suffering.
I wish for this person to be happy.
Because this person is a fellow human being, just like me.
(Pause)
Now, I wish for everybody I know to be happy.
(Long pause)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 min resting
It can be used to heal relationships and deal with conflicts (dissipate anger).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional Metta Bhavana (source for the loving kindness approach above):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min rest&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May I be well / happy / free from suffering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone you like&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May he or she be well / happy / free from suffering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone neutral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May he or she be well / happy / free from suffering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone negative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May he or she be well / happy / free from suffering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;May they be well / happy / free from suffering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;trust&quot;&gt;Trust&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy helps to build trust. 
Five dysfunctions of a team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Absence of trust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fear of conflict (no debates)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of commitment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoidance of accountability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inattention to results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absence of trust is the root cause of all dysfunctions.
Specifically “vulnerability-based trust” - willing to expose our own
vulnerabilities because we are confident that they won’t be used against us.
Once you learn to establish this type of trust, you can become effective
team-leader, mentor, coach. Trust has to begin with sincerity, kindness and openness.
Assume that other person is good and deserves to be treated as such until proven otherwise.
Assume that others make the right choice, even if we don’t understand or would have done differently ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust begets trust. If you assume someone is trustworthy, it is easier to build trust with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three assumptions (before a meeting)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assume that everybody in this room is here to serve the greater good until proven otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given the above assumption, none of us has any hidden agenda until proven otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are all reasonable even when disagree until proven otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathic listening - like listening practice above, but for feelings.
Same exercise as in mindful conversation but “What I hear you feel is”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors never explain what a given skill is before doing any of the exercises in their courses.
These skills come preinstalled into humans, we just need to improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve empathetic listening, we need
mindfulness, kindness, curiosity and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can practice informally. Do mindfulness meditation, then “Just like me / Loving kindness”.
Start by thinking “I want this person to be happy”.
Give as much feedback (or go into feelings) as possible. Give them airtime.
Consider going meta in the end - “Was this conversation helpful to you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;praise&quot;&gt;Praise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never praise falsely - it will be sniffed out and you will lose credibility.
However, you still need to praise skillfully.
Bad praise can undermine. Being praised for being smart is bad (“a person praise”)
-&amp;gt; fixed mindset (success due to a fixed trait). In this framework a fail would mean
personal inadequacy. “Process praise” (“You must have worked hard”) -&amp;gt; “growth mindset”
-&amp;gt; creates love of learning and resilience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Structure feedback around effort and growth rather than by labeling the person, i.e. 
for working hard rather than being smart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;political-awareness&quot;&gt;Political awareness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political awareness - reading organization’s emotional currents and power relationships.
Generalization of empathy from an interpersonal level to an organization level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rich personal network. To do this - care about people, help people and nurture relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practice reading currents. How decisions are made, by authority or consensus.
Who are the most influential in making them?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distinguish your own self interest, your team’s and organization’s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercise (writing or speaking)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of conflict or disagreement (real, with meaning for you).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Describe the situation as if you are 100% correct and reasonable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Same for other person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose - see perspectives of different players. Both parties can be correct and reasonable
in a conflict -&amp;gt; different priorities, missing info.
Once you see that both parties are correct and reasonable, you will be able to understand
differing perspectives objectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kindness is the most important mental habit for empathy.
I.e. during an interaction “this person is a human being just like me. 
I want him or her to be happy” should effortlessly arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be liked helps in career.
Leading with compassion.
Compassion is the happiest state ever.
The second happiest is “open awareness”.
Compassion is a mental state endowed with a sense of concern for the
suffering of others and aspiration to see that suffering relieved.
Components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I understand you”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I feel for you”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I want to help you”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compassion creates highly effective leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compassion is about switching from “I” to “we”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on “Good to Great” by Collins, company needs L5 leader to become great (from good),
i.e. highly capable, great ambition (for greater good, thus, no need to inflate ego), personal humility.
As a result they are highly effective and inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compassion can be used to train L5 (necessary, but may be insufficient).
We can train compassion by mental habits.
Exercise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min resting on breath.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualize your goodness as white light radiating out of your body. Breathe in all your goodness in your heart.
Multiply 10x in your heart. Breathe out and send goodness out to the whole world
(e.g. like brilliant white light).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min pause&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Same as above, but for people you know.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min pause.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Same for everyone in the world.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 min pause.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 min resting on breath.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This develops&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeing goodness in others and self.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving goodness to all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confidence that you can multiply goodness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonglen meditation - same as above, but breathe in suffering and pain and transform into goodness.
You can start with multiplying goodness and after some time give Tonglen a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;influencing&quot;&gt;Influencing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already influence others. They key is to expand this and use for good.
Social brain - “minimize danger (with high weight), maximize reward (with low weight”.
We respond more strongly to negative events than to positive (Fredrickson -&amp;gt; 3 negative : 1 positive ratio
makes people more resilient
and helps to achieve goals, Gottman -&amp;gt; 5:1 for marriage to succeed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCARF model - five primary domains (survival issues)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Status - relative importance. When learning something that matters to you, you gain status (reward against
your former self).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Certainty - uncertainty takes brain resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomy - perception of exerting control over environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relatedness - whether another person is “friend” or “foe”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fairness - people are the only animals to sacrifice their self interest
due to unfairness (99 and 1 dollar example - I am given an offer where I can take 1 dollar and if I do so
another person will get 99 dollars. Even though having 1 dollar is better than 0, the person is inclined not
to take it due to unfairness).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;difficult-conversations&quot;&gt;Difficult conversations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Difficult conversations - the ones hard to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framework:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three conversations (walk though them as a preparation):
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What happened&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What emotions are involved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What does this say about me (am I competent, good person, worthy of love)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sort out objectively what happened, understand yours and others emotions, identify what is at stake for you.
Decide whether to raise the issue. What do you want to accomplish? Solve a problem? Help? Or make someone feel bad?
Sometimes the right thing is not to raise the issue.
Start from objective “Third Story” (third party view).
Explore their story and yours.
Problem solve - invent solutions to meet concerns and interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impact is not intention. We judge ourselves by intentions and others by impact (infer intentions).
If someone said something and hurt us, this doesn’t mean that they wanted this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are issues of identity in every difficult conversation. E.g. “Am I competent?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preparing for a difficult conversation - may be in writing or speaking (e.g. to a friend):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think of a difficult conversation (you had, will or should have had).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Describe the three conversation from your point of view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then from the other person’s perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;e-mails&quot;&gt;E-mails&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In e-mails - emotional context can be miscommunicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain gets no emotional data and makes it up. 
It believes the result to be true. Usually the result has strong negative bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice for mindful email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breathing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect humans on receiving end.
Just like you. You may do “Just like me” meditation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write email.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reflect that the receiver will assume negative emotions if none.
Reread email from their perspective and assuming no context.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breath before sending. You may change your mind and don’t send.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mantra - love them, understand them, forgive them, grow with them.
Repeat silently when in difficult situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inner happiness is contagious. Social interactions become more positive
-&amp;gt; create more inner happiness. Positive feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I finished reading “Search Inside Yourself” by Chade-Meng Tan recently. This was an amazing book. I enjoyed it and learned a lot. I can call it life-changing. Here is my review and summary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stagnation in impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation-in-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stagnation in impro" /><published>2019-08-24T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-24T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation_in_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation-in-impro">&lt;p&gt;I started to feel a stagnation in impro. 
I have a hypothesis that this is natural and expected.
Let’s see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impro-for-fun&quot;&gt;Impro for fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally haven’t met that many groups doing deliberate practice in impro.
It looks like accepting random participants into the workshops makes this impossible.
In order to deliberately practice people must be heavily motivated and focused.
In the end newcomers may not even like impro at all, thus, it makes no sense for them to exert
that much effort. I speculate that one needs closed meetings (e.g. invite only,
where all members have to accept a new member) to do deliberate practice.
As a result, 99% of workshops I have been to are meant for fun and laughing.
It is mostly about using the skills you already have and not that much about improving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progress-in-impro&quot;&gt;Progress in impro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t started that long ago, so I don’t know how this works in the long term.
However, I clearly observed that initially one just removes their own inner blocks
and starts risking to experiment and make mistakes. This is the first stage in impro growth.
In the beginning one is scared to look weird, to be misunderstood, to accidentally insult someone. 
Step by step these blocks get removed and finally one builds almost a direct channel of their
inner creativity to execution. This feels like an enormous growth. I think initially at
my first impro workshops I only observed others and minimized my interactions
(i.e. I did anything only when necessary). I never volunteered and didn’t express myself 
without an external demand. However, already in couple weeks I started to understand
that everyone accepts whatever I do and no one uses that against others. 
People don’t use what you do (especially if you fail) to evaluate you as a person.
That’s very popular outside of impro and I get this reaction often when I tell people
about impro. E.g. I say that one needs a special very understanding group, because some 
stuff may look crazy. Others often reply something like “oh, yeah, people have weird
stuff inside them which just comes out”. That’s a wrong way to look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expectation of no judging helps enormously to progress at first. Basically you just unlock
your skills which you already have - acting, singing, story telling, dancing. Everyone has them
developed to some degree, people are just too shy to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stagnation&quot;&gt;Stagnation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to this level (at a very high speed), you reach a plateau.
Removing inner blocks is not easy, but it is reasonably fast.
And you see very rapid results. Developing the base skills (e.g. acting)
is quite slow. Much slower than removing the blocks. Moreover, the fun workshops
work even better for removing the blocks (people care less about the process or results,
it is less painful when you screw up), they don’t help much with developing the underlying skills.
I can clearly see that some other people seem to perform much better (the result is more interesting),
but I can’t reverse engineer why. There is too much indirection - they just perform a random
scene involving a lot of elements - the problem gets too hard to reverse engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that I am at this level right now. It feels like standing at one spot.
My impressions is that I perform consistently better than when I started, but 
I don’t see that much growth anymore. Occasionally people mention little details 
which could be improved, but this happens somewhat rarely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I have no clue where this will bring me or whether I will be able to overcome this plateau.
I didn’t plan to take acting classes (and still don’t). I also didn’t expect that this would
be needed for getting better at impro (pardon so naive me). Thus, let’s just see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-better&quot;&gt;What is “better”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, what does it even mean to become better at impro?
I think everyone has their own goals. E.g. if people play impro games
without an audience and never intend to perform, then it could be just
“having more fun”. If they plan to perform with audience, then the
criterion must be “more interesting to observe”. Since each workshop
usually has “temporary audience” (other participants who don’t take part in the scene),
the second criterion feels much more common. For “having more fun” case, you
probably need a very small group of e.g. 2-4 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, “more interesting to observe” does not help much to grow.
It is not obvious that better acting will be that much more interesting
to observe. One definitely needs more peculiar and interesting ideas
in order for the resulting scene to be interesting. I am not aware of any skill
outside of impro directly targeting this area. Perhaps this is the
gist of impro and one can improve it only be doing and observing more impro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-plan&quot;&gt;My plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall impro is a lot of fun for me, so I do plan to continue.
I can’t say that my main goal is to grow. Just having fun is already 
good enough. Thus, I will just proceed as it is and see whether I
keep having no progress. If this persists for long time and becomes
not fun anymore, I will re-evaluate the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy growth in impro!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><summary type="html">I started to feel a stagnation in impro. I have a hypothesis that this is natural and expected. Let’s see why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Consumerism would be rational if FIRE did not exist</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-non-existence-and-consumerism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consumerism would be rational if FIRE did not exist" /><published>2019-08-20T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-non-existence-and-consumerism">&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that consumerism makes sense if one assumes that Financial Independence is not achievable. 
Let’s look more into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-fire-perspective&quot;&gt;“No FIRE” perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example of Alice. She works at some job and makes some money.
Let’s consider a case when she does not know about FIRE or for some reason assumes that it is not achievable
(e.g. expects the stock market to stop growing). She spends some part of her salary
each month and with the remaining part she is free to do whatever she wishes. 
It was surprising to me that in such a situation spending a large portion of the remaining money just for fun
makes sense and it is even rational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Alice’s perspective, there are not that many options to go with her work. At some age, she will
start getting a pension and stop working. Before that she needs money, so she cannot leave the job.
Basically, her no-FIRE assumption leads to “I will likely work until governmental pension age”.
That’s optimistic case. In the worst case she could lose her job. That’s why I said spending “large” portion
of her money and not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them. From a rational perspective, she needs some emergency savings, but
they don’t have to be as aggressive as for FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under such conditions, it makes sense to try to get the most out of free time she has left (evenings,
weekends and vacation). That’s all what she has left (based on her assumptions) and she needs to maximize
utility of this time, i.e. to maximize happiness. Here we unfortunately leave our so far very formal framework,
because defining happiness is tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider a more concrete example.
Let’s say she has X EUR left after covering all necessary expenses for this month.
One option would be to invest this money and just leave them there. 
Another option would be to boost her happiness by somehow spending them. 
Here we assume that she already has a reasonable emergency fund and various insurances
(disability, medical). If FIRE is not possible, investing does not make sense.
The money will be just laying somewhere without positively affecting her life at all.
I agree that this can be perceived as an additional buffer, but we assume that she already
has a sufficient emergency fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically by investing she could spend the money later. E.g. if she exhausted all ways to
boost her happiness, shew could wait to discover new ones. However, the timeline in this case is still
very different from FIRE. Here it is much shorter - like the next vacation or saving for something expensive.
For FIRE - it is years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that I am not saying how she should spend them. Obviously she could go 100% consumerism
route and start buying a lot of expensive unneeded stuff. As “The science of wellbeing” course has
pointed out (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt;), this won’t
help her to become happier and even can make her unhappier. She could probably pay for experiences
(e.g. travel) or try to help others. However, here I just assume that there are some meaningful ways
to boost her happiness with spending money and Alice has a magical box telling her these ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this framework, as long as spending money boosts her happiness even a little, it is rational for her to use this opportunity
and spend the money. If there are no meaningful options left, she may save the money for some short time until
an opportunity arises. Anyway, she we will work until pension age and nothing can be done about this (from her perspective).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall visually we can represent this as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism/without_fire.png&quot; alt=&quot;a sample scale with happiness boost of various opportunities, showing number of opportunities ranked by their boost value.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise values are arbitrary.
How to evaluate each option is an art in itself, which we don’t even touch here.
Alice just goes through the opportunity list from top to the bottom and executes them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-exists-perspective&quot;&gt;“FIRE exists” perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s imagine that Alice discovers Mr. Money Mustache blog or somehow changes her mind about FIRE.
Now FIRE becomes viable for her and she may pursue it. 
How does this affect the framework outlined above?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much, FIRE is just another opportunity on her list with its own “happiness boost score”.
Again it is close to impossible to estimate it well (you probably have to trust your feelings and priorities),
but for simplicity we assume that Alice somehow magically can make this estimate.
Thus, the framework still works the same as before, there is just one more option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the picture becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism/with_fire.png&quot; alt=&quot;a sample scale with happiness boost of various opportunities, showing number of opportunities ranked by their boost value, including saving for FIRE.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically there are still opportunities, in which it makes sense to spend money to boost happiness.
However, at the same time there is now a new mega opportunity - saving for FIRE.
It functions as a lower bound for all other opportunities - with FIRE I expect to be
happy to a certain degree, thus, if I have some spare money and no better way to spend them (i.e. bringing more happiness),
I should invest them for FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like you are going to ask “hey, that’s all very cool, but what is the point?”.
So I am going to reply in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, this is a useful exercise to understand others better. I am reading “Search Inside Yourself” these days
and they talk a lot about taking other people perspective to understand them. Previously I personally was 
confused by people, who explicitly refused FIRE and continued their regular “shopping therapy” routines.
It may the case that they just don’t find FIRE realistic - likely they have never seen anyone who reached this state,
this also means going against the crowd and one becomes an outlier and in some sense a pioneer.
It is also funny that I can remember the times before I discovered FIRE. I definitely felt unhappy about
working for decades, but this unhappiness didn’t go anywhere. I just couldn’t find a solution, so I was 
slowly going into “ok, let’s at least have as much fun as I can” mode. Fortunately, I discovered FIRE
and this gave me proper perspective and I abandoned that route immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the happiness maximization framework with a list of opportunities also works for FIRE.
Are you not sure whether you should invest the money or spend them in some fancy way?
Then try to answer whether it will make you that much happier. I understand
that this is still a hard question, but it is a good first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy rational happiness maximization!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><summary type="html">I’ve noticed that consumerism makes sense if one assumes that Financial Independence is not achievable. Let’s look more into this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #7: true happiness</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-7-true-happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #7: true happiness" /><published>2019-08-08T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_7_true_happiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-7-true-happiness">&lt;p&gt;The new thought experiment! About happiness this time! Woohoo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concept&quot;&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;my last thought experiment post&lt;/a&gt; for
the description of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;before-we-start&quot;&gt;Before we start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, this time I feel quite excited and I was looking forward to the new experiment.
I am extremely curious what it is about. Somehow I started to really enjoy participating 
in them. I am reading “Search Inside Yourself” by Chade-Meng Tan these days and there they
write about “Journaling”. Basically writing down your thoughts as they are, without blocking them.
They claim that this allows you to understand yourself better and overall become happier.
Today I understood that SavingNinja experiments are like that!
So, the therapeutic effect is included! And it is completely for free! Ok, looks like I jumped to dumping my thoughts too
early, let’s actually have a look at the new experiment. I hope it is not scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-statement&quot;&gt;The statement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most people’s lives are filled with so much commotion. We’re constantly moving and thinking like an electrode jumping from atom to atom. There are very few moments when we experience true clarity, when we have a chance to really think clearly. These moments may come when reaching a mountain peak in the early hours of the morning or when you’re sitting up late one night and silently staring at the stars. Lots of life-changing decisions can be made in these moments; when you have the time to think about true happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So, for this Thought Experiment, I’d like you to create one of these moments for yourself. I’d like you to think, and I mean really think about what you want and need to make yourself and your family happy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What do you need to achieve real, true happiness? What are you aspiring to? Paint that perfect picture, you will need it as a guide whilst you make your way through life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment page is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-is-happiness-to-you&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (it includes links to answers of others, I definitely recommend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the word “commotion”. Let’s see the definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;commotion - a state of confused and noisy disturbance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, ok, that’s approximately what I guessed. Ok, reading further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;finished reading&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, this sounds really tricky. True happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have no clue, but I start to get vague ideas, so let’s go with something
and then see where this brings us (oh, this is so meta-meta level now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely would like more control in my life and a better guarantees for the
worst case scenario. It is hard to define control well, but I can give a couple of examples.
E.g. when I wake up one morning and I &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; go to work, but don’t feel like it at all.
I am not physically sick. I just don’t feel like working today. I would love to be able to
just say - “ok, a good day not to work” and just not to work. Currently, I can’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst-worst case is death. This I don’t consider much,
because I probably can’t affect it much either. So by the worst case scenario I mean something
like I lose my ability to earn money and then I don’t have enough to live.
I would like to know that
if something like this happens, I have enough to just be. I.e. I won’t need to be needed.
In some sense this is like an insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But both of these examples follow from my desire to reach FIRE. If I had to explain why
I want to reach FIRE, these would be the first two examples. This somewhat discredits
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, did I mention journaling in the book above? They claimed that one can understand themselves
and what they want better. So I should probably try that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that I definitely would like to be healthy. This is probably a precondition for
everything else. It is funny that this did not come as the first idea, but whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I started to derail, I will reread the statement again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like enough time and financial resources to satisfy my insatiable curiosity.
&amp;lt; I had to check the definition of “insatiable”, because I was not sure&amp;gt;. To be honest,
calling it financial resources is probably an overkill. I can definitely find plenty
of interesting stuff costing 0 or close to 0. But when considering the time, the situation is completely
different. I definitely would like more free time and just to do stuff for the sake of doing it
without any other (e.g. financial) incentives. I think this is called time affluence.
I suppose when I gradually lose it in my life, I start feeling bad and then notice
absence of time affluence, slowly regain it back and start feeling better again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is again just equivalent to “become FIRE”.
Oh, SavingNinja, you are putting me into a tricky situation here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then more communication with people would be nice. I feel like it is overall fun
(depends on people, but with some it is amazing), but I kind of lazy enough not to
try that hard to establish something with others. As a result, I don’t communicate often.
Occasionally it works out well and I feel very nice. I also have strong views (aka 
stubborn), so with some people it is just hard (not for me, I suppose, mostly
for them). This desire is probably coming from outside. I just heard from multiple
sources that this makes people happier (including the happiness course on Coursera,
I did 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;a proper review for it&lt;/a&gt;
 as well as 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary&quot;&gt;a brief summary&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I am really scared to reread this. It probably makes little sense.
It would be funny just to post this without rereading at all, but I need to 
at least fix my typos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also be very surprised if this experiment would really change my life dramatically.
It takes me ages to make a decision, but once I do that, it is very unlikely
that I will change it (see “strong views” above and also I need quite a few
arguments to make a decision, so it is unlikely that all of them become
void at the same time). Thus, changing my views is very
gradual process. This could be a trigger or the beginning of the shift, but
not an actual change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also scared that FIRE will lose its charm once I reach it.
Basically, now having free time could look so nice, because the time is scarce.
Once I have free time, what if this charm and magic just goes away due to absence of 
scarcity? Scary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeap, finding a perfect life partner would be great. Oh, perhaps even understanding what
“perfect” means would already be amazing. Oh, a funny observation, “understanding what
would make me happy would make me happy”. Technically I should be happy already :)
that’s like a recursive criterion of happiness, because I know that “understanding what
would make me happy” would make me happy. And since I know this I should be happy now.
Ok, at least this made me smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would say - health, FIRE with freedom and control coming out of it, 
a bunch of interesting people to talk to (who would inspire me),
an obviously great life partner (without whom I would not be able to imagine my life).
It is actually funny that it is quite a strong criterion: “without whom I would not be able
to imagine my life”. My worry is that I may be overshooting. Like the maximal level could be like
“having great time together”, but I ask for “not being able to imagine my life without”
and as a result refuse good relationships. Oh, how did it go into relationships?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt; rereading the statement again &amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also love to make people, who I care about, happy.
Try to improve their life and help them to make the best out of it.
This can mean challenging them or traveling together.
This does not mean making it as easy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also probably need acknowledgment from other people.
I.e. some positive feedback for what I am doing.
It might be interesting to do something for the sake of it and my own
joy, but so far I cannot imagine this. E.g. painting something which
no one else in the world would ever enjoy or find interesting. This is 
a valid activity and I can see how it could be pleasant, but somehow
I can’t imagine doing this at this stage. I would rather try to impress others.
In some sense this adds challenge or in the math terms - regularization. 
When doing it for myself, there are no limits or boundaries. Whatever I do is
the right thing. It can be tempting to choose the easy path.
For others, there is always some external limit, which I can’t cross,
otherwise they will refuse the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, also being able to use computer sustainably would be amazing as well.
So far I feel like no matter which approach I choose with my setup,
it works for some time and then I discover that actually some part of my body
does not like that approach. It is not that acute, but slowly it accumulates
and after some time I notice that something is fishy and “let’s start this game again”.
So somehow being sure that what I am doing with my computer setup is reasonably 
sustainable would be amazing! It is hard to imagine my life without a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I would like to spend more time in nature as well.
Perhaps more days without Internet. I occasionally spend a day without Internet at all.
I just turn off my router and that’s it. Somehow it feels very differently.
Easy and calm. Amazing. I definitely can’t explain that. So I would like to try
to have more of such days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also doing projects with others would be interesting (like a combination of my curiosity
and communication). Now I don’t have enough time for this (blink, blink at SavingNinja and
our plans for a game-project, I feel sorry for not having much progress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I just looked back and I wrote really a lot. I even feel a bit lazy to reread it.
Ok, I did reread it anyway. I did write a lot. Somehow it went mostly from “what I am scared of”,
but I think this is fine. I did say that I don’t have much clue what would make me really
happy. That’s also why I am trying to reach FIRE. This sounds like a good tool
for whatever I decide later. Also working in the office until 67 or so does not
go into that list for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I would like to point out that happiness course (which I already mentioned
above and even gave links to my reviews, it would be weird to give them again) thinks about happiness
somewhat differently. Basically, it is about (I am not looking into the reviews,
just doing this from memory) having enough money, having enough free time (time affluence),
deep social connections and doing kindness, being in the flow, good reference points
(not comparing yourself with others or at least not with wrong others), good sleep,
enough sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I hope you enjoyed it. This was challenging and I was in the flow for sure.
Thank you, SavingNinja for challenging me and bringing plenty of food for thought!
I am looking forward to what others will write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy discovering what makes you happy (without my recursive tricks above)!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;About me&quot;, &quot;Thought experiments&quot;]" /><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">The new thought experiment! About happiness this time! Woohoo!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I write this blog</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-i-write-this-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I write this blog" /><published>2019-08-06T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-06T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_i_write_this_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-i-write-this-blog">&lt;p&gt;I would like to go a bit meta and tell you how I write this blog. 
This includes somewhat technical details and just general process.
You can treat this is an overview of a life of a post in this blog - from an idea to being published.
Thus, please let me welcome you to the backstage, but take your shoes off first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideas&quot;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every post in this blog starts with an idea. As you might have noticed, I don’t limit myself to any
particular topic and this is also true for my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I collect ideas for posts non-stop. Whenever I get something vaguely resembling an idea for a post,
I just take a note of it and add it to my list. The bar at this stage is extremely low.
Basically, I just write it down (with enough info to be able to understand what I meant and occasionally
possible ways to develop it) and forget. I use my “the worst that can happen” principle here (which I already
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-worst-that-can-happen&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; before). In the worst case, I just change my
mind later and delete the idea. Thus, my goal here is to just collect something, evaluation will happen later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my idea-collection phase (I call it “catching”). Overall, I like this process a lot,
because it is hard to get an idea on purpose, but they do come often by themselves especially when walking
or doing something unrelated. As a result, when I feel like writing a post, but don’t have any idea in mind,
I can just look at my list and something immediately resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea list has a lot of items at this stage. As I said, the bar is extremely low. 
I would say I have ~100 items there. Some are probably not actionable (the bar is unbelievably low here, did I say this already?).
But there are 10-20 ones which I could just start writing about right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this has some disadvantages. The list works like a stack. Thus, the oldest items
just stay there and normally I don’t reach them at all. Normally I find something interesting already in the beginning of the list.
With time I add more items and it gets even less likely to reach the oldest items.
I could probably randomize the order, but this is not a problem for now. Just an observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also publish some ideas as ideas in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/queue&quot;&gt;“Future post ideas” list&lt;/a&gt;. As you might have
noticed I don’t do this that often. Theoretically you could check out my ideas there and I would notice
in my statistics that some of them are more popular than others and then write about the more popular ones sooner.
In practice I haven’t got that much signal this way so far. Also publishing ideas feels cumbersome, because there are 
too many of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-minutes-of-post&quot;&gt;First minutes of post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then at some point I feel like writing a post. If I don’t have anything in mind, I will go through
my list and find something. Here I again use “The worst that can happen principle”. Basically, I just
sit down and start writing whatever I like without rereading or correcting much. The idea is to get
something out. Polishing is not a goal. In the worst case, I will reread it at some point and
just delete the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have the first reasonable draft, I put it into “baking” stage. This should have been named
more like “aging” (like wine), but I like “baking”. I just leave the draft for at least 
a week without looking at it at all. The point is to completely forget about it. This is 
surprisingly easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;publishing&quot;&gt;Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing&quot;&gt;Choosing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually publish 2 posts per week these days - one on Tuesdays and one during the weekend.
This is completely arbitrary. I definitely started with publishing randomly, but having some
system helps to develop a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say it is Tuesday and I need to publish a post. I just go into my folder with drafts
and check whatever I have there. During good times I have 5-6 drafts at the same time
(i.e. posts for the next 3 weeks already baking). During average times only 1-2 drafts
(i.e. enough only for this week). Nowadays I am in the later stage. I should try to 
get to the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple benefits with having 5-6 drafts at any point in time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;posts are being baked for much longer (~3 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if something unexpected happens and I won’t have time to write new stuff, I will 
have enough posts in my reserve to get by for some time. On average publishing a draft is much faster
than writing a draft. You can treat this as my emergency post fund.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when choosing what to post, it is easier to find something resonating with me 
when I choose out of 6 posts (instead of 1 or 2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-baking-processing&quot;&gt;Post-baking processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I selected something, I just go through it and fix whatever I don’t like.
Very often the structure is weird or there are a bunch of typos or weird language constructs.
Funny enough - this is impossible to see just after writing a draft and this almost screams
at me when I reread the post after “baking” it. If the post is too bad or I find a major flow
(e.g. false assumption), it can get deleted at this stage or postponed for additional improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this stage, the post gets published! Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-publish&quot;&gt;Post-publish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I also tweet about almost each published post in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;my twitter account&lt;/a&gt;.
This is a good exercise for my mind to clearly identify the gist of my post. If you are into Twitter, this might
be a good way to learn about the new posts. There is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml&quot;&gt;an RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve
heard that Google Reader is dead, so I don’t know how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I also publish on Reddit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;my account&lt;/a&gt;).
I do this only for posts which are relevant to the reddits I am aware of.
There people can comment and I definitely enjoy this. Very often they propose corrections (e.g. I was thinking
that capital gain tax with solidarity tax in Germany was 26.25% (i.e. 25% * 105%) and it was pointed out that
it is 26.375% (i.e. 25% * 105.5%)). In such cases I do add corrections to my posts. Sometimes this involves redoing
all the calculations and graphs (a lot of fun - irony^100).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-details&quot;&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; framework to run my blog. I already &lt;a href=&quot;/post/jekyll-post-url-not-working&quot;&gt;touched
the benefits of using Jekyll in an older post&lt;/a&gt;. Since I am into
programming, Jekyll’s approach fits me well. My blog has “source code”, the same way as programs in programming.
I also need to “compile” it to produce the actual final website. As a result, I can automate or simplify
a bunch of changes. Theoretically, I could completely change the design and then recompile and all
the pages would use the new design. Similarly with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/about/&quot;&gt;“About” page&lt;/a&gt; - yes, it took me
40 minutes to set it up, but now when I add a new post, I just mention its category and everything 
else happens completely automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have already guessed, I also use git for version control of the blog.
Theoretically this is not necessary for blog posts (especially since there is only me
writing them), but as I said with Jekyll there is some programming involved, so I definitely
prefer having git versions. This way if something goes wrong, I could easily go to a previous version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love this feeling of seeing how something great and sizable is made step by step, a little bit
at a time. Occasionally I look at my git log or blame and enjoy this feeling. This is also a good source
of raw data for statistics about me writing this blog (e.g. how much and when).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-last-section-normally-this-would-be-conclusions-but-there-is-nothing-to-conclude-in-this-post&quot;&gt;The last section (normally this would be conclusions, but there is nothing to conclude in this post)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hoped you enjoyed me giving you a peek into how this blog is getting created. That is a brief look
behind the curtains. Please don’t forget your shoes.
I definitely plan to continue with similar posts in the future (e.g. “Why I write this blog” and “Why I 
believe that everyone should write a blog”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any feedback, questions or suggestions, you are welcome to contact me with whatever channel you 
prefer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;,
email - merelycurious protonmail.com). If you are unsure whether you should write to me, please use “The worst that can happen”
principle. These days I don’t get that much feedback (I am going forward pretty blindly with the blog, mostly following
my curiosity), so I will
(with high probability) enjoy your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy going meta in your lives, folks!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="meta" /><category term="about_me" /><summary type="html">I would like to go a bit meta and tell you how I write this blog. This includes somewhat technical details and just general process. You can treat this is an overview of a life of a post in this blog - from an idea to being published. Thus, please let me welcome you to the backstage, but take your shoes off first.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chrome Incognito, FlixBus and 5 EUR</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito-flixbus-and-5-eur" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chrome Incognito, FlixBus and 5 EUR" /><published>2019-08-03T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito_flixbus_and_5_eur</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito-flixbus-and-5-eur">&lt;p&gt;Quite a peculiar story happened to me recently.
I was buying a FlixBus ticket for 24.99 EUR. I already had it in my “cart” and I had 
30 minutes to buy it before the cart expires. Then I started double checking other
details and in the end it expired (actually couple seconds before I pressed “pay”).
I tried to buy it again, but now the price was 29.99 EUR, i.e. 5 EUR more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workaround&quot;&gt;Workaround&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh, I was confused and surprised. They definitely knew that I am interested in this ticket.
I already almost bought it once and, yes, I still wanted to buy it.
But increasing the price by 5 EUR because of that would be mean.
Fortunately, I knew that they can recognize me (by my browser session) and perhaps if I start fresh
the price would be different. E.g. they could set a “cookie” in my browser saying
something like “hey, this chap tried to buy this ticked already, let’s do +5 EUR, cheers!”.
This cookie would be absent in my new session. Thus, I tried to open the same page
in a Chrome Incognito tab. Guess what - the price was the old one - 24.99 EUR.
They could potentially correlate my new session with my old one (e.g. by IP, time and my computer hardware),
but that would be cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I don’t remember precisely, but I feel like I refreshed the old session page as well after seeing 24.99 EUR
in the incognito tab and it was still showing 29.99 EUR. This is actually a very important detail to understand
how this happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypotheses&quot;&gt;Hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;someone-is-being-mean&quot;&gt;Someone is being mean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, this could be intended. Theoretically, FlixBus almost made +5 EUR out of nowhere
(ok, out of my pocket to be precise). It is easy to see how this could benefit them.
However, this would be pretty mean and I would be very surprised if this is the case.
The approach does not look very sustainable, someone would definitely notice and complain.
Also it is better to assume positive intention and give benefit of doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bugs-bugs-bugs&quot;&gt;Bugs, bugs, bugs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit more plausible explanation is that this is just a bug. So far this is my best guess.
As far as I know, FlixBus uses “adaptive” pricing. I.e. if someone buys a ticket, the next 
ticket can cost more. This tries to adapt to the actual demand (people buy more tickets to
some destination, demand must be high, so the price can higher too). Airlines go crazy
with this stuff. I haven’t observed FlixBus increasing and decreasing their prices
frequently, but airlines (based on my experience) do this a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, when “almost” my ticket (24.99 EUR one) was in my “cart”, FlixBus could already raise the price for
the next one to 29.99 EUR. They could just assume that the first ticket is almost sold.
And then when the first ticket “expires”, they need to decrease the price back.
Perhaps there is some race condition here and I happened to open the state when my old not-bought expired ticket
was still in the cart (but in the reality it wasn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the question is why incognito helped. I could imagine them having multiple servers
and perhaps some caching. Theoretically, my new tab could have hit some other server,
which was already aware that 24.99 EUR ticket came back. Or the server serving the old
session could have cached 29.99 EUR (but caching price pages sounds weird).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that my hypothesis is somewhat weak, but, hey, the info I have is limited as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experiment&quot;&gt;Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, originally I didn’t plan to experiment with this, but now I am curious.
The plan is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a couple tickets to “cart”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let them expire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check their price again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open incognito and check price there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I observe the increase, I could create a new Chrome profile, check the price and then and inject the cookie from the old profile
into the new one and check the price again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to add Berlin - Munich tickets to my “cart”. Unfortunately, one cannot add two tickets on the same day in the same
direction (which makes sense, but it is inconvenient for my experiment), so I added 3 tickets for each day from 21st of August to 
23rd of August. FlixBus shows when there are 0, 1 or 2 tickets left at this price, so I varied this parameter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21st of August - price 27.98 and 2 seats left at this price
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 21st of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;22nd of August - price 27.98 and 1 seat left at this price
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 22nd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;23rd of August - price 27.99 and no additional messages.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 23rd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall my cart was 83.95 EUR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_summary.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cart overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I waited for ~20 minutes and checked from an incognito window.
Only in the second case (22nd of August) price grew to 30.98 EUR.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;22nd of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes sense (they said I took the last seat at the previous price).
On the 21st of August they say that 1 seat is left at this price, but the price is the same.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;21st of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 23rd nothing has changed.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;23rd of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I let the cart expire.
Funny fact: they say “1 minute&lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;” when only 1 minute is left:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/1_minutes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;1 minute**s**&amp;quot; expiry warning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably so few people reach this point (and observe the page while doing that), that no one complained or it is
not worth fixing. Yeap, a minor nit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fun fact: the number turns red when it is 0:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/0_minutes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;0 minutes&amp;quot; expiry warning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally - expired:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/session_expired.png&quot; alt=&quot;Session expired message&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I checked all the prices from the same browser window, i.e. same session.
All prices were the same as they were when I started my experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 21st of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 22nd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 23rd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e. I did not observe any price increase in any of the cases.
I was just able to rebuild my “cart” with exactly the same prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_summary.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rebuilt cart with exactly the same prices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not able to reproduce the issue.
Obviously they could do this trick only once in a while to prevent someone like me detecting this.
My gut feeling is that this is a weird bug due to multiple system part interaction (e.g. caching or distributed servers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flixbus-opinion&quot;&gt;FlixBus opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have asked them on Twitter (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_/status/1157727264647372801&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;). Not sure whether they
will reply (that would be very unpleasant to debug for someone there
especially based on the scarce data I have here and me being unable to reproduce it), but let’s see.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="funny" /><category term="bugs" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Quite a peculiar story happened to me recently. I was buying a FlixBus ticket for 24.99 EUR. I already had it in my “cart” and I had 30 minutes to buy it before the cart expires. Then I started double checking other details and in the end it expired (actually couple seconds before I pressed “pay”). I tried to buy it again, but now the price was 29.99 EUR, i.e. 5 EUR more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dangers of “Work hard, play hard”</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers-of-work-hard-play-hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dangers of &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot;" /><published>2019-07-30T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers_of_work_hard_play_hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers-of-work-hard-play-hard">&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered that people use expression &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot; as a way to
explain treating themselves something nice. The expressions itself often comes from
their workplace. At first, this felt ok to me, but when taking into account
Financial Independence / Early Retirement, I can see that one’s employer
can be incentivized in one following this expression. Let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work hard, play hard. Sounds pretty innocent and reasonable. You do a great job, 
you get to enjoy its results and “rest”. It also seems to make sense to use your time 
as efficiently as possible in both cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when working - to improve your results,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when resting - to rest better and to have more fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often “Play hard” part involves
spending a lot of money. E.g. one could consider vacation nearby (e.g.
if they live in Germany, some city in Germany or neighboring country) or some exotic
far away destination (like Costa Rica). In the process one can say “I worked very hard, now I 
deserve playing hard, so Costa Rica it is”. You see the principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-comes-fire&quot;&gt;Here comes FIRE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Work hard, play hard” makes sense before one knows about FIRE. I have to admit 
that at some point in my life even I used “Play hard” part to decide whether to spend money.
However in the context of FIRE, it is very easy to see dangers of this
expression and why it can be good for one’s employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-1-obvious-one-work-hard-for-productivity&quot;&gt;Incentive #1 (obvious one): Work Hard for productivity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employers love when one works hard. They are extremely incentivized
to make this the case. The harder their employee works, the better the results are,
the more money employer makes. Normally one doesn’t get all the benefit which they
produce at work propagated back to them. Thus, even after a raise or a bonus for good
work, the employer still benefits from one’s hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-2-another-obvious-one-play-hard-for-rest&quot;&gt;Incentive #2 (another obvious one): Play Hard for rest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to work hard, you need to recharge your energy well.
Otherwise, you will burn out. Thus, based on the previous incentive, employers
also love when you rest very well and recharge before coming to work. Thus, if one
spends their personal time for their own very effective rest, this is very positive
for their employer (better performance, more money) and somewhat positive to the person
(somewhat more money theoretically, burnout sucks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-3-surprising-play-hard-to-spend&quot;&gt;Incentive #3 (surprising): Play Hard to spend&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is hard to notice without FIRE. Basically, imagine that your salary is magically 
2 million EUR per month. After couple months, you could likely quit, since you
will have enough money in your stash (not for getting 2kk EUR monthly during your FIRE, but still enough).
And now imagine that your employer manages to convince you to “Play Hard”. Heck, you
are making 2 million EUR per month. You can spend 1.8 million EUR every month and
still save 200k. You will still save more than majority of people. Very few people earn that much,
so you deserve this! Then you find many fancy ways to spend a lot of money. Inflate your
lifestyle. After vacation on a yacht in the Caribbean and an amazing 10 room apartment
with a jacuzzi (or 5), having a vacation in Stuttgart or living in a studio apartment
feels hard. And now you can’t quit anymore. You need a lot of money to support such
a lifestyle. By saving 10% of your income, you need ~51.4 years to save for your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably don’t get payed 2kk EUR monthly (otherwise, wow, I am proud that you
read this). However, the same approach applies to any salary. I just exaggerated the example
to make it easier to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-4-questionable-play-hard-to-not-grow&quot;&gt;Incentive #4 (questionable): Play Hard to not grow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you don’t know about “Play Hard” and just work.
In the evening, you tinker with various projects, learn new skills.
In some sense, this is good for your employer, because theoretically
you may become more productive. But at the same time,
this makes your more valuable on the job market. The raises are usually 
lower than starting bonuses (i.e. one will likely end up with more
money by changing a job instead of getting a raise). Thus, in this case
there is a risk that you will leave your employer. E.g. some other
company notices your projects and makes a more generous offer. 
Or you can even start a startup. I feel like the risk of losing you is higher
for the employer than the benefits from your learning. And with
“Play Hard” you are directed to just have fun without long lasting
effects (except rest and spending money). I understand that for some
of us, “playing” may involve learning or tinkering, but in the general
case this is considered work and normally people wouldn’t use this activities
for their leisure time. Even though it would make them much happier
(e.g. due to being in the flow, according to “The science of wellbeing” course, 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;summary of which I already posted&lt;/a&gt;
).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, if you notice yourself using “I worked hard, I may play hard” argument, especially to spend
more money, try to stop for a moment and reconsider. Is this really what you want? Is this really
beneficial for you and your life? I am pretty sure there are enough cases when it is, but your
employer may be heavy incentivized in you following this expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another funny way to understand this expression could have been “Work Hard” = “Save for FIRE”,
“Play Hard” = “Enjoy FIRE”, but even this does not work well. This seams to involve life style
inflation and implicitly says that your FIRE saving phase sucks and you won’t 
“work” during FIRE. It doesn’t have to be this way. Ideally your lifestyle shouldn’t change much.
You just replace ordinary job time (i.e. 40h a week) with some other activities, which you enjoy more.
This can be whatever you like (even just continue working).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I would rephrase the expression as “Work reasonably ok, analyze incentives, consider saving for
FIRE, enjoy your life in the ways you like (this does not have to be rest or expensive “play”, but it may”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy effective work and conscious rest!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;, &quot;Frugality&quot;]" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">I’ve discovered that people use expression &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot; as a way to explain treating themselves something nice. The expressions itself often comes from their workplace. At first, this felt ok to me, but when taking into account Financial Independence / Early Retirement, I can see that one’s employer can be incentivized in one following this expression. Let’s see how.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physics, acceleration and FIRE\(^2\)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-squared" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physics, acceleration and FIRE\(^2\)" /><published>2019-07-28T01:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T01:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_squared</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-squared">&lt;p&gt;Financial Independence / Early Retirement is about reaching a state, in which you get enough passive income to live.
Let’s say you get \(Y\) EUR each month. The overall money you get over time is \( M = Y * t \), where \(t\) is time.
This resembles a physics equation for movement with constant speed (i.e. no acceleration).
Let’s explore this similarity and try to add acceleration to FIRE and get FIRE\(^2\) (FIRE squared, I just made this
name up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;physics-prelude&quot;&gt;Physics prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an object moves with a constant speed \(V\) in one dimensional space,
then its position can be obtained by \(x = V t + x_0\), where \(t\) is time
and \(x_0\) is the initial position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case above assumes no acceleration (the speed is constant).
If we have constant acceleration the equation becomes \(x = \frac{a t^2}{2} + V t + x_0\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-to-fire&quot;&gt;Back to FIRE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In physics the object moves by \(V\) for each unit of time.
In FIRE one gets \(Y\) EUR each month (i.e. unit of time).
Basically, if we denote cumulative number of money obtained through FIRE as \(C\),
the equation is similar to the equation above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = Y t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s try to add acceleration here.
The equation becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = \frac{a t^2}{2} + Y t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
Y = a t + \text{&lt;initial value&gt;} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean? 
The first month we get \(Y\). The second month we get already \(Y + a\).
The third - \(Y + 2a\) and so on. In other words, the amount we get from
FIRE each month (our speed) should grow by \(a\) each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s check whether equation above works as we expect. At \( t = 1 \) 
the value is \( C = \frac{a}{2} + Y \), but we expect only \( Y \). This is likely, because the
speed in physics grows continuously, while here in FIRE the process is discrete.
E.g. for \( t = 0.5 \), the formula above gives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
Y = 0.5 a  + \text{&lt;initial value&gt;} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, let’s try to build our own equation then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At time \( t = 0 \), we have 0 EUR overall and our monthly income is \( Y \).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 1 \), we get \( Y \), overall we have \( Y \) and our monthly income becomes \( Y + a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 2 \), we get \( Y + a \), overall \( 2Y + a \), income \( Y + 2a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 3 \), we get \( Y + 2a \), overall \( 3Y + 3a \), income \( Y + 3a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 4 \), we get \( Y + 3a \), overall \( 4Y + 6a \), income \( Y + 4a \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see the equation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
C = t Y + \text{&lt;something&gt;} \cdot a %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first we add no \( a \), then \( a \), then \( 2a \) and so on.
Thus, this is just a sum
of arithmetic progression. The formula for the general case is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S = (x_1 + x_n) \frac{n}{2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i.e. sum of the first \( x_1 \) and last \( x_n \) elements multiplied by quantity \( n \) and divided by two).
In our case it is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(0 + t-1) \frac{t}{2} = (t-1)\frac{t}{2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final formula becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = t Y + (t-1)\frac{t}{2} a&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under \( t = 4 \), we get \( 4 Y + 3 \cdot \frac{4}{2} a = 4 Y + 6 a \). Thus, it matches our manual calculations above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;even-further-back&quot;&gt;Even further back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am curious to see how much money one needs to build such FIRE with acceleration (FIRE\(^2\)).
In other words, what kind of safe withdrawal rate one needs for this (could be denotes as SWR\(^2\)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that we want our acceleration to be \( A \) and we start with 0 speed at first.
After the first month we get \( A \) units of money. Under 4% SWR, we would need \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot A \) EUR overall.
After the second month we get \( 2A \) EUR. In the normal FIRE we would need \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 2 \cdot A \) EUR overall
to achieve such withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this approach does not bring us far. Instead let’s say that in the first month we get \( A_1 \) EUR
and in the second month we want to get \( A_2 = A_1 + 1 \) EUR. This means that after \( A_1 \) our stash
should grow such that it starts producing 1 EUR more. Under 4% SWR one needs \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 1 = 300 \) EUR to
get 1 EUR per month. Thus, \( A_1 \) should be 300 EUR. Now we can try to extend this further.
We want \( A_2 = A_1 + A \) EUR. Thus, \( A_1 \) should be \( 300A \).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider an example. Our monthly FIRE target is \( 300A \) EUR. We have \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 300 \cdot A = 300^2 A \) EUR overall.
After the first month we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;300^2 A \cdot \frac{0.04}{12} = 300 A&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reinvest them. Now our stash becomes
\( 300^2 A + 300 A \) EUR. In the second month, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(300^2 A + 300 A) \frac{0.04}{12} = 301 A&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oops, we wanted \( 600 A \). So it feels like the compound interest works differently from the physics motion equation.
Let’s say our principal is \( P \) EUR and it grows by 4% each year, then after \( n \) years we will have
\( P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \).
If we don’t spend anything, our monthly FIRE income after \( n \) years will be \( P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12} \).
In other words, in contrast to the motion equation, here the time \( n \) is in the power. Previously, it was just square multiplied. This is why our analogy breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we know that \( Y = a t \). We can plug income from the above as \( Y \) here and see the acceleration (for simplicity we switch units to years here):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = a n = P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a = \frac{ P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12} }{n}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words the acceleration is not constant, it grows as well.
In some sense, the real 4% is even better than the constant acceleration case above.
If we want \( Y \) to be \( 2A \), we need \( 2 A \cdot 12 \cdot 25 \) EUR stash. 
Let’s say our initial stash supports \( Y = A \), i.e. it is \( 12 \cdot 25 \cdot A \). 
We know that in \( n \) years it will be \( 12 \cdot 25 \cdot A \cdot 1.04 ^ n \). 
Thus, let’s find \( n \), such that \( Y = 2 A \), i.e. the stash of \( 2 * A * 12 * 25 \) EUR.
This is just \( 1.04 ^ n = 2 \), i.e. \( n = 17.673 \) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=1.04%5En+%3D+2&quot;&gt;wolfram alpha&lt;/a&gt;). That’s a long time, but when we want \( Y = 3 A \), \( n \) becomes 28.011.
I.e. the jump from \( Y = 2 A \) to \( Y = 3 A \) takes us ~10 years, while the jump from \( A \) to \( 2 A \) takes 17 years.
For \( 1000 A \), \( n \) is 176.125, while for \( 1001 A \), it is 176.151, i.e. one needs only ~10 days to go from
\( Y = 1000 A \) to \( 1001 A \), because the acceleration of compounding is not constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can visualize this well with a plot. Let’s draw \( Y \) for both cases (linear and compounding):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
Linear is much higher.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, linear is doing much better job at first. There is not much money to work in the compounding case yet.
However, if we look further right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_100.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 100 on x axis and compounding almost reaches linear.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding starts to reach linear. Even further right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_200.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 200 on x axis and compounding sky-rockets.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And kaboom! Compounding case just skyrockets.
Further to the right, it looks like linear is just flat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_300.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 300 on x axis and linear looks completely flat.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, the fact that acceleration is not constant feels now obvious. 
Basically, when one has more money, compounding growth has more effect, because each euro works separately. 
While in the physics motion equation, the speed is just time multiplied by acceleration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, building such FIRE scheme when one each months gets \( A \) more money
is not possible with the compounding growth. The compounding growth grows
faster than that scheme (it just starts slow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a bit sad that my attempt to define FIRE\(^2\) and SWR\(^2\) didn’t work out,
because the real thing is in some sense cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-follow-up&quot;&gt;Possible follow-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t workout, because the time goes into power. However, there is a way (logarithm) to move
from exponent to linear. Thus, I could theoretically consider logarithm of the monthly income and try
to do exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><summary type="html">Financial Independence / Early Retirement is about reaching a state, in which you get enough passive income to live. Let’s say you get \(Y\) EUR each month. The overall money you get over time is \( M = Y * t \), where \(t\) is time. This resembles a physics equation for movement with constant speed (i.e. no acceleration). Let’s explore this similarity and try to add acceleration to FIRE and get FIRE\(^2\) (FIRE squared, I just made this name up).</summary></entry></feed>