<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-08T13:07:45+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 11) - Neuroscience</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-11-neuroscience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 11) - Neuroscience" /><published>2019-12-08T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-08T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_11_neuroscience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-11-neuroscience">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but steadily…
Lecture 11, Neuroscience - part 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time you heard about neuroscience, now something in your head has changed and you remember that you
heard about neuroscience before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;memory&quot;&gt;Memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;super-memory&quot;&gt;Super memory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Wiltshire - an autistic savant. He can draw a very precise city view only after looking from an airplane
for some time. Savants take spacial tours through their memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mechanism&quot;&gt;Mechanism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory (learning) happens (to the best of our knowledge) in synapses. People used to assume that each new
memory leads to a new neuron. That is learning was perceived as equal to growing new neurons. Then people 
discovered synapses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is synaptic plasticity. When your presynaptic neuron fires a lot in a given time, eventually this will
cause a stronger response in the post synaptic neuron. I.e. a simplified version of Hebbian Plasticity -
neurons that fire together - wire together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excitating neurotransmitter is glutamate. It is excitatory and information is transmitted in the brain through 
activation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-term-potentiation&quot;&gt;Long term potentiation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long term potentiation (LTP) - getting more output for the same input. This can be achieved through e.g.
releasing more glutamate, reacting stronger in each of receptors, having more receptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a way for post-synaptic neuron to communicate back - retrograde neurotransmitter, e.g. nitric oxide gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hippocampus is the site of memory and LTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is adult neurogenesis and adult plasticity. In the last 20 years it was discovered that adult brain
forms new neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM - person with their hippocampi surgically removed. As a result he could no longer form any new memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But LTP happens all over the brain e.g. for motor and emotion memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTP can also go wrong, e.g. post traumatic stress disorder, when context brings undesired memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ltp-disruption&quot;&gt;LTP disruption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also mechanics for intentional disrupting LTP:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hypoglemic states (i.e. when one is really hungry) lead to insulin cascades, which in turn reduces LTP.
In other words, if you starve, it is not a good time to remember something, but to find food instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stress hormones - improve short term memory (e.g. one may be able to remember tinniest details after
a car crash as if in slow motion). However, if the impact is chronic, this damages LTP and memory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alcohol directly disrupts LTP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;networks--inhibition&quot;&gt;Networks &amp;amp; inhibition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you connect each neuron to e.g. 10k others and overall you have 100B of them, small changes in each
synapse start having large effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be random and spontaneous generation of signal.
It is important for the brain to filter out the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to consider neurons as groups instead. They also have capability to inhibit. A neuron can
inhibit itself. This allows temporal sharpening. A neuron can inhibit its neighbors:
“this is my signal, ignore my neighbors”. This creates spatial sharpening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be fast sharp pain and dull aching throbbing pain. There are two types of neurons and each type
is responsible for each kind of pain. Fast pain generates slow pain. Slow pain can inhibit first spike
of fast pain. If you get stung by a scorpion, the fast pain forces you to pay immediate attention, perhaps
the scorpion is still there. But there is no sense to keep this forever. Instead slow pain comes to remind you
that you still have the issue and have to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also allows retinal cells to be responsible for specific types of receptive fields.
Each neuron in your eye just gets a certain angle of light. This allows e.g. edge and contrast detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you activate a neuron in your retina, you get spatiotopic (oriented and aligned in a similar way)
field in the back of your visual cortex.
This was detected by tracing back which neurons a given retina neuron was connected to. Then this has been 
repeated for the next level. However, no single neuron activation was propagated. Instead a group of neurons
forming a line lighted up a neuron in the next layer. This was e.g. a neuron responsive to a vertical line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can construct visual world in layers by extracting features. The further you get, the higher order
abstractions you create (e.g. orange, banana). However, no one has found orange neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can simplify your brain to a neural network. Once a neuron is activated, it doesn’t know where the input came
from. I.e. it is a one-of function. So you can have concepts and categories. E.g. you have separate neurons
for impressionist painters. Then all of them are connected to one neuron. This one neuron can represent
impressionism. This is also how you remember stuff. You first remember a category and then try to narrow it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotionally salient memories last longer.
Context (like emotion) can get represented neurally too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is encoded in such a neural network, not a single neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;variation&quot;&gt;Variation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory variation can come from variation in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much glutamate gets released&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how strongly post-synaptic receptors respond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ways in which neural networks are constructed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result there is spectrum from HW to Stephen Wiltshire.
We are in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;autonomic-nervous-system&quot;&gt;Autonomic Nervous System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It controls anything that happens automatically.
E.g. heart beating, digesting, goosebumps, orgasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nervous system can be divided into Central and Peripheral.
Peripheral divides into Somatic and Autonomic.
Somatic system is responsible for transferring sensory information from periphery to Central Nervous System
(CNS) and voluntary control (e.g. moving muscles). It is fast and myelinated (covered with 
myelin which allows faster signal propagation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic - moves organs, unmyelinated and, thus, slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;parts&quot;&gt;Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic system is further divided into Sympathetic and Parasympathetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sympathetic&quot;&gt;Sympathetic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for arousal, alertness, emergency, flight or fight.
Releases norepinephrine (NE) into target organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;parasympathetic&quot;&gt;Parasympathetic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for growth, repair, calm vegetative function.
Releases acetylcholine (ACh) into target organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;Interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sympathetic and Parasympathetic have opposing functions.
Homeostasis - dynamic balance between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one exception - in male reproductive system they work together. Erection is controlled by 
Parasympathetic (and that’s why one needs to be stress free). Then Sympathetic overtakes and culminates
in ejaculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of erectile dysfunction - 60% of cases are due to stress and not organic basis in the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premature ejaculation - transition from Parasympathetic to Sympathetic happens too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;effects&quot;&gt;Effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Parasympathetic system is active, immune system works. In Sympathetic - contrary.
As a result, it is easier to get sick when you are stressed out (Sympathetic gets activated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NE &amp;amp; ACh can inhibit and excite depending on the organ. E.g. in case of heart, there is excitatory NE reception
and, thus, it is excited by NE. Gastrointestinal tract has inhibitory NE receptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulation&quot;&gt;Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center of regulation of Autonomic Nervous System is hypothalamus.
Even reptiles have it.
Then there is limbic system, which is responsible for emotions in mammals.
As a result, seeing someone you hate can cause sympathetic response through limbic system (emotion) and then
hypothalamus.
In primates, cortex is responsible for thoughts and memories. As a result, just a thought can cause
a sympathetic response (from cortex to limbic system and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when you think about a test, this activates your cortex, then limbic system, then hypothalamus
(so-called triune system of the brain). This cases sympathetic response. It can be similar to a reptile’s body
response to losing blood, but caused only by your thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic Nervous System is highly plastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biofeedback can be used to cure high blood pressure. You think of something pleasant. This decreases blood 
pressure. You repeat. Get further decrease. This makes the connection between this cortical thought and 
parasympathetic activation even stronger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Slowly but steadily… Lecture 11, Neuroscience - part 2.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 10) - Neuroscience</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-10-neuroscience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 10) - Neuroscience" /><published>2019-12-03T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_10_neuroscience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-10-neuroscience">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 10, Neuroscience - part 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;broader-context&quot;&gt;Broader context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course tries to show how various sciences answer “why chicken crossed the road”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evolution - how behavior evolved, why it is adaptive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;molecular genetics - genes controlling the evolution, how they change over time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;behavioral genetics - what individual genes are responsible for variation in behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ethology - studying behavior in nature, stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we consider neuroscience - what happens in brain before the behavior and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Chief function of the body is to carry the brain around. (attributed in Internet to Thomas A. Edison)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nervous-system--brain&quot;&gt;Nervous system &amp;amp; brain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nervous system is divided into central and peripheral. Central consists of brain and spinal cord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stem - responsible for communication with spinal cord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cerebellum - motor movements (especially when learning new stuff and correcting mistakes).
There is a peculiar experiment with prism glasses (everything appears normal, but in reality shifted
to the side). When wearing such glasses, one struggles with touching a target, because their brain
calculates object position as if there were no glasses. After some time (~minutes) one gets used to the glasses
and learns to touch the object as precisely as without glasses before. I.e. their brain learned 
how to correct for the shift. Once one takes off the glasses, they have the same “problem” again, but in the
other direction, and it takes time to autocorrect back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cortex
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;frontal lobe - plans actions, controls movements, each body part has its own part here and they
are located the same way as in the body.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;parietal lobe - sensory touch info. Area per body part can differ, e.g. fingertips are overrepresented.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;temporal lobe - auditory info + memory formation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;occipital lobe - visual info (back of the brain)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;limbic system
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hippocampus - forming new memories.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;amygdala - fear and anxiety - sweat of scared people (experiment described in a previous lecture)
lights up amygdala.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hypothalamus &amp;amp; pituitary gland - hormone secretion&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joke about 4 F’s of brain - flight, fight, feeding and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spinal cord has specialized areas too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peripheral system - all motor and sensory nerves + nerves for heartbeat, digestion, breathing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brain-cells&quot;&gt;Brain cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago Ramón y Cajal is considered by some a grandfather of the modern neurobiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before people thought of a brain as a web. He stained individual cells in the brain with black
and drew pictures of them. This way he investigated brain structure on cellular level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cell examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;90% of cells in brain are glia (means glue).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;astrocytes supply nutrients to neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;myelin wraps around neuron wires and makes the signal go faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;microglia - immune system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neurons - computational units (100B in average, each has 10k synapses-connections).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neuron&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consists of dendrites (inputs), nucleus (cell core), soma (cell body), axon hillock (start of output),
axon (output) and terminal (end of output branch).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuron is binary (on or off) instead of gradual (i.e. there is no middle level of activation). This helps to keep
resting potential. Sending of information happens through movement of ions (charged chemicals).
Neuron keeps itself quiet by keeping positive ions outside of the cell by using pumps.
Net charge inside is as a result negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When dendrites receive neurotransmitter, channels for positive ions are opened. This changes the charge.
If there is a lot of positive charge, neuron may fire further. If there is enough, channels on axon
hillock open to let more positive ions in, this creates a positive feedback loop.
Positive ions in the terminal trigger sending the signal further to the next neuron.
As it was said above, this is also binary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stop, cell opens other channels to let some positive ions out.
Axon terminal stores large amounts of neurotransmitter packaged in vesicles (discrete structures).
After that a channel can be opened in the next neuron to let ions in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurotransmitter might induce transcription factor.
Neurotransmitters are located in terminals.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dopamine - commonly associated with reward, pleasure, but it has many other functions too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;epinephrine (adrenalin) - involved in flight or fight response&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;norepinephrine - pretty much interchangeable with epinephrine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;serotonin - e.g. regulation of sleep, appetite and mood.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gaba - inhibitory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;glutamate - excitatory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to remove used neurotransmitter from receptor (re-uptake), otherwise it will keep signaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neuropharmacology&quot;&gt;Neuropharmacology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;External manipulation of synaptic events, e.g. for research or to correct a disease state.
Often this involves something resembling a neurotransmitter, but not fully. Hallucinogens often
work like that (e.g. LSD resembles serotonin).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can weaken synaptic response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with Parkinson’s have low level of dopamine in brain areas responsible for movement. One can increase level of dopamine globally, but this will cause other issues (e.g. schizophrenia-like symptoms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hm&quot;&gt;HM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient HM - a man who had terrible seizures. As a fix, his hippocampus was removed. As a result, he 
couldn’t form any new memories. He could remember some stuff from childhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 10, Neuroscience - part 1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversifying over ETF providers</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying-over-etf-providers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversifying over ETF providers" /><published>2019-11-30T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-30T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying_over_etf_providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying-over-etf-providers">&lt;p&gt;Many people talk about diversification in terms of geographic areas or economy sectors.
However, the diversification does not stop there. One can also diversify over brokers
where the shares are held. This way if something happens to one broker or the account gets hacked,
not everything is lost. Another dimension is over ETF providers.
This decreases impact of forced capital gain tax realizations. Let’s see how and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a company behind each ETF. E.g. for Vanguard S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF it is Vanguard and for iShares STOXX Europe 600 - BlackRock.
Each of these companies have their own history and can potentially go bankrupt. That’s the worst case. Alternatively
they can decide to change ETF structure or its ISIN. In both cases we are not worried about loosing our money.
However, a forced capital gain realization due to such an event can be unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it is hard to imagine Vanguard going busted, but in FIRE community we are talking about investment horizons
of 30-60 years. This is a long period of time and our imagination is pretty useless for such timescales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-impact&quot;&gt;Possible impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by evaluating how bad the impact can be. For simplicity, let’s say we’ve been investing into one
ETF and now we have \(X\)€ invested and portion \(Y\) of these are unrealized capital gains (e.g. for 35% \(Y = 0.35 \)). For even more simplicity, we will 
assume that the investment is in Germany and, thus, the capital gain tax is 26.375% (25% tax + 5.5% of that for Solidaritätszuschlag).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if we are forced to realize capital gains, our \(X\)€ will become \(X * (1 - Y) + X * Y * (1 - 0.26375) = X - X * Y * 0.26375\) €.
In this abstract form, we can’t conclude much, because we don’t know \(X\) and \(Y\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we can notice that \(X\) actually does not matter. Once we know \(Y\), we know which percentage of our money
we will have to pay as a capital gain tax and that’s what we are the most interested about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;estimating-y&quot;&gt;Estimating Y&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made a quick &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Gh-Sh6GNh3g0Cm5Csr-RXaHfU54EWlWPmUQIhITYIc4/edit&quot;&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;
for this. Please use “File &amp;gt; Make a copy” to put your numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet shows that \(Y\) at a time when we reach FI is affected by how long it took us to save
(i.e. our savings ratio, expected safe withdrawal rate and yearly market growth). The slower we save,
the larger is \(Y\). In other words, the slower we save, the larger role market has in our FI path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 7% yearly market growth and 4% safe withdrawal rate, we get the following values of \(Y\) based on savings ratio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.11 for 90% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.4 for 60% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.66 for 30% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you have 30% SWR, at the time your reach FI, 66% of all your money are unrealized capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worst-case-impact&quot;&gt;Worst case impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you reached FI today. Let’s ignore capital gain tax for now (i.e. if you are forced to realized all capital
gains, you won’t be FI anymore).
I will look in the following posts whether this assumption is reasonable (i.e. how much more one should save to account for capital
gain tax and other mandatory expenses like health insurance), but for this post this is not that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then something happens to your only ETF and you are forced to realize capital gain tax.
Depending on your savings rate (90%, 60% or 30%), you will have to say goodbye to 2.9%, 10.5% or 17.4% of your stash
right away. For 30% savings rate, this means working 20 more months to reach FI again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;events-which-can-be-taxable&quot;&gt;Events which can be taxable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a tax advisor and this varies across countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ETF liquidation is the most obvious example. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/articles/exchangetradedfunds/09/etf-out-of-business.asp&quot;&gt;Investopedia says&lt;/a&gt;
that investors get their money as a check and this may force an investor to pay capital gain tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is ISIN change, e.g. to due to a merger.
E.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyxoretf.de/pdfDocuments/Merger%20Q&amp;amp;A%20-%20Lyxor%20MSCI%20Turkey%20UCITS%20ETF_0b7b4493f192ea25211a8d348553fd26.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
is a document from Lyxor about the merger of Lyxor MSCI Turkey UCITS ETF in March 2019.
They very vaguely say that you may need to pay some taxes, but this depends on your country.
Fortunately in Germany, figuring this out will likely be broker’s problem, not yours, but you are
the one paying the taxes in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-solutions&quot;&gt;Possible solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose ETFs which are less likely to get liquidated or merged (usually this means large liquid funds from well-known companies and for popular indices)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversify across providers. This increases probability of you being affected by such an event (now there are more 
ETF companies your work with, each of them can have troubles and this will affect you). At the same time this decreases
an overall impact of such an event (each provider has only a small portion of your money).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy diversification!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Many people talk about diversification in terms of geographic areas or economy sectors. However, the diversification does not stop there. One can also diversify over brokers where the shares are held. This way if something happens to one broker or the account gets hacked, not everything is lost. Another dimension is over ETF providers. This decreases impact of forced capital gain tax realizations. Let’s see how and why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Value does not have to be perfect</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/value-does-not-have-to-be-perfect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Value does not have to be perfect" /><published>2019-11-26T17:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-26T17:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/value_does_not_have_to_be_perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/value-does-not-have-to-be-perfect">&lt;p&gt;I am interested in startups and try to pay attention to how exactly value is created around me.
I am also somewhat a perfectionist and when I try to create value myself, I tend to over-polish 
the details, often not being even sure whether the value is actually created. I noticed a couple examples
of projects with imperfections (sometimes major), which people use anyway. Let’s look at these examples more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anki---memorizing&quot;&gt;Anki - memorizing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anki is a program to memorize whatever you want using spaced repetitions. The idea is that you forget
exponentially and each repetition resets the curve and makes it not so steep. However, it does not make sense to
repeat too often. Anki tries to estimate what you are about to forget and shows you these &lt;em&gt;cards&lt;/em&gt; for repetition.
It works especially well for learning languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, there is only one major Anki program on Desktop. There is also one on Android and iOS. At least Desktop and Android
ones allow one to synchronize and backup their data through cloud for free. Pretty convenient, especially when one uses
Anki one their phone (e.g. when travels). As a result, the data needs to be merged occasionally. This merge logic can
become a nightmare pretty quickly. To my surprise, the authors of Anki just decided to refuse to merge in some cases.
E.g. when a card type is changed (e.g. instead of “show me both sides as 2 items”, you replace it with “show me only 1 side”),
the program just says - “hey, next time you will have to reupload all your data to the cloud, just FYI”. Then the other device
just asks you whether you want to download or upload your data and whether you really want to overwrite your local data.
My software engineering part feels pretty uncomfortable seeing that, but this is a great example of prioritization.
The desktop and Android versions are completely free (even cloud storage). Thus, the authors probably didn’t have too much spare time.
This reupload is definitely not perfect, but it is also not that bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely get plenty of value from Anki and this reupload is just a minor nitpick. I personally would feel uncomfortable
about making such decision not to merge some cases and just reupload everything. However, I haven’t seen anyone refusing to
use Anki because of that. Also I am not aware of any competitors either (probably, because it is free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shotcut---video-editing&quot;&gt;Shotcut - video editing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember I needed to compose a small video. I definitely didn’t need any serious software, because this was a one-off thing.
Thus, the goal was to have it done as easy as possible (i.e. no learning curve at all). Somehow I discovered Shotcut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program itself is pretty simple and easy to learn. At the same time there are some rough edges. It is obviously free.
However, occasionally it could crash (pretty rarely though). Also my computer is not the newest, so keeping all the high
resolution videos in memory got impossible pretty fast (especially when using preview function). Surprisingly, there is
no built-in fix for that. However, the Shotcut community found a workaround. Basically, the program does not store videos
themselves, but only their paths in the file system. Thus, we make a project with all the high resolution videos (add them from
some folder). Then we backup this folder into some other temporary folder. In the old folder, we downscale the resolution of all
videos. Now reopen the old project. Shotcut will just use downscaled versions as if it always was like that. Now you
can do everything as usual (just the quality will be poor). Even the preview works. Once you are done, you restore the old
high resolution backup and reopen the project again. Now you don’t need to look at the high resolution preview, you just
produce the final video. This is not that RAM intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised by this solution. However, I discovered got stuck with this issue pretty far in the process,
so I already had some part of my video
done in Shotcut and what was even more important - I already knew how it worked. So I did the workaround precisely as described above.
In the end it went very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, if I need to do another video, I will consider using Shotcut again (mostly because I already know how to use it).
I even don’t mind this workaround at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like quite an imperfection to me, however, the program still provides plenty of value.
There are many competitors in this area, but they are not free and not so easy to use without much preparation.
This “easy-to-start”-ness is the main value of Shotcut for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a reminder to myself to focus on the value when creating something. It is very easy to get stuck with small details
and polish them forever. However, this polishing does not make sense, if there is no value provided. Unfortunately, it is much easier
to do such value analysis once there is a finished product with some history and customer base. When I do
something myself, it is also unclear whether I will be able to provide any value at all. Anyway, this is a great reminder to focus
on what should be the most important to the customer, prototype it as fast as possible and polish later once you see that it
works and provides value (if any polish is needed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy value creation!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am interested in startups and try to pay attention to how exactly value is created around me. I am also somewhat a perfectionist and when I try to create value myself, I tend to over-polish the details, often not being even sure whether the value is actually created. I noticed a couple examples of projects with imperfections (sometimes major), which people use anyway. Let’s look at these examples more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology" /><published>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_9_ethology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 9, ethology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethology is a field, which studies behavior under the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will need to study the behavior in as many environments as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these environments must be as natural as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will have to translate a language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, ethology is a process of interviewing animal in its own language,
i.e. an expansion of “if you want to understand behavior, get your animal out of the lab”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the historical context, let’s have a look at the history of psychology.
At first it was a branch of philosophy and wasn’t about numbers (i.e. not a science in the modern terms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then behavioralism appeared, which treated an organism as a black box and the goal was to measure as much as possible.
The field had number of strong beliefs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extreme environmentalism - impact of environment is very high.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement theory - when I can control positive/negative reinforcement, I can form any behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Universality across species. Everything is black box, thus, it does not matter whether it is a human child,
a puppy or an elephant. As a result, the studies used mostly rats and pigeons for practical reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then meanwhile in Britain people started to collect butterflies as a hobby. The goal was to just observe
variability. Then ethology emerged, which was like butterfly collection, but for behaviors. 
There were 3 main figures in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nikolaas Tinbergen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Konrad Lorenz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karl von Frisch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field was about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gene-environment interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;examples of animals acquiring new (often unexpected) behaviors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;every species solving its own evolutionary challenges in its own way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: in 1960s it was discovered that, if a lab rat was placed in a richer environment (cage with toys), 
its cortex got thicker. As a result, people started to assume reversibility of early brain damage using
richer environments. However, then it was observed that a simple wild rat had very thick cortex, which was
unreachable using any artificially rich environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;Approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethologists look for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the behavior was - fixed action pattern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what triggered it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what happens in the head of the animal, when it is triggered by the stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the adaptive value of this behavior is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fixed-action-pattern&quot;&gt;Fixed action pattern&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed action pattern - a sequence of actions, which animals don’t have to learn, but they have to improve it.
Experience can also change context of fixed action patterns.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a squirrel raised in a cage on a liquid diet still can crack a nut without any preparation. It will get even better at it practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“visual cliff” = baby animals scared to sit on glass over a height (floating = falling). Baby sloths are not scared of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a male monkey, which was raised in isolation and have never seen another monkey. Show him a video of a face of huge scary
monkey of the same species with threating display. He will freak out and do subordinate gesture. Experience: who to do the subordinate
gesture to, i.e. not kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vervet monkeys have different alarm calls for eagle, snake and leopard. As kids they know how to do the call, but may not know when to do it
(i.e. mix up them). Adults don’t trust young monkey calls, but double check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In humans:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Infants smiling as well as fetuses and blind babies. Learning: who to smile to.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nursing. Learning: increase efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Detecting anger, fear, disgust in others; Learning: social context (i.e. when the meaning is not obvious).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adaptive-value&quot;&gt;Adaptive value&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand adaptive value, they did experiments. E.g. Tinbergen experimented with a bird turning egg shells non-white side up
after its chick hatching. Tinbergen turned them back. As a result, predators could detect the nest better. Frisch looked into bee
dancing. Bees communicate info about food sources (direction, how far, how much). They do this by dancing on the floor in patterns
shaped as “8”. Axes of “8” define the direction. The duration of the dance - distance. The more frantic the dance is (more back
wiggling), the more exciting the food source is. E.g. Frisch rotated a bee hive after the dance and all bees went in wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stimulus&quot;&gt;Stimulus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are number of techniques to study stimulus (so-called releasing stimulus in the field). One can assume what the stimulus is and then
subtract it, then put it back (replacement), then substitute (replace with something else), then superstimulate (exaggerate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently people started to use robotic animals (e.g. bees or cockroaches) for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female deer ovulate when they hear male mating calls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats can be tickled on their ribcage and they giggle in ultrasonic
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=78PfGQbL-g0&quot;&gt;youtube&lt;/a&gt;). Other rats come over to check “the party”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female ovulation in human leads to higher voices. Males can subliminally detect this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was research (&lt;em&gt;Stimuli eliciting sexual behavior&lt;/em&gt; by Schein, M.W., &amp;amp; E.B. Hale, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/how-to-seduce-a-turkey-the-bizarre-poultry-sex-experiments-of-the-1960s&quot;&gt;atlasobscura&lt;/a&gt;) on what makes a female turkey attractive to a male turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olfactory information in people. People can subliminally
(amygdala activation) distinguish scared people sweat from normal exercise sweat.
After “scary” sweat, they tended to interpret ambiguous faces as more frightened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electric fish - males jam each other frequency when courting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vibration in insects - animals have vibration detectors in their feet. They can communicate this way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrogate mom monkeys - a monkey is given a choice of two fake moms - one made with cloth (warm) and one
made out of wire, but with milk. Behaviorists claimed that mom attraction is due to milk. However, animals choose cloth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baby animals look cute (large eyes, ears) even across species. Early illustrators of Disney studied this
(e.g. evolution of Micky Mouse, youtube: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vDiykIUwSo&quot;&gt;with commentary&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3hWXfrANSd8&quot;&gt;without&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.wwu.edu/rcm/mickey.pdf&quot;&gt;“A biological homage to Mickey Mouse” by S. Gould&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neuroethology&quot;&gt;Neuroethology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it was hard to study how stimulus is processed in the brain. Currently there is neuroethology. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neurobiology of bird songs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Lordosis” reflex in female hamsters. When having a pressure on their back, they arch their back to make mating easier.
Only works when the hamster is ovulating. Specific neurons responsible for this are known, even which ones of them 
are affected by estrogen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding electrodes to the brain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sapolsky studied baboons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of learning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female childcare competence in female monkeys is not a strong instinct. Evidence: later offsprings have higher likelihood to 
survive. If she has a sister with a baby, her first child is more likely to survive (observed sister doing the care). The same
when having a niece or a nephew.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meerkats eat scorpions. Mom has to teach her kids. First, she brings a dead one, baby learns how to eat it.
Then mom brings alive scorpion, but she bites off the stinger. Kid has to tackle this one. Finally, she brings 
a normal scorpion. Thus, incremental learning steps (with progressing difficulty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animals make tools (e.g. apes). Chimps use sticks to get termites. One learns by observing others.
Daughters learn better (much more attentive). The larger the social group is, the earlier in life kids learn to use tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One trial learning (imprint after one exposure) - after hatching bird chicks imprint on something big around to bond for mom.
In this case, there is no place for trial and error.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared learning, e.g. Sauce-Bearnaise Syndrome. One ate the sauce and then went to opera. They had stomach pain.
The next time they were to taste the sauce, they had repulsion (unpleasant smell). The pain was not attributed to opera
(even though it occurred during opera), but to the sauce, since there is a prepared learning of food -&amp;gt; stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bees learn smell better than color or shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humans are not inherently scared of spiders and snakes, but have prepared learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cognitive-ethology&quot;&gt;Cognitive ethology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Griffin (random fact: discovered echolocation in bats) wrote “On awareness in animals”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;self-awareness&quot;&gt;Self awareness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can test for self awareness. E.g. dogs are not self aware.
Take a chimp, anesthetize, put a black dot on its forehead with a marker. When looking into the mirror,
chimps are much more likely to start scratching their head where the dot is. Elephants pass this test too.
Marmoset monkeys don’t. They don’t look into eyes normally. Thus, when the dot is on their neck, they
start noticing it too. An example of “interviewing” an animal in its own language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theory-of-mind&quot;&gt;Theory of mind&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing that other individuals can have different information than you. Humans start understanding this at the age of
4-5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test, one can tell a child a story about another child X, who has a doll called Sally. X goes to school.
Mom washes Sally and puts it into a different place. When X comes back, where would it look for Sally?
With the theory of mind the child will say “the old place” (since X does not know that they doll has been moved).
Without the theory of mind - “the new place” (since the child knows where the doll is and can’t imagine X having
different info).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chimps have this too. E.g. you can have two chimps (one high ranking, one low ranking) and a banana (all divided by dividers). 
If there is a glass divider between high ranking and banana, low ranking won’t try to get the banana (he knows that high
ranking knows). When you swap high ranking chimp with a different high ranking one, low ranking will go for the banana, 
because he understand that the new high ranking chimp does not know about banana. However, they can do this only in
competitive setting (no cooperation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corvus have this too. If they see someone observing them when they hide food, they won’t proceed with hiding the food.
I.e. they understand that other birds will know about the food hidden here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can distinguish intentional action from unintentional. In chimps - they react more dramatically to a person throwing
away their food vs. tripping over it. Dogs know the difference between an intentional kick and someone tripped over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can plan for the future. E.g. take corvus living in a cage with 2 areas. In each of the areas, there is a place
where researchers put food every other day. In one of them, they put more. Corvus starts bringing food from this place to another one for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flexible-cognitive-strategies&quot;&gt;Flexible cognitive strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bees will distrust implausible dances. E.g. researchers put food in the middle of the lake. A bee tells others about this. Others
don’t do anything, because there can’t be food in the middle of the lake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerosity.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teach chimp to detect series of 3 objects, e.g. “ABC” and “HIJ”. When they see them, they should pull the lever and
  they will get food. When shown “HI&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;”, they make less mistakes than when shown “H&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;J”. In the former case, the third object
  was replaced with the first. In the latter - second with second. I.e. chimp detects that this object is “second”, but forgets
  which triplet it belongs too.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take a chimp troop. Record foreign male chimp vocalizations. Play one foreign male chimp vocalization in the bush. The troop will
  investigate. Play vocalizations of the same number or more other chimps than in the troop, the troop will know that they are outnumbered and
  silently run away. They understand that 4 is more than 3.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In fish. Fish C sees A defeating B and then B defeats C. C gives subordinate gesture to A (transitivity).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 9, ethology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All (my) advice is awful!</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/all-advice-is-awful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All (my) advice is awful!" /><published>2019-11-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/all_advice_is_awful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/all-advice-is-awful">&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to advice others to do something, but it is very hard to be sure that this will actually help them.
However, not all understand this or choose to phrase their advice accordingly. I.e. instead of “here is a way to X”,
it actually should be “this is how I did X”. Thus, very often non-objective advice is just a description of what helped
the author, which is also true for some of my posts.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please treat this as a mega disclaimer to all my future and past posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do try to self-improve a lot and it seems that I am not alone in this desire. There are plenty of blogs,
sites and videos on self-improvement with various advice. This can be about better productivity, self-confidence,
startups, health, exercise. It is a very good way to create value for people and improve people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subjectivity&quot;&gt;Subjectivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, often such advice is very subjective. People just share what they do and how this helps them.
Someone wakes up at 4am every day and starts by making their bed. This helps them to be extremely productive.
As a result, they tell others “hey, do you want to be more productive? Just wake up at 4 am and make your
bed everyday”. Obviously, this does not mean that this will have positive effect (or any) on you. 
The author of the advice has their own life with their own weak and strong areas.
You have your own, which may be completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have vitamin C deficiency (hypothetical example) and this has physical negative consequences, but you
don’t know the reason. You somehow miraculously start taking vitamin C supplements and this fixes the deficiency.
The deficiency is now gone. Then you can advise others - do you want to get rid of such negative consequences? Take
vitamin C supplements. However, let’s imagine that there is some other way to get similar negative consequences. Thus, one
can have perfect level of vitamin C, but still have same negative consequences (hypothetical example). Thus, your advice won’t help them. The situation
above with 4am and making one’s bed is exactly the same. Perhaps the author was missing routine and was too dynamic and
that’s why waking up at 4am helps them. Perhaps you are over attached to your routine and adding more to it will even harm you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eye-opening-examples&quot;&gt;Eye opening examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effect is easy to observe with advice which had an enormous effect on you, but didn’t work for others.
E.g. I do consider “The science of Wellbeing” course on Coursera
(my summaries: 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;full&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary&quot;&gt;brief&lt;/a&gt;)
 to be a life changing as well as “Search Inside Yourself”
book (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/book-summary-search-inside-yourself&quot;&gt;my summary&lt;/a&gt;). However, I met people who
took the course and read the book and were “meh”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, context of the advice matters a lot. There are thousands of dimensions in life and when you do something,
each of these act as an input condition. There are obvious examples of this. Let’s say you’ve been studying positive
psychology for years. Then “The science of Wellbeing” won’t bring you anything new. Even regarding this post right now, you
can think that this is obvious for everyone and it is weird that I am talking so much about this. However, this was
not that obvious for me and I even decided to write about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asymmetry&quot;&gt;Asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it is very easy to give such subjective advice (in other words describe what you did
and which effect it presumably had on you). However, identifying all input conditions as well as even estimating
whether this could help someone else is extremely hard. For some input conditions, it may be even hard to 
understand that they can vary. E.g. you always wake up energized. It may look like all humans are like that.
Or you can be extremely organized and require structure in your life and you implicitly assume that that how
all people live. It is like fish living in water. If you never experience anything else (meeting a people, who
don’t have this quality), it is hard or impossible to even observe your “water”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estimation of usefulness for others is a nightmare. Unless you are a researcher with a group of test subjects
with double blind testing, you have very little tooling for this. In your own life, you almost always have sample size of
1 (just you yourself). You can’t go back in time and redo the intervention differently (or even not do the intervention
to simulate a control group). Basically, you just have one trial and then you have to derive everything you have from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;incentives&quot;&gt;Incentives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, people are incentivized to increase perceived value of their advice. Very often authors of the advice
also share various positive details about their life, e.g. making a million in couple years, being financially independent,
making a successful startup, feeling very happy for many years. I am not saying that this is done maliciously, however,
there is clearly an incentive to create an appearance that this positive quality was caused by the advice. At the same time
the author is not incentivized to point out weaknesses of their advice. E.g. the sample size of 1. If you want to attract
attention, you will rather say “hey, this always works, 100% credibility and reliability”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat peculiar that I do point this weakness in my blog right now. Basically, I am saying here that you should treat my advice carefully
and always keep in mind that even if it works for me, it does not mean that it will work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix&quot;&gt;Fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If authors are not the ones to fix this, you will have to take this into account. When you see someone saying “do X and 
you will get Y like I did”, always remind yourself that you may have different context. Even advice which worked for you
before, may not work anymore. I especially observe this with startups. Usually there is someone who made an extraordinary
exit and then they often start advising others. Usually they just tell their story and what they perceive as key factors
to their success. Often they actually don’t know themselves why it worked out. Remember, sample size of 1. Thus, they already
estimate. At the same time, the market is very dynamic. The situation they had is now gone. That demand is fulfilled by them. The world is
different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I don’t have any concrete example of a serial startup founder. Based on my observations a person with an amazing exit just tells
others about the exit, but can’t reliably reproduce their success again. Obviously, their context is now different. E.g. they may not
have financial pressure they had before. However, this somewhat contradicts credibility of their advice. If their advice was that sound,
they would be able to use it themselves to create a new startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can try the advice out. Alternatively you can try to generalize yourself based on multiple sources. E.g. if there are
100 different people telling that waking up at 4am improves their productivity and they are diverse enough (e.g. not all are 
military folks), you may conclude that this is reasonably general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix-as-an-author&quot;&gt;Fix as an author&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an author, I do feel somewhat weird about writing such subjective advice. One way to improve the situation is to always
mention that you didn’t do extensive research, this just worked for you and your own unique conditions. Another way is to avoid
writing about subjective topics. Instead do e.g. objective calculations and simulations. I personally write about subjective
advice if its impact on my life was enormous (like the course and the book above). In some sense, we can estimate expected
effect by multiplying probability of having effect with its magnitude. If magnitude is huge for me, the expected effect on
others is also larger (even if probability is generally low).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy self-improvement &amp;amp; mental adjusting of subjective advice value!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is very easy to advice others to do something, but it is very hard to be sure that this will actually help them. However, not all understand this or choose to phrase their advice accordingly. I.e. instead of “here is a way to X”, it actually should be “this is how I did X”. Thus, very often non-objective advice is just a description of what helped the author, which is also true for some of my posts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How technology affects our lives - a story about a delayed sms</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-technology-affects-our-lives-or-story-about-delayed-sms" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How technology affects our lives - a story about a delayed sms" /><published>2019-11-09T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-09T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_technology_affects_our_lives_or_story_about_delayed_sms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-technology-affects-our-lives-or-story-about-delayed-sms">&lt;p&gt;Today I stumbled upon a tweet about an SMS which was sent before Valentine’s day, but was delivered only recently
(i.e. 9 months later). This made me think about the impact of technology on our lives. Let’s look more into what 
has happened and my thoughts as well as speculations about the reasons for such a delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tweet&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danandelin/status/1192510312634695680&quot;&gt;The tweet&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_technology_affects_our_lives_or_story_about_delayed_sms/tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-context&quot;&gt;More context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, I noticed in the thread that there are journalists eager to reach the author
and wondering whether the two are going to reconnect. There were also plenty of news articles
(e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/11/7/20953422/text-messages-delayed-received-overnight-valentines-day-delay&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/a29726341/texts-delayed-random/&quot;&gt;popularmechanics.com&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were multiple tweets from other people about similarly delayed SMS. Someone complained about their boss receiving an SMS
from them at 4am. Some claimed that they didn’t send these messages at all (it is easy to forget an SMS after 9 months).
For some this was a sad experience, since they received a message from people, who died in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/11/7/20953422/text-messages-delayed-received-overnight-valentines-day-delay&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt; seems
to provide the most technical details:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A company named Syniverse, which provides networking services, later took blame for the messages being delayed.
Syniverse said a single server was at fault: that server failed on February 14th, trapping messages waiting to be
sent out; the server was only brought back online on November 7th. When that happened, all of the messages were finally delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Syniverse initially published a note saying that 168,149 delayed messages were sent. A spokesperson later told The
Verge that the company is “still assessing the scope and volume of messages impacted by this server disruption.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that 168k messages is an underestimation. It is hard for me to believe that 168k would create such a public outcry.
On the other hand, it is super easy to write something on twitter or reddit these days, so perhaps this number was enough…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-has-happened-on-their-side&quot;&gt;What has happened on their side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just my speculations. I don’t work in communications, so I have no clue how their system is setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that there was some server responsible for delivering such messages and around 14th of February it
stopped working for some reason. It likely had some cache (presumably even on-disk), because dropping SMS messages
seems bad. Perhaps it was one machine out of many (e.g. geographically distributed). Then I can see two possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No one noticed and the server just was off all this time;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone noticed and restarted the server, but there was a bug in how the cache was processed
(i.e. the cache was just ignored for long time and recently someone fixed this bug).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like option 1 more. It also seems to agree with the quote in The Verge. 
I speculate that other servers in the system just overtook the work this server had to do, that’s why no one noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then around 7th of November someone noticed this server being offline. 
Here I can again see 2 options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They think “oh, wth, this is bad” and investigate;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They think “oh, this one is offline, let’s restart it, not a big deal”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of (1), they might have discovered 168k message undelivered and then had a discussion with their manager
or even the manager of their manager about what to do. However, I prefer option 2 here. I.e. this cache was delivered unintentionally.
Otherwise I don’t think they would go for delivering these messages during the night and without any explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, these are just pure speculations. Bug happens, this one was not the worst.
Dropping the messages completely would probably be less fun (but on the other hand after 9 months their value is of doubt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-can-be-malicious&quot;&gt;This can be malicious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had a thought that perhaps there is some entity, which intercepts all my communication in all channels
(SMS, email, messengers) and filters it. Perhaps that’s why people, who I write to, sometimes don’t reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it is very easy to shoo such a thought away by just reminding myself that there is no point in doing
that to me and it is quite hard in terms of resources and tricky to automate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it is entertaining to imagine such a super entity controlling everyone’s communication. 
Basically it would decide who can say what and to whom. Like a god-like AI orchestrating our lives to maximize our happiness
(or just because it can).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again this is more like a conspiracy theory. I am pretty sure that if that was the case, someone would have noticed. 
E.g. they send a message to someone close by and just verify physically that it is not delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more realistic case would be parents doing this to their child. Parents definitely have preferences who their child
should hand out with. Usually with people who parents like more. So it would be convenient for parents to create an
illusion that other less desirable people are not even interested to communicate with their child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again practically pretty hard - one still communicates directly quite a lot, but in a fully digital world (i.e. no physical
communication at all) - easy peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effect-of-technology-on-our-lives&quot;&gt;Effect of technology on our lives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peculiar to think more about the original tweet I stumbled upon. There was a romantic relationship involved (probably 
at a very early stage) and due to this missing SMS, it didn’t go further. In some sense, this delayed SMS had a substantial impact
on the author’s life. While I doubt that the two are ideal match for each other (just using a probabilistic argument - probability of that is low), the author would still spend time with the other person and might have attempted to build a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think that technology always affects our lives in multiplicative ways. I.e. if I do something, technology may help
me to do this easier, cheaper, more conveniently. Somehow I didn’t think that technology could do something on my behalf (or 
it could another human using technology) or negate effect of my action completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fallacy&quot;&gt;Fallacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is very easy to start falling into a fallacy, which reminds me of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterfly_effect&quot;&gt;Butterfly effect&lt;/a&gt;. 
In some sense one could start saying that technology actually changes our life extremely.
Because of computer, I sit more often than I would otherwise, my profession is based on IT.
I spent numerous hours in Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that this is a fallacy because you can say this about anything in your life.
Basically, you can consider almost any effect or detail in your life as your own
“flapping of butterfy wings”. Your life might have been very different otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that one can’t just separate an impact of an individual event. The life is too interconnected these days
and it has too many dimensions. This impact of something depends a lot on initial conditions.
E.g. the same startup idea may work for someone who has enough resources or experience 
(or just lives in the more appropriate country).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also consider such deep thinking about alternatives counterproductive. Basically one can
spend plenty of time thinking what could have been different, but this does not bring any value.
It is just a form of entertainment and dreaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-is-still-good&quot;&gt;Technology is still good&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the author of the tweet ended up in this peculiar situation, I still think 
that technology is good and the author would agree with this as well. Funnily enough, for them
this story might have even a net-positive effect due to journalists’ interest. This also has
potential to boost the relationship with that other person (at least it is a funny story
to tell other people about how you met). But even if this was negative, e.g. this message
was completely lost, I would prefer losing this SMS to not having SMS at all (e.g.
using paper mail or not being able to communicate via long distance at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to stop appreciating the positive impact of technology on one’s life,
especially since one is so deeply ingrained in it that they never see any alternative. But it 
is enormous. I think I could be naming examples for a very long time. I am definitely
grateful for medicine (this extends life and its quality a lot), Internet and knowledge 
available there (a way to multiply your impact, partial equalization of opportunities independent
of your initial conditions like wealth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy living in this bizarre world!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I stumbled upon a tweet about an SMS which was sent before Valentine’s day, but was delivered only recently (i.e. 9 months later). This made me think about the impact of technology on our lives. Let’s look more into what has happened and my thoughts as well as speculations about the reasons for such a delay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Github Pages refused to refresh my Jekyll blog</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/github-pages-not-refreshing-my-jekyll-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Github Pages refused to refresh my Jekyll blog" /><published>2019-11-05T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-05T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/github_pages_not_refreshing_my_jekyll_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/github-pages-not-refreshing-my-jekyll-blog">&lt;p&gt;Recently I was trying to publish a post (namely
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-8-jobs-in-2030&quot;&gt;thought experiment #8&lt;/a&gt;
) and I was in a hurry. Peculiarly, Github Pages (the hosting I use) didn’t completely refresh the site
after my commit with the post. Let’s see how I fixed this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix&quot;&gt;Fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to waste your time - here is what fixed the issue for me. I just recompiled the blog locally
(this just changes the timestamp in a couple of places) and committed again. This time everything worked.
I don’t know why. I cross my fingers for it to work for you as well :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Jekyll on Github pages. Since I want to have more control over the visual theme
and plugins, I do the Jekyll compilation locally and publish the final html to Github pages.
Usually it takes up to couple minutes for Github pages to start showing the new content
after my commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;symptom&quot;&gt;Symptom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that time the link just didn’t work. I kept getting 404. Obviously, I assumed that
I made a typo in the link. I double checked - it was fine. I started the Jekyll server locally
and it also worked. I manually crafted Github Pages URL from a local URL and still got 404.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then tried the same link with “.html” in the end and it worked. I might have given up,
but this was a thought experiment and Savings Ninja &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/the-future-of-work/&quot;&gt;had already published&lt;/a&gt;
my link without “.html”, so this was not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovering-the-fix&quot;&gt;Discovering the fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just decided to follow the usual “turn it off and on again” advice and did another commit with
no user visible changes (just some timestamps after Jekyll recompilation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging with timely refreshes of your Github Pages websites!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently I was trying to publish a post (namely thought experiment #8 ) and I was in a hurry. Peculiarly, Github Pages (the hosting I use) didn’t completely refresh the site after my commit with the post. Let’s see how I fixed this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to buy ETFs at Flatex</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-to-buy-etfs-at-flatex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to buy ETFs at Flatex" /><published>2019-11-03T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-03T09:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-to-buy-etfs-at-flatex">&lt;p&gt;It can be overwhelming to start buying ETFs, especially for non-German speakers.
Here is a step by step guide to buy ETFs at Flatex in Germany (directly, not savings plan aka Sparplan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally started investing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/&quot;&gt;Flatex&lt;/a&gt; too (funny fact, this is 
not a referral link, their referral system conditions are weird). They have constant fees (5-8 Euro) to
buy and sell ETFs. To the best of my knowledge all other brokers (except onvista and its derivatives) have
percentage-based fees, which I avoid (here is 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/underestimating-ter&quot;&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt;
 why - basically paying 0.5% of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my networth is not fun). I already did
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/german-brokers-overview&quot;&gt;an overview of German brokers&lt;/a&gt;
before. I also started using Interactive Brokers in parallel with Flatex to diversify across brokers
and to save more on the transaction fees. However, Interactive Brokers won’t do your investing related taxes,
while Flatex will, so for beginners Flatex is definitely a much better choice.
If you are curious
about Interactive Brokers anyway, I wrote about
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions&quot;&gt;their commissions&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee&quot;&gt;monthly fee&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-buying-etfs&quot;&gt;how to buy ETFs there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware of two disadvantages of Flatex. First, they charge 0.4% (Negativzinsen) each year of all the &lt;em&gt;cash&lt;/em&gt; you have with them.
This is actually applied each day (as ~0.4%/365 = 0.00109%) and rounded down. E.g. having 1k EUR with them
for one day will result in 1 cent charge. Solution: just don’t store cash for long. One should be careful, though, and don’t let
the account be negative for long, because the credit rate is 7.9%. One pays Negativzinsen at the end of 
a quarter, so you should transfer the missing money soonish there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second potential issue is that
they charge 5.9 EUR for receiving dividends from individual non-German stocks (this is not ETF, dividends from ETFs are free).
Solution: just buy ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, they have nice customer service, who unofficially speaks English (i.e. this is not advertised,
but they all switched to English easily). They also have non-customer service (i.e. for potential
clients), which is amazing for asking random questions not related to me personally (I don’t have to fill
in all the account details and to verify my identity to ask 5 second question).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume that you have already registered at German Flatex (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/en/&quot;&gt;flatex.de/en&lt;/a&gt;).
Unfortunately I can’t help you with this, because I already have an account with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before buying an ETF you need to have money in your Flatex account. Surprise, surprise.
Fortunately, you get a usual IBAN number where you can transfer money as if it is just a different bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find the IBAN:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&quot;&gt;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to “SERVICE” tab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Bankverbindungen” (which means bank connections or links)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for “Cashkonto” (cash account) and its IBAN. That’s where you need to send your money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the best to save this IBAN as a template in your bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/iban.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sample screenshot of Bankverbindungen with fake data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please be careful and don’t confuse this with “Externes Konto” (external account),
i.e. the account linked with your Flatex account. For security reasons, you can transfer
money out only to 1 predefined IBAN (in order to change it you actually need to send a paper letter).
This is your “Externes Konto”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to transfer money from your “Externes Konto” though. It can be any account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-etf&quot;&gt;Finding ETF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting an ETF to buy is an art of itself and this is outside of the scope of this guide.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justetf.com/&quot;&gt;JustETF&lt;/a&gt; is a good start. Once you know the ETF, you need to find
its ISIN number, e.g. for accumulating S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF from iShares it is IE00B5BMR087
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justetf.com/de/etf-profile.html?query=IE00B5BMR087&amp;amp;groupField=index&amp;amp;from=search&amp;amp;isin=IE00B5BMR087&quot;&gt;iShares Core S&amp;amp;P 500 UCITS ETF (Acc)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/isin.png&quot; alt=&quot;JustETF page for iShares Core S&amp;amp;P 500 UCITS ETF (Acc) with ISIN highlighted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buy&quot;&gt;Buy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;buying-screen&quot;&gt;Buying screen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you received your money (you see it in your Cashkonto), you can get to ETF buying screen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in at &lt;a href=&quot;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&quot;&gt;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “HANDEL” (trading)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Order aufgeben” (give an order)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paste the ISIN number of the ETF you want to buy. I use IE00B5BMR087 as an example&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The suggestion with the ETF should appear, select it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You get to the ETF page, scroll down to see exchanges overview
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/exchanges.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flatex short exchanges view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose one of the exchanges. I recommend XETRA, flatex Preis (TRG) or gettex. 
I personally used gettex in the beginning a lot and, if you are not sure, I suggest to try gettex at first.
Possible criteria for choosing an exchange:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;opening times - exchanges work only at particular times, so some may be closed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fees - each exchange takes its own fee as well, I tried all 3 mentioned above and
the resulting fees were 5-9 EUR&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ETF price - there may be different price at different exchanges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;availability - there may be more stocks available to buy at one exchange&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your exchange is not in the list, click “Weitere Handelsplätze anzeigen” (show other trading places)
to show the full list.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click green “K” button (stands for “kaufen”, i.e. to buy) in the row of the selected exchange.
I use flatex Preis (TRG) here as an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;buying&quot;&gt;Buying&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you get to the actual buying screen. To buy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double check “Verfügbar” (available), i.e. how much money you have.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/available.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flatex buying view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change “Handelsart” (kind of order) to “Limitorder” (order with a limit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change “Ordertyp” (type of order) to “Limit”. This means that order will be fulfilled 
only when its price is smaller than the limit. This saves you from buying at an extreme price due
to an unexpected market spike.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type the desired price limit into “Limit”. This can be just the current price or 
something 0.1% or 0.5% lower if you don’t mind waiting or risking that your order does not get fulfilled.
Basically, Flatex won’t execute your order unless the price is lower than the limit.
If you set unrealistic limit, your order won’t get executed. At the beginning I suggest to set 
the current price. &lt;em&gt;Important:&lt;/em&gt; use comma (i.e. “,”) as a decimal separator, i.e. 7 EUR 50 cents should become 7&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type into “Stück/Nominal” (quantity) number of ETFs to buy.
It can’t be fractional. Please leave 10-15 EUR gap for the fees. Usually they are applied later and not shown at this stage.
If you are curious to know more about the fees, there is “Kostendetails &amp;amp; Auswirkung” link, which shows the breakdown.
This is quite a recent feature, I don’t remember seeing this before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Nettoschätzung” - should look green, this means that you have enough money. Double check that the number agrees with your
understanding. E.g. if you forgot to use “,” as a decimal separator, the number here will be super large.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Orderzusatz” - “&amp;lt;ohne&amp;gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Gültigkeit (Datum)” - how long the order should be valid. In other words, if the price does not reach your
limit in this timeframe, the order will be canceled. This happened to me couple times and I didn’t pay any fees (anecdotal evidence, I haven’t seen this officially confirmed anywhere).
You can choose “tagesgültig” (i.e. today) or “gültig bis:” (“until”) and some
date of your choice. At the beginning I suggest to set lax limit (i.e. just the current price) and “tagesgültig”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Press “Eingaben übernehmen”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The site will ask you for your TAN code, just fill it in from the card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Done, your order has been created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually “Verfügbar” (available) cash decreases at this stage, but in some places the money for the order may be shown as if
they are still in your account. Actually, they are, they are just “frozen” for the order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tracking&quot;&gt;Tracking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the status of the order in “HANDEL” -&amp;gt; “Orderbuch”. There you can also cancel your order, e.g. if you limit
happened to be too aggressive.
I did this couple times and didn’t pay any fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some time (depends on your limit and market state), the order should get fulfilled and usually after
a delay of at most 1 day, the result gets reflected 
in the interface (i.e. you can actually see the new ETF in your account). 
If this is not the case after a day (assuming this is not a weekend), I suggest to call their customer service.
I personally never had to do this, but better safe than sorry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-still-scary&quot;&gt;This is still scary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that this may look hard and complicated. It definitely took me couple months of research before I started
investing myself. As a workaround, I suggest you to make your first order with 10-50 EUR instead of your original amount.
This way it is much easier to convince yourself to try. In the worst case, the loss is very limited. I did this myself
too. I bought 1 share of some ETF and then sold it the next day to double check that I can get my money back. I know, this sounds
very naive now, but it was scary to move a bunch of my money there otherwise. But soon after, I started to feel pretty confident
with the process, so the learning curve is steep, but manageable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy investing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It can be overwhelming to start buying ETFs, especially for non-German speakers. Here is a step by step guide to buy ETFs at Flatex in Germany (directly, not savings plan aka Sparplan).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisit what you are bad at</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit-what-you-are-bad-at" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisit what you are bad at" /><published>2019-11-02T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-02T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit_what_you_are_bad_at</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit-what-you-are-bad-at">&lt;p&gt;Often we can get conditioned from outside that we have no talent in some area
and it is just not our thing. Thus, we shouldn’t even try. It is easy to get into 
this trap as a kid due to yet low self-confidence. Consider stopping for a moment and explicitly
catching all ideas like that. Let’s see why you might discover a lot of new about
yourself this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;talent-is-weird&quot;&gt;Talent is weird&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is indeed the case that a person has very strong innate talent and just
excels in some area. However, in the majority of cases it is not like that. Skills
require time and practice. It is naive to expect immediate results. However, external
observers very often forget about this. Yes, a given kid may not sing too exquisite, but
this does not mean that they can’t sing well in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One does not require that much of talent, but rather just interest and curiosity 
about the area. If one desires to practise and get better, this is already enough
to do so. You don’t have to be good at something, in order to be able to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-your-main-reason&quot;&gt;What is your main reason?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the second point. There may be various reasons to get better
at some skill. For example, it is just fun and one enjoys the process. This is
a perfectly valid reason to just do the thing. The growth is not important.
You don’t have to even show what you are doing to others. If one likes to
sing in the shower, please go ahead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason might be to make money or to impress others. In this case, one
has to care about external opinion. If someone says that you should stop,
this is just a feedback that what you are doing now is not good enough &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;.
Take into account negative feedback, but remember to decrease its
amplitude. Also don’t focus on the negativity, but try to understand what
exactly causes such effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revisiting-i-never-will-be-able-to&quot;&gt;Revisiting “I never will be able to…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a bunch of areas about which I can
easily say “I never will be able to do it”. For some of them I even spent
quite some time in my childhood and even took lessons. That is I had
quite enough of data to make my conclusion and decide to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with years somehow by chance I went back to some of these areas.
To my surprise, a) it wasn’t that bad
back then b) I can actually improve these skills further and it goes pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then it has become my personal sport to tackle such areas.
If there is something about which I could say “I will never be able to do this well”,
I am definitely lured to disprove that. This was definitely hard at first,
when I didn’t have any positive examples. E.g. I remember
I tried ice skating as a kid. I sucked at it really terribly. But as far as I remember
I tried only once or twice. Then I concluded that this was not mine and I should have focuses
into something else. After some years, I tried again and it just went fine.
I was able to learn to ice skate reasonably well and it is a lot of fun.
With each new such example of breaking “I will never…”, I get
more self confidence to tackle even harder areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, you are now quite a different person. You know so much
more, you have experienced so much more in your life and the world is different now.
There are new challenges, new opportunities. Perhaps something that blocked you back
then is now gone. Perhaps the technology has improved. Perhaps the learning materials
are now so much better. Thus, it makes sense once in a while to revisit your self
beliefs about what you can do and what you can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can imagine some really serious obstacles on one’s way to some skill
(e.g. physical body irregularities). Yes, this may affect the traditional
way of tackling the skill, but nothing prevents one from trying something else.
There are people, who play guitar with their legs (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/CK2TkN0m1SM?t=93&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;irrationality-of-i-will-never-be-able-to&quot;&gt;Irrationality of “I will never be able to…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense, “I will never be able to…” is almost always false.
Obviously, there are examples where such statement is hard to disprove.
E.g. breathing under water. But if it is about some human developed area
(like art, sport) and the bar is not too challenging (e.g. not world class or Olympic level),
the question is only about how much time one needs to achieve this level. 
It is also about how much time one is ready to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that some skills go better due to some innate ability and just
general life situation. Perhaps one already has skills which work well in that field.
E.g. from math into programming. However, the absence of some skill should never be
a blocker. It just means that one will have to spend more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I suggest to rephrase “I will never be able to…” into 
“I consider it is not reasonable to invest so much time into area X
to reach level Y”. This moves the question from your ability into
your priorities and decisions. Sounds much better, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sometimes-it-goes-better-once-you-start&quot;&gt;Sometimes it goes better once you start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of ignoring such self doubts is that
one can discover their innate ability once they start working
on their skill. Perhaps at first it goes badly, but after
some time they can discover that they are actually quite good at it.
Thus, one should avoid premature conclusions and dropping stuff
too early. Unfortunately, I have no clue when it is the best time to stop trying.
Perhaps when it is not fun anymore.
But to avoid false positives, it should rather be “when it is constantly not fun anymore
for a specific predefined period of time (e.g. a month)”. Otherwise one could
drop out by accident e.g. on a bad day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-others-do-this&quot;&gt;Why do others do this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do other people seed such self doubts?
Obviously this can be malicious (either explicitly
or implicitly). If a competition is possible, it is
easier for them to just convince you to drop than
to actually compete properly. This may happen implicitly as well
(i.e. person does not realize what they are doing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, they may believe into innate fixed talent 
(i.e. fixed mindset instead of growth mindset) and even consider
their advice very beneficial for you. They may not want you to
waste your time. From their perspective, since you does not perform
well at this, you never will and should search for something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed quite a few examples of parents saying this to their kids.
Often this is supported by an argument that parents themselves are really bad at
this skill and, thus, the kids are genetically predisposed to be bad as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dangers-of-such-self-doubts&quot;&gt;Dangers of such self doubts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem with such self doubts
is that they become deeply ingrained self-fulfilling prophecies. 
One just stops questioning this statement. It just becomes part of 
them and as a result - becomes completely true. Each time one claims
that they are not good at something and refuses even to try,
they push this self doubt even further into themselves. They self
reinforce it. With time they may even fully forget where it actually came
from and just live with it as a fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, next time you catch yourself thinking that you are not good at something
and as a result shouldn’t even try, try to understand where this is coming from
and whether this is still actually the case. Perhaps it is not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy self improvement, while crashing your irrational self doubts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Often we can get conditioned from outside that we have no talent in some area and it is just not our thing. Thus, we shouldn’t even try. It is easy to get into this trap as a kid due to yet low self-confidence. Consider stopping for a moment and explicitly catching all ideas like that. Let’s see why you might discover a lot of new about yourself this way.</summary></entry></feed>