<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-09T21:13:53+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment 6: unpopular opinions</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment 6: unpopular opinions" /><published>2019-06-09T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_6_unpopular_opinions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions">&lt;p&gt;The new thought experiment is live and this time it is about unpopular opinions,
which your peers don’t share with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concept&quot;&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, let me tell a couple words about the concept.
Every 2 months SavingNinja &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/category/experiments/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;
a hypothetical question about FIRE or life in general. Then one is encouraged to write their
answer in one go (just putting their raw thoughts as they come) without
editing afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already took part twice 
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;losing everything&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;projects when FIRE&lt;/a&gt;
and 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;overview of other people responses&lt;/a&gt;)
 and I definitely enjoy the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I am again writing this in the morning (in case it is something scary,
the “losing everything” impact still didn’t wear out).
SavingNinja thanked &lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/&quot;&gt;{ in·deed·a·bly }&lt;/a&gt; for a subject, so I am definitely curious.
Also did SavingNinja start running out of ideas or was indeedably’s idea so irresistibly good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;“Unpopular opinion”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new experiment statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A different opinion is somewhat frowned upon in our clique based society, but some of the greatest
minds of all time were outliers. They weren’t scared to go against the grain and stand up for what
they believed in. So, for this Thought Experiment, I’d like you to reveal yourself: What opinion do
you have that most of your peers do not share?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and there you can read other people
answers, which I definitely recommend. In the last experiment I even did
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;an overview&lt;/a&gt;
of people responses and I definitely enjoyed reading all the diverse opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, that’s a tricky one. 
I.e. I have to enumerate my beliefs and then compare them with beliefs of other people and estimate
the intersection. I definitely like that the question talks about “my peers” and not people in general,
because then it would be completely impossible. Here I can at least estimate by remembering anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure whether I will come up with one concrete answer. So far I have 2 options - the 
positivity of the concept of FIRE and negativity of alcohol. I think my views on alcohol have a good
chance to be the rarest across my peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I happen to be not a fan of alcohol. Somehow when everyone was starting to drink alcohol,
I didn’t like the taste much and didn’t start myself (but I definitely tried, peer pressure is a strong
motivator especially in the young age). As a result I don’t drink any alcohol. Obviously, this topic gets
raised at almost any celebration. As a result, I suspect that such an opinion is extremely rare across my peers. 
I don’t mean that my peers are constantly drunk, but somehow I can remember only 1 other person who
does not drink any alcohol due to non-religious reasons and one - for religious. It is funny that in the former
case their views were even more extreme than mine - they disallow people to drink any alcohol at celebrations
in their home. I personally don’t mind that. In the end each has their own life and if someone enjoys
drinking (even people who I care a lot about), but they don’t overdo it, then it is fine with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that this view may be quite rare across the general population as well.
I think the keyword is a teetotaler (Teetotalism). I am not part of Teetotalism per se,
but I suspect that for an external observer it will look like I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I suspect that alcohol abstinence (to clarify, I don’t restrain myself from alcohol and I often have
to actively refuse) is my opinion, which the fewest of my peers share (so far I can remember only 2 people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could I probably beat this number? Is there something one person or no one else shares?
Thus, let’s get to the second point. FIRE. Obviously, I don’t talk much to my peers 
about the concept. I work at a normal job and even though my colleagues are very understanding,
this might be too dramatic for them. Across my immediate peers (e.g. not FIRE related people in the Internet who
I actively tried to meet) I know only 1 other person, who is into FIRE and considers this to be a positive thing.
I assume that others either don’t know about it (majority) or find it unattractive or unattainable.
Why didn’t I put this before the alcohol? Because I did actively go to FIRE related meetups and I met
quite a few people interested in or even pursuing FIRE. I have no clue whether I should classify them as my peers or not.
Probably not, but I am not sure. Thus, it is up to you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this experiment does not invite to write a lot. I wrote a couple paragraphs and already
have 2 opinions. Oh, let’s also phrase them as opinions. So, the first one is “I should not drink any alcohol
aka there is no point in alcohol” (this is just my opinion, if you see a point in alcohol, that’s your opinion
and I will actively force myself to accept it as yours and to respect it). The second one - “I should pursue FIRE, FIRE is good and
will make me happier and improve my life”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I would like to go a bit meta. In general I try to avoid using society opinions when making my decisions.
I speculate that “average” opinions in society are often wrong and misleading and may even be artificially created
e.g. by some companies or the system in general 
(see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak&quot;&gt;my post on how capitalism benefits from this&lt;/a&gt;). 
One concrete example is other people age.
I think that society has unwritten rules “advising” one not to communicate across large age gaps.
I consider this very weird, because when two people communicate, age plays very little or no role at all.
Imagine that there is a set of people, with whom you would enjoy spending your time (this can be any activities,
e.g. just talking, doing sport, walking, hiking). Then if you add an artificial limitation based on age, you just
remove some people from this set, i.e. make finding interesting people even harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously I can see where this is coming from. This indeed works as a stereotype and a heuristic.
Most of the time people with a large age gap may have different interests, goals and problems in life
and, thus, establishing the communication may be hard. However, if you somehow happened to see that another
person is in your “interesting” people set, not building a relationship due to their age would be
a waste of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I don’t try to do opposite to mainstream opinions. That would be weird. 
I just try to assign them an artificially smaller weight in my decision process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this artificially lowered weight of mainstream opinions could be another example of an opinion
which few of my peers share. I think I know only 1 other person like that, but they are just a random acquaintance
and we don’t talk much these days. Obviously, I don’t discuss this much either.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">The new thought experiment is live and this time it is about unpopular opinions, which your peers don’t share with you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capitalism wants you to be weak</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalism wants you to be weak" /><published>2019-06-04T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism_makes_you_weak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak">&lt;p&gt;Mr. Money Mustache wrote multiple times about weaknesses and inconvenience. 
This made me think about the modern world mechanics around them.
I then understood that capitalism benefits from people being weak
and avoiding inconvenience. Let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By capitalism I mean privately owned companies, which operate exclusively for profit.
I am not trying to say that the system is bad - the modern world operates like that anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By weaknesses I mean people choosing options, which are too easy (perhaps even harmfully easy)
for them. Similarly for inconvenience - choosing options, which are too convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;capitalism&quot;&gt;Capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company’s goal is profit. There are artificial limitations created by governments,
because, otherwise, company’s actions can be even harmful for the customers. E.g. they could
use substances, which are harmful in the long term, to save costs. Alternatively they
could become a monopolist and then start rising prices to have more profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the company’s goal is the profit, whenever there is an opportunity to increase the
profit - the company is likely to take it. For simplicity, let’s consider only 
net-positive opportunities (i.e. ones which are in the end overall positive for the company,
even if at the beginning they can be negative).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humans&quot;&gt;Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, humans have hedonic adaptation and get used to any current state
and stop enjoying it. Majority of situations can be improved, so the current state can
even be considered inconvenient or too hard. There are also many people, so from probabilistic
view, some of them (outliers) will over-exaggerate and require unnecessary (from majority’s 
perspective) simplification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;both-together&quot;&gt;Both together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then when someone signals their desire for simplification, this can be a good opportunity 
to make money. As a result, if enough people happen to have this desire and are ready to
pay for its solution, this may become profitable for some company. Since the company’s goal
is profit, they don’t care about how weird or absurd the problem can be. The customers will
pay, this is enough. At the same time the company can even claim that they are improving 
customer lives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;customers want this solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are paying for it (i.e. consider it valuable enough)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, they must have a problem and we are solving it for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we get a positive feedback loop. Enough people want some simplification. Some company
fulfills this need. People get used to it due to hedonic adaptation (just start considering it
normal) and want more simplification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own example is washing clothes.
One can have a washing machine or wash them manually. The former saves a lot of time
and effort. However, one still needs to hang the clothes to dry up. I got so used
to the washing machine that I now consider hanging up the clothes as quite inconvenient.
Basically I completely forgot how manual washing would have felt. I can imagine other
people having similar feelings and then some company coming and fixing this issue.
However, I personally remind myself that washing machine already solves 99% of the problem
for me and going for that remaining 1% is an overkill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-step-further&quot;&gt;One step further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously we considered people having a problem and wanting a solution. However, the companies
are also incentivized to create a problem when there is none. In other words, people may consider
something to be ok and normal, but this does not bring any money to for-profit companies. Thus,
they are incentivized to come and “teach” people that their current state is inconvenient, 
sub-optimal, can and should be improved - just pay for the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider this much more dangerous than fulfilling weird-but-real needs coming from people. In this case,
the company itself affects people. What is even scarier, the company is interested in making
money and they don’t need to consider entire scope of their effect on people. In other words, if
they can make people to buy something, but at the same time there will be some unintended consequences,
the company does not care as long as the customers pay and this is inside governmental boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming with particular examples is hard. I can imagine someone trying to define “beauty” in a way
which helps them sell their product. E.g. some nose shape and plastic surgery or body weight and 
products for losing weight. It is peculiar that companies still can claim that they are improving
people lives (e.g. people still buy their product in some sense voluntarily), but this is
objectively questionable. E.g. if someone would consider themselves ok, but then they get affected
by company advertisement and start considering themselves ugly, then the company just made them less happy.
In some sense, this is caused by people’s irrationality. Yes, they may want to buy something,
but the source of this desire may be external.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is fear. Whenever one fears something, they greatly value protection against it.
Thus, the companies can be incentivized to over-exaggerate how bad something is or just create the fear
artificially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Freakonomics, one particular example are mouthwashes (they use Listerine as an example).
They are incentivized to make you scared of bad breath. According to the book, before Listerine
the bad breath was not considered that bad, but their ads changed this perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/05/fashion/weddings/how-americans-learned-to-love-diamonds.html&quot;&gt;the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;,
diamonds is another example. At some point in history diamonds were not that popular.
However, companies selling diamonds wanted this to be different. As a result, they
managed to convince many that having diamonds (and giving them as present) is good.
This in some sense created a fear - “if I don’t present a diamond, my partner will be less
happy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the human nature, looking at products for kids often illustrates this even better.
Each parent intrinsically wants the best for their children. As a result, 
creating artificial fears and simplifications here is even easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;remarks&quot;&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I considered only existence of people wanting “weird” simplifications, while their quantity
is actually much more important for estimating the actual effect. However, I don’t think such an estimation
is feasible, so I just hypothesize how the mechanic works without any quantitative data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting, I am not saying that these people are bad. This is their own choice
and they are free to want something. I am just interested how some weird and absurd things end
up on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important observation is that the actual definition of weakness depends on your own
life situation. E.g. I could say that having a dish washer is unnecessary and such people are weak.
I can imagine someone else saying that having tap water is unnecessary and I am weak.
Nevertheless I suppose that there are some products, which are considered unnecessary by the
majority (e.g. 99%) of the population (hi, &lt;a href=&quot;/post/crazy-pistachio&quot;&gt;crazy pistachio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I am not against all the simplification. I definitely enjoy having a washing machine, physical safety,
medicine, grocery shops and so on. I think these and many others did improve my life and made it quite better.
In some sense, these do solve major part of some problem for me. I don’t think that the remaining small part
of such problems has to be solved. E.g. I don’t need groceries to be delivered to my place, I am fine with just going
and buying them. Delivery companies could try to create a perspective that buying your own groceries 
is not cool (like not having diamonds during a wedding). I am definitely against such artificial perspective.
Please note that for others this may make more sense, e.g. they are very busy and want to save time.
However, I struggle imagining being so busy (like not having 1-2 hours per week).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">Mr. Money Mustache wrote multiple times about weaknesses and inconvenience. This made me think about the modern world mechanics around them. I then understood that capitalism benefits from people being weak and avoiding inconvenience. Let’s see how.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impro games for non-impro group</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-non-impro-group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impro games for non-impro group" /><published>2019-06-02T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-02T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/impro_games_for_non_impro_group</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-non-impro-group">&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that some impro games can be played in a group unrelated to impro 
(e.g. work colleagues at a party). Here is my compilation of such games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many impro games one needs a special crowd, which won’t judge and so on
(for more details see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/beauty-of-impro&quot;&gt;my post-reflection about impro in general&lt;/a&gt;).
However, there are many other games, which are just fun and would work even
for people outside of impro. The main requirement is that they don’t require
too much free-form input. E.g. if it is a work party and you suggest to make a scene,
either everyone will feel uncomfortable (the context is wrong) or someone will
say something too dramatic and this will be misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I have previously collected
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/impro-games-for-two&quot;&gt;impro games for two people&lt;/a&gt;,
which might be of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer-about-the-source&quot;&gt;Disclaimer about the source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t make up any games here, I just reference them from &lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/&quot;&gt;improwiki.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compilation&quot;&gt;Compilation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/alien_tiger_cow&quot;&gt;Alien Tiger Cow&lt;/a&gt; - 
on count of 3, everyone represents one of 3 figures. The goal is to converge
to one figure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/be_my_fan&quot;&gt;Be My Fan&lt;/a&gt; -
people play Rock-Paper-Scissors, the one losing becomes a fan of the winner and cheers them up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/blind_stalker&quot;&gt;Blind Stalker&lt;/a&gt; -
people wander around the room (with people-bouncers at the walls) with closed eyes,
there may be a vampire (when they catch someone that person should shout and stop)
and person reviving (they can revive someone who was caught).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/bunny_bunny&quot;&gt;Bunny Bunny&lt;/a&gt; - pass the bunny
with a special hand-finger motion (people around the bunny can do something special as well).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/digits&quot;&gt;Digits&lt;/a&gt; - count to 21 without 
any synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hand Loops (no source, played at a workshop) - everyone gets into a circle and looks down. Then people go towards 
each other with their hands in front of them. They hold on one other hand with each hand.
Then they try to undo “the knot” without releasing the hands.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/forming_molecules&quot;&gt;Forming molecules&lt;/a&gt; -
everyone wanders around, a leader shouts a number, everyone tries to form groups
of this size. When the group is formed they hold hands and sit down.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/group_stop&quot;&gt;Group Stop&lt;/a&gt; - everyone wanders
around, when someone freezes, everyone should freeze. When all freeze, everyone starts
wandering around again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/triangle&quot;&gt;Triangle&lt;/a&gt; - each player takes two other players
as references without telling anyone. Then they try to form an equal triangle with them.
Another variation - try to keep one selected person in the middle between you and the other person
(like a bodyguard and a killer).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/you&quot;&gt;You&lt;/a&gt; - define a chain randomly. Pass “You” across the chain.
Define another chain e.g. with fruits. Pass “fruits”. Add more chains (e.g. sounds, movements).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/samurai&quot;&gt;Samurai&lt;/a&gt; - one establishes eye contact with someone,
raises their sword with “Heeee!”, the other person catches the sword with “Hu!”, then they do their
“Heeee!” and people around them “cut them in half” synchronously with “Haaaa!”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/3_x_different&quot;&gt;3 X different&lt;/a&gt; - two players count 1, 2, 3
one by one. Then they replace 2 with a movement. Then they replace 3 with e.g. saying a name of a famous
person (each time different).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;names&quot;&gt;Names&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/cross_circle&quot;&gt;Cross Circle&lt;/a&gt; - ones names someone,
when the receiver acknowledges, one starts walking towards them. The receiver has to name
someone else and start walking before the first person reaches them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Name Pointing (no source, played at a workshop) -&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 1) point at someone, say your name.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 2) point at someone, say their name.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 3) point at someone, say third person name, the second person has to point at the third person.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-interaction&quot;&gt;No interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/circle_up&quot;&gt;Circle Up&lt;/a&gt; - 
shake each hand and leg 7 times, then 6 and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="compilation" /><summary type="html">I’ve noticed that some impro games can be played in a group unrelated to impro (e.g. work colleagues at a party). Here is my compilation of such games.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty of impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty-of-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty of impro" /><published>2019-05-28T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-28T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty_of_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty-of-impro">&lt;p&gt;As you have already read, I started doing impro recently. I enjoy it enormously. 
This is my reflection on what I enjoy and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a couple words about the concept just in case. Basically a group of people gather together and play
so-called improvisational games. There are many kinds of such games, but the main idea is to be very
spontaneous and just channel your ideas outside. Usually there is a suggestion from the group for the 
theme, so that the players are forced to be spontaneous and couldn’t prepare anything in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the contrast to games in general, here it is rarely about winning or losing. You mostly fight yourself (being shy,
indecisive, blocking your ideas). The mechanics often has no way to win or lose. Very often
the game forces people to cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common class of games is based around “scenes”. Here two or more
players get on the “stage” (this can be just part of the room), get some suggestion from the audience (e.g. their
location and relationship) and then just do the scene without any script. There are multiple variations, which usually
add some limitation to the scene mechanics or just spice things up. E.g. I like “new choice” game a lot. 
There two players do the scene and a moderator can say “next choice”. The player who did something before
“next choice” was said has to redo their action or phrase again, but differently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPfkJo3e7_M&quot;&gt;This youtube video&lt;/a&gt; gives a nice example,
but keep in mind that folks there are extremely good at this and had a lot of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;necessary-conditions&quot;&gt;Necessary conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that impro won’t work if group tries to judge participants or use what they say and do against them later.
This must be a safe space for experimentation without any long standing consequences for the participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering why, but it is simple. Once one stops blocking their ideas, they start getting a lot of them,
but majority (especially at first) can be perceived as weird (especially from a mainstream point of view).
This is definitely not person’s fault. I feel that brain just works that way. In our normal everyday life we learned 
very deeply to cut such ideas quickly and never express them. Impro is about trying to reverse this process. You just get
some idea and go with it, because usually you have no time to evaluate it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This non-judgment part feels very bizarre at the beginning. The first couple times you come, you still block your ideas
just in case. You don’t want to look weird and scare people off. But at the same time if the group happens to have
experienced people (you should aim for such groups), you will observe that they do pretty crazy stuff and people
react perfectly fine to this. The most common examples are insults, swearing and sexually related topics.
After some time observing others, you start trying a bit crazier ideas yourself and notice that no one objects.
Eventually, you will stop blocking yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding long lasting consequences - the impro group can be non-judging, but the mainstream society (or your non-impro friends)
may be not like that. Thus, I personally prefer to keep stuff which happens at impro sessions just there. E.g. majority
of people outside of impro would not understand what happens there at all. But they don’t have to.
As long as the group understands you and everything is kept inside the group, you are fine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-yourself&quot;&gt;Understanding yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After starting impro I noticed that this thought post-processing mechanism (the one blocking ideas)
sits very deeply in my mind.
Consider a game “free association”. Basically each player says a word, the next player has to say the first thing
that comes to their mind. This is extremely hard at first. You get some word very quickly, but then all this machinery
jumps in and in no time you get thoughts like “this word makes no sense, it is not related to the previous word,
should I say it? Will it be embarrassing?”. I personally found this very surprising. Fortunately, this gets better
with practice. But still it is extremely peculiar to observe our brain “low level” machinery so vividly. 
In some sense this is similar to mediation. In mediation, you try to keep your thoughts under control. Here you 
try to avoid wandering away as well. In some sense impro helps to go on meta level and observe how you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This safe space is actually extremely valuable, because you can try out new stuff there without worrying of being judged.
Normally if you can’t or never tried singing, you feel scared to try, especially in front of other people.
They may get upset and tell you that they don’t like your singing. One is scared to embarrass themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read somewhere that this fear to embarrass yourself is an evolutionary advantage. If you imagine 
prehistoric people, each of them separately was quite weak against all various dangers in nature. But when they gathered into
groups it worked out much better (basically, they used their ability to communicate to their advantage). However, when the group
does not like you, they will kick you out. Then you are on your own, which is not a pleasant experience,
especially in prehistoric times. Thus, people started fearing being rejected by a group, which could happen as a result of
misbehaving or embarrassing yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that desire to keep the group happy is bad per-se.
E.g. in work context, being scared to embarrass yourself sounds fair.
However, the modern society propagates this to other branches of life. As a result, one is scared to try new stuff,
to take risks and to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to our singing example, one could easily try singing at an impro workshop. Since the group is non-judgmental
(e.g. due to the nature of impro itself), they won’t judge singing either. Obviously, this is not a hard rule, but
I would be extremely surprised if someone said you something negative (that would not be very kind of them).
Once you try, you can see how you feel and whether
you like it. Perhaps by trying multiple times you can even improve your skill a bit. Or, on the other hand,
you can understand that you actually don’t enjoy singing that much and just drop it completely.
Either outcome sounds like a good progress to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that this could work especially well for learning languages. Very often people who learn new languages, feel
self conscious. They don’t want to embarrass themselves in front of others by making mistakes, taking too long to speak
or talking weirdly. Obviously, non-native language at impro is a handicap. However, at the same time, since the group is
non-judgmental, at impro one can get through their own language embarrassment barrier and just get used to using the language
and observe that others do understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definitely applies to various artsy stuff like dancing, singing, playing music instruments,
writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-boundaries-and-possibly-getting-through-them&quot;&gt;Understand your boundaries and possibly getting through them&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern society has plenty of unwritten rules, especially about behavior, communication or relationships.
Everyone is highly incentivized (aka forced) to be “normal”. Yes, there are ways to differentiate yourself,
but they are all highly preselected, like templates from which you can choose. You can have
some other kind of clothing or even a tattoo, but there are plenty of other people who will do this as well.
Overall, you are encouraged to be predictable and easy to understand to simplify everyone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find extremely funny is that when growing up one just gives up their unpredictability and curiosity. When you were a kid,
you didn’t know “rules of the game”, i.e. norms of the society. That’s why crying loudly on a plane didn’t bother you as well
as wearing dirty clothing. In some sense, there is nothing intrinsically wrong with either, just the society happens
to be against. With time you get directed more and more and eventually just accept these new norms and become an adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During impro you hit these boundaries quickly. Normally you don’t observe them explicitly in your life. They are just there like
invisible walls, but you probably never went that far, so from your perspective these limitations didn’t exist. Impro encourages
you to go all the way and you very quickly discover that, yes, there are plenty of blocks and boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering them is already extremely valuable. But with impro and safe space you can go even further - to the other side.
I am not saying that you should drop all the norms in the society completely.
No. But understanding that they are there is useful and getting through them at least at impro sessions is a nice exercise as well.
Then it can be your own explicit choice to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If growing up adds blocks and limitations to your life and impro helps you to become aware of them and to remove some,
then impro is equivalent to trying to become a child again. In other words, ungrowing up. If you think about it, you did
actually play such games as a child a lot. You would gather with other children, come up with some shared fantasy world
or some life situation (doctor or fireman) and then explore that world together with others according to its mechanics.
If someone suggested you to consider a stone to be your spaceship, you would easily accept that.
If someone says that you are attacked by aliens and you need to run, you would run and shout. This is precisely how impro works.
You do a scene with someone in a shared reality, either of you can suggest something and other can either accept it or refuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;confidence&quot;&gt;Confidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not being scared of embarrassing yourself (i.e. taking risks) looks like confidence for an external observer. 
From this perspective, impro helps you to gain confidence. Another peculiar fact is that you can get used to people being non-judgmental. Then assume the same in other situations, e.g. when you make a presentation for a large crowd.
Obviously, people there are much more likely to be judgmental, but in majority of cases people just don’t care at all.
I know, this is hard to believe, because from your perspective you are the main hero of everything in your life and everyone
seems to care about you, but from their perspective they are the heroes. Thus, assuming that people are non-judgmental
can help you in situations outside of impro and improve your confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, not judging others yourself is also extremely cool. When someone does something unusual, you are tempted to
stop them quickly, e.g. if it is inappropriate or you don’t understand it. But during impro you learn
to notice this and instead just let it be. In the end, it is other person’s choice and their action.
Thus, this skill can help you to support people in creative situations, especially when they take risks and can
embarrass themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;people&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, such an unusual activity gathers peculiar people as well. Very often they come from various backgrounds,
but somehow find a common language and collaborate. Learning cool people is definitely another benefit of impro
sessions, which I enjoy. As well as socializing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acting&quot;&gt;Acting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Majority of games culminate with acting, so you get to practice acting a lot and in various situations.
This is definitely nice. You get to experience situations, which you would not encounter normally. This helps
to understand other perspectives better. You obviously improve your acting skills too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-and-fun&quot;&gt;Play and fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, impro is all about play and having fun! I believe that all people are very playful and enjoy
free-form playing, but are unfortunately limited by the society and opinions of others. Impro gives you
a chance to play. In some sense it allows you to be yourself. Once you
are not limited by society it is easier to express your own views, emotions and just represent your inner self.
As a result, this is often a very fun process. Obviously at first there is some introduction period where you get
used to the concept, stop being scared and slowly experiment while crossing your own boundaries.
Eventually, you get there and this kind of play just brings a lot of joy. It is also extremely funny. I do laugh
a lot, because some scenes are surprisingly hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy ungrowing up!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="improv" /><category term="improvisation" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">As you have already read, I started doing impro recently. I enjoy it enormously. This is my reflection on what I enjoy and why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impro games for two</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-two" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impro games for two" /><published>2019-05-26T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-26T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/impro_games_for_two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-two">&lt;p&gt;I tried impro recently (aka improv, improvisation theater). I did extremely enjoy the experience, but also felt like I
didn’t get enough out of the workshops (they are surprisingly crowded). Thus, I will try to practice in much smaller
groups (like 2 people). This can be challenging since majority of games are for more people. Here is my compilation
of warmup and “main course” impro games for 2 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start, a couple words about impro in general. The main idea is to come on stage without any preparation
and to develop some theatrical scene on the go, possibly with some artificial limitations or a forced format.
This may sound extremely challenging. And, yes, it is challenging, but the important detail is that the crowd
has to be special. They must be very open-minded, non-judging and not to take what you say personally.
This allows you to just say the first thing you have in your mind. Yes, it may be extremely embarrassing and
scary (especially at first - “this people will be aware of the weird thoughts / ideas I am having”). But after 
some time and observing others, one starts realizing that everyone occasionally has weird ideas and people just 
accept and celebrate that. No one criticizes and blames. No one takes your ideas against you. Basically you
start trusting the crowd. But as I said above you need a special crowd for this, this won’t work with random people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally there are various “workshops” where you can practice impro with others. Usually these are just
gatherings of people, where they play “impro games” - games which require one to improvise. Using my notation
above, these games add artificial limitations to what you can say or do. Usually there is also a moderator - an experienced
person, who gives the high level direction - which games to play, how and when to stop. They may also give advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such gatherings are definitely fun, but there are often a lot of people.
Sometimes the games require a participant “to die” when they make a mistake (i.e. just leaving the stage).
Thus, the active play time can be very limited (too many people in the first place and then “losing” quickly).
As a result, one mostly observes. So now I am trying to form a smaller “unofficial” group (starting with only
me and someone else) to play these games on our own and to practice more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not meant as a replacement for the workshops. I think that at workshops one gets new ideas from others
or a moderator and tests their skills in “real” scenarios with audience. In a smaller group one
can actually practice what they observed at the workshop and hone their skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worth noting that there are usually two major kinds of games - warmup and the main games. They have different goals.
The warmup games are meant to activate you and to bring you in a cheery mood, so that you improvise better.
They may involve some improvisation, but just a little bit (e.g. one suggestion at a time). Usually they involve
concentrating on what others do and paying attention to them. They also may involve physical activity - jumping, dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer-about-sources&quot;&gt;Disclaimer about sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not making up any games on my own here. This is just a compilation and I just reference games from &lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/&quot;&gt;improwiki.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;games&quot;&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For brevity, players are denoted as A and B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may use Wikipedia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Random&quot;&gt;random article link&lt;/a&gt; as a source of suggestions,
when a game requires some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warmup&quot;&gt;Warmup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warmup for 2 people is extremely tricky, because the majority of exercises are meant for groups.
It is also easy to pay attention to others, when there is only one other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;Interaction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/call_and_reply&quot;&gt;Call and Reply&lt;/a&gt; - set 
the rhythm, A sings a line in Gibberish, B repeats the line together with A.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/follow_the_king&quot;&gt;Follow the king&lt;/a&gt; - 
A moves around the room while avoiding invisible obstacles, B follows A
and avoids the same obstacles at the same places (as if they are really there).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/last_word_-_first_word&quot;&gt;Last word - first word&lt;/a&gt; - A says a
line, B has to say a line starting with the last word A said.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/free_association&quot;&gt;Free Association&lt;/a&gt; -
association game without thinking - A says a word, B says what came to mind first
as is. One can play in Gibberish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/peculiar_neighbor&quot;&gt;Peculiar neighbor&lt;/a&gt; - 
A says to B something that stands out, B must accept, explain and clarify.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/what_is_a_what&quot;&gt;What is a what?&lt;/a&gt; -
rhyming. Everything must be said in “What is a &amp;lt;word X&amp;gt;, without a &amp;lt;word Y&amp;gt;?” format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-interaction&quot;&gt;No interaction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/block_of_ice&quot;&gt;Block of ice&lt;/a&gt; - imagine 
that A is frozen in a block of ice which melts from the top. As their body parts
get free, they can move them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;physical&quot;&gt;Physical&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/circle_up&quot;&gt;Circle Up&lt;/a&gt; - shaking hands
and legs 7 times, 6 and so on until 1 (while counting).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/sword_of_samurai&quot;&gt;Sword of samurai&lt;/a&gt; -
slow motion - hands = swords, when they touch = sword sounds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/what_are_you_doing&quot;&gt;What Are You Doing!&lt;/a&gt; -
A mimes, B - “What are you doing?”, A says something they didn’t mime,
B mimes what A said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;main&quot;&gt;Main&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/3_x_different&quot;&gt;3 X different&lt;/a&gt; - count
1, 2, 3, one by one and replace each number with something (e.g. an action).
The action can be non-repetitive (e.g. say a famous person name, each time different).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/gibberish_circle&quot;&gt;Gibberish Circle&lt;/a&gt; -
A explains something in Gibberish (with gestures), B translates into English, but using
the same gestures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/story_solo&quot;&gt;Story Solo&lt;/a&gt; - A tells a story,
B can say a word, A has to use it in their next sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scenes-with-limitations&quot;&gt;Scenes with limitations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/talk_at_touch&quot;&gt;Talk at touch&lt;/a&gt; - 
one can speak only when they touch the other player.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/emotional_replay&quot;&gt;Emotional replay&lt;/a&gt; - 
play a scene. Then choose an emotion, replay a scene with that emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/scene_mix_10x20&quot;&gt;Scene mix 10x20&lt;/a&gt; -
play 10 scenes (20 seconds each) and try to establish the scene ASAP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/he_said_she_said&quot;&gt;He said, she said&lt;/a&gt; -
A says their line, B says “he said while &amp;lt;some action&amp;gt;” and A has to perform
&amp;lt;some action&amp;gt;. To make the flow more natural, one can swap the order, i.e.
A says “he said while…” and then B says something while doing what A said.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/new_choice&quot;&gt;New Choice&lt;/a&gt; - 
play a scene. When “New Choice” is said, the player has to replace their last
line or action with something different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/pen_friends&quot;&gt;Pen Friends&lt;/a&gt; - two
pen friends meet and remember what they read in the letter and find affirmations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/an_illustration&quot;&gt;An illustration&lt;/a&gt; -
both players suggest a pose for each other, play a scene and each end up
in suggested poses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/the_conscience&quot;&gt;The Conscience&lt;/a&gt; -
play a scene, any player can become other player Conscience (i.e. give commands,
express doubt etc) for some time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/countdown&quot;&gt;Countdown&lt;/a&gt; - perform a scene
in time X, then exactly the same scene in X/2 and so on until you get to
10 seconds. After that do “a photo moment” - just one pose from the scene.
This works better with a lot of movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general any game where 2 players do something and moderator somehow affects
them (like “New Choice”) can be attempted just by 2 players alone. Each player then can affect
the other player in the same way (like saying “New Choice”). You may need to agree on your
intention before the game, e.g. saying “Next Choice” can be done to make the scene funnier
or when the person does not like what the other person said.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="improv" /><category term="improvisation" /><summary type="html">I tried impro recently (aka improv, improvisation theater). I did extremely enjoy the experience, but also felt like I didn’t get enough out of the workshops (they are surprisingly crowded). Thus, I will try to practice in much smaller groups (like 2 people). This can be challenging since majority of games are for more people. Here is my compilation of warmup and “main course” impro games for 2 people.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 8)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-8" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 8)" /><published>2019-05-21T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-8">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 8, recognizing relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;follow-up-to-previous-lecture&quot;&gt;Follow-up to previous lecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heritability&quot;&gt;Heritability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that humans have 5 fingers is an inherited trait.
However, the variability of #fingers is exclusively due to environment, thus, heritability
is 0%. People often assume that heritability tells whether a trait is inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;previous-disciplines&quot;&gt;Previous disciplines&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous three approaches (behavioral evolution, molecular genetics, behavioral genetics)
are just descriptions at different levels. For example one can view epigenetics as either of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way how culture and environment affects biology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way in which environment turns genes on/off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regulation of chromatin, remodeling, regulation of genes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;behavioral-genetics&quot;&gt;Behavioral genetics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;classical - adoption studies, good at showing that environment has less impact than assumed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modern - we suspect that a given gene has some behavioral effect, let’s see which.
Alternatively, we suspect that this behavior is genetic - let’s see the link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;observed-effect-size&quot;&gt;Observed effect size&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When evaluating studies, keep the observed difference size in mind.
For example, there was a study of 250k 18 years old in Norway, which has shown that 
first borns have higher IQ than second borns. There could be multiple ways to explain this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parental investment - no, they controlled for this, if you are the only child, you have
lower IQ than first born with younger siblings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Tutoring” phenomenon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mother age (egg quality) - they controlled for this too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each pregnancy causes immune suppression, a mother could become less healthy after the first pregnancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to age 12 second borns have higher IQ than first borns. By age 18 it gets other way around.
A second born IQ reverts to the level of first born, if the first born dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the difference was only 2.3 IQ points (as Sapolsky says “sneeze at the IQ test
and you get this difference”), i.e. not important at all (even though the study has been done
in a very elaborate fashion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-8-recognizing-relatives&quot;&gt;Lecture 8: Recognizing relatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ability to recognize relatives can be present even in very primitive organisms. E.g. deer mice have 2 strains -
monogamous and polygamous, the later has sperm competition. When sperm forms a clump,
it travels better. However, in polygamous strain sperm tries to form a clump only with its own kind. 
In the monogamous strain, this is not the case (happily forming a clump with any sperm).
In the polygamous case, sperm “knows” who it is related. This is example of single cells recognizing
relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can show innate relative recognition by cross fostering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanisms&quot;&gt;Mechanisms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pheromones&quot;&gt;Pheromones&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pheromonal communication can be used for relative recognition. 
One needs qualitative differences e.g. in urine (reflecting genetic makeup)
and some mechanism to process the differences. This is achieved by creating a completely
unique protein (major histocompatibility complex), which functions like a fingerprint.
This protein is attached to each of your cells (at the surface). Your immune system
uses it to detect your own cells. This protein can become soluble
(saliva, urine) and give unique signature to pheromones coming off of you.
These protein structure is also more similar in closer relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxytocin and vasoprasin tune cells in olfactory system for better accuracy to recognize relatives and,
if the match is good, take care of them (e.g. baby after birth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only 2 areas in the brain, which have neurogenesis (new neurons generation) in adults  - hippocampus (learning) and behind olfactory bulb.
In rats, new neurons in the olfactory bulb are created before giving birth. This way the mother can detect her babies better and
bond to them. This can explain weird sense of smell during pregnancy as well as a desire for unusual
foods. Basically, olfactory system gets heavily renovated to improve accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons distinguish social implications of dominance reversal depending on family relatedness
(if rank 4 submits to rank 27 - others have no interest if 4 and 27 are from the same family - “crazy relatives”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mating, one has contradicting goals - prevent inbreeding, but to pass as much of their own genes as possible.
As a result, mating with the 3rd cousin (i.e. two of your grandparents are siblings, i.e. had the same parents) is the optimal solution.
This is observed in nature. Humans also find the odor of 3rd cousin the most appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;non-innate-recognition&quot;&gt;Non innate recognition&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non innate recognition requires imprinting, i.e. learning who’s mother / baby.
The fact that learning occurs is innate. One can learn sounds, odor or appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goats don’t have innate ability to recognize relatives. Instead there are other approximations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“smells like my vaginal fluids”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lick the kid and “smells like my saliva”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scent mark and “smells like me”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mouth smells like my milk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be used to detect siblings as well, e.g. “smells like my mom vaginal fluid”.
This can be proven by cross fostering, the goat will take longer to decide (“hm, it does not smell
that much like my vaginal fluid”), but in the end will take care of the kid anyway (“but there is no other baby,
so yeah, it must be mine”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cognitive&quot;&gt;Cognitive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans do it cognitively. Hey, I see this one baby around me, it must be the one I just gave birth too.
Who was the father? The only guy with whom I had sex. To detect sibling - “I saw mom giving birth to them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons can also do this. Males care about kids more when they are sure.
E.g. “if I am the only one who mated with her” (for example, female can be too young and
not that fertile, thus, no interest from higher rank baboons and, as a result, mate with exactly one lower rank baboon).
They also consider probabilities - the closer to female’s prime fertility point a baboon mated with her,
the more likely he is to take care of the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works even in fish. In sunfish males are very paternal. If you bring another male
(e.g. in an transparent container) between a female and a male (closer to the female), the latter male will assume
that he is not the father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusiform cortex is used to recognize faces.
Normally it fires more for relatives (e.g. mom &amp;gt; stranger &amp;gt; chair).
In autistic people it does not work well (mom ~ stranger ~ chair).
Sheep and pigeons have it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babies can distinguish mom smell after birth (but not dad’s) - when given two sources of smell,
they prefer one with mom’s smell. The can recognize mom’s voice (by learning it from inside),
but not dad’s (hard to hear it from inside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this affect your decision who to mate with?
One study considered Kibbutz in Israel, a collective community, which raises their kids all together.
If two kids were raised in the same age group up to 6 years of age, they never marry each other.
In other words, if it is someone, who you spend a lot of time before 6 years of age, you don’t mate with them
(they are more like a sibling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ways to manipulate us to feel more/less related than we are (pseudo kinship / pseudo speciation).
Military does this a lot (us - brothers, them - non-humans).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 8, recognizing relatives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The luckiest investor or what if you knew the future?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/luckiest-investor-or-investing-when-knowing-the-future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The luckiest investor or what if you knew the future?" /><published>2019-05-19T07:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-19T07:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/luckiest_investor_or_investing_when_knowing_the_future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/luckiest-investor-or-investing-when-knowing-the-future">&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have 1000 USD on the evening of 31st of December, 2017. In addition to that
you happen to know daily prices of all US stocks in 2018. How much money could
you make by taking into account the future and investing perfectly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this does not have that much practical sense, since we don’t know the future.
However, I was curious how “knowing the future” outperforms passive investing.
In other words this could be in some sense an upper for investment returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is complex, so let’s make a bunch of assumptions to simplify the problem a bit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On a given day, only one of the following actions is allowed:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Buy one position with all your cash at the lowest price available during that day.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Sell everything at the highest price available that day.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Do nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transactions are free.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One can buy only securities, which are available at 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://iextrading.com/developer/docs/#getting-started&quot;&gt;IEX&lt;/a&gt; (I had to get the data somewhere).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All transactions succeed no matter what (e.g. volumes are ignored).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One can buy fractional shares.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may look like holding at most one position at a time is limiting. However, the optimal
trading sequence is like that. Imagine that you bought more than one stock. Then you sold them
and got some profit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imagine you got the same profit from both. Then you could have bought only
one of them originally and the overall sequence profit would have stayed exactly the same.
In other words, if the first sequence (with more than one stock at a time) is optimal, then
the resulting sequence with at most one stock at a time is also optimal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;otherwise, one of them brings more profit. Thus, if you buy only this better stock (instead of two stocks),
you will only improve overall sequence profit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a simplistic proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the results. This way if you are not interested in all the details,
you don’t have to waste your time going through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you get 2235976324368894910070981708437303314132384811588503138465677325225209962386423808 USD.
Yeap, for people confused, this is 2.2e+81 USD. 
&amp;lt;here goes a default boring comparison with number of atoms in the universe&amp;gt;.
This is equivalent to 63.93% return on investment, &lt;strong&gt;daily&lt;/strong&gt;. 
A lot, right? Penny stocks happened to be very volatile, you know.
And in order to achieve this, you just needed to do 
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/post_resources/luckiest_investor/sequence_with_penny_stocks.html&quot;&gt;these 107 transactions&lt;/a&gt;.
Easy-peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, now this feels boring and less exciting than I expected it to be.
Moreover, I feel like buying stocks for 2.2e+81 USD can be tricky these days.
What if we forbid penny stocks? In particular, let’s not buy anything cheaper than 5 USD per share.
Boom, 1537713047211124526310105417510931136512 USD (i.e. 1.5e+39, daily ROI 25.64%,
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/post_resources/luckiest_investor/sequence_without_penny_stocks.html&quot;&gt;transactions&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Argh, this is still just some unrealistically large number. And I don’t recognize literally any of these stocks.
Ok, let’s get &lt;em&gt;really conservative&lt;/em&gt; here and restrict ourselves to S&amp;amp;P 500 only. 
Buying penny stocks can be tricky to execute, trading volumes can be low, volatility may be too &lt;em&gt;volatile&lt;/em&gt;.
So S&amp;amp;P 500, it is. And… &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;30 853 548 412.13 USD&lt;/code&gt; (i.e. 3.1e+10, i.e. just almost 31 billions, ROI 3.1e+09%, daily 4.84%).
So what did you have to do? Just 
&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/post_resources/luckiest_investor/sequence_s_p_500.html&quot;&gt;these dozen of dozens transactions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so this is now much more interesting (at least for me). The number is somewhat realistic
and the first transaction involves AMD, which I know. I declare this a success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious, my code is available in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/merelycurious/luckiest-investor-data-analysis&quot;&gt;this Github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-research&quot;&gt;Further research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am curious to look more into “S&amp;amp;P 500 only” transactions, e.g.
how long each company was in the portfolio, how large their relative impact
on the final result was and so on. However, this post already took 7 hours
and I haven’t even started writing the methodology yet. Moreover,
I decided that I will have breakfast only after finishing this post
and it is 12:03 already and I am starving now. And I have super tasty curry in the fridge,
which I cooked yesterday. Obviously, it was not my original plan to eat curry for breakfast,
but it is also not strictly a breakfast anymore. So I hope you understand me (and curry)
and I may write another post about this some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pretty sure you all would love to know how I got the numbers above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dataset&quot;&gt;Dataset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I needed to get daily prices from somewhere, 
so I took them from iextrading.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://iextrading.com/developer/docs/&quot;&gt;API docs&lt;/a&gt;).
These folks don’t even require registration (i.e. you don’t need an API key),
which is great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For S&amp;amp;P 500 I just used &lt;a href=&quot;https://datahub.io/core/s-and-p-500-companies#data&quot;&gt;some random datahub.io csv dataset&lt;/a&gt;,
which was built from Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;optimization&quot;&gt;Optimization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have the numbers, how do we find the optimal sequence of transactions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key observation here is that if we have X shares of a given stock Y on day
Z, then we don’t care at all how we arrived in this state. E.g. we could have bought
them yesterday or 1 week ago, but this has zero effect on the final outcome 
(i.e. amount of money we have in the end).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allows us to apply so-called dynamic programming. Basically for each day of
2018 and each available stock 
we want to calculate the maximum amount of that stock we could have had.
I.e. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[2018-03-14][APPL]&lt;/code&gt; is a maximal number of APPL stock
we could have had on Pi day in 2018 (i.e. by doing optimal transactions before).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the problem definition, we know that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[2017-12-31][$]&lt;/code&gt; is 1000
and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[2017-12-31][&amp;lt;any stock&amp;gt;]&lt;/code&gt; is 0 (we have 1000 USD and no stocks
at the beginning).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we can notice that we can calculate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt; + 1]&lt;/code&gt; if we know
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt;]&lt;/code&gt;. If we are in a some state on some date, there are only
3 actions we can perform:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hold what we have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we have cash, buy something&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if we have something, sell and get cash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we can just go over all states, try to perform the action and see whether
this improves the result for the new state. For example, buying stock X means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt; + 1][&amp;lt;stock X&amp;gt;] = 
	max(best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt; + 1][&amp;lt;stock X&amp;gt;],
	    best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt;][$] / &amp;lt;price of X on &amp;lt;date + 1&amp;gt;&amp;gt;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, imagine that you have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[&amp;lt;date&amp;gt;][$]&lt;/code&gt; USD on the day &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;date&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (evening)
and you want to buy &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;stock X&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. You can do this by waiting until tomorrow, i.e. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;date + 1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;
and just buying that stock according to the current price. Why do we have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;max&lt;/code&gt;?
Because there may be other better ways to get more of this stock (e.g. by buying it earlier
at a cheaper price and just holding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing this for each date and each symbol, we get our final answer in 
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[2018-12-31][$]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to get the actual optimal sequence of transactions? Each time some &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity&lt;/code&gt; is improved,
we can just save which action has led to this improvement (i.e. from which state
we got there). Using this information, we can easily see how we got to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;best_quantity[2018-12-31][$]&lt;/code&gt; and 
go to the previous state. And then just repeat this process of going backwards, until we reach our initial state
of having 1000 USD. Once we know 2 adjacent states, reverse engineering which action it was is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;issues&quot;&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this wasn’t as smooth as I expected (and I have to explain spending at least 7 hours on this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;noisy-data&quot;&gt;Noisy data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly the issue was with weird prices in the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, my first attempts returned something like 10^124 USD, which was
somewhat larger than I expected. After inspecting the proposed sequence of stocks,
I discovered some very lucrative transactions, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2018-05-30 buy ZAZZT 7.87048936311242e+47 @ 0.9  
2018-05-31 sell ZAZZT 8.185301067147553e+52 @ 103999.9  ROI = 115554.44444444444
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and in the data it was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; ['2018-05-29', None, None, None, 0.9],
 ['2018-05-30', None, None, None, 0.9],
 ['2018-05-31', 87359.95, 103999.9, 103999.9, 87359.95],
 ['2018-06-01', None, None, None, 87359.95],
 ['2018-06-04', None, None, None, 87359.95],
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which looked very fishy, so I just dropped all price points where at least one value was missing
(i.e. 35098 price points out of 1962200, i.e. 1.7% - yeah, I was worried to drop too much, so I checked
the percentage).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brought the result down to $10^115. This time the transactions were less awkward, but still odd.
Example culprit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2018-02-12 buy ZWZZT 2.5002156249822376e+16 @ 12.5  
2018-02-14 sell ZWZZT 1.600121998608632e+21 @ 63999.36  ROI = 5118.9488
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; ['2018-02-09', None, None, None, 18.1],
 ['2018-02-12', 12.5, 12.5, 12.5, 12.5],
 ['2018-02-13', None, None, None, 12.5],
 ['2018-02-14', 5, 63999.36, 63999.36, 5],
 ['2018-02-15', None, None, None, 5],
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like an outlier.
Thus, let’s kick out price points with all 4 values being the same
(65112 out of 1927102) and with max-min ratio larger than 10 (20 points out of 
remaining 1861990).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gets us down to $10^84.
The only suspiciously large ROI now was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2018-10-04 buy ZXZZT 5.209604829132704e+61 @ 10.86  
2018-10-10 sell ZXZZT 6.338984640830725e+66 @ 121678.8  ROI = 11203.309392265193
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fighting this one was not obvious, so I started looking at trading volumes as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; ['2018-10-03', 100, None, None, None, 10],
 ['2018-10-04', 1200, 10.86, 11, 11, 10.86],
 ['2018-10-05', 100, None, None, None, 10.86],
 ['2018-10-08', 835, 0.0072, 0.0072, 0.0072, 0.0072],
 ['2018-10-09', 800, 168998.31, 168998.31, 168998.31, 168998.31],
 ['2018-10-10', 400, 121678.79, 121678.8, 121678.79, 121678.8],
 ['2018-10-11', 100, None, None, None, 121678.8],
 ['2018-10-12', 300, 115198.85, 127998.72, 127998.72, 115198.85],
 ['2018-10-15', 400, 99999.9, 100000, 100000, 99999.9],
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity I just removed all price points with less than 1000 trading volume
(51610 out of remaining 1861970).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave 2.235976324368895e+81, which you have already seen above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;penny-stocks&quot;&gt;Penny stocks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After morally accepting that number, I noticed that majority of the transactions are just penny stocks anyway, 
which is not that interesting (they are volatile as crazy). So I just stopped “buying” anything cheaper than $5 per share.
I know that not all of these are penny stocks, but this affects only 226071 price points
(and I am hungry, remember the curry), so the limit is $5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brought us down to 1.5377130472111245e+39 USD, which still didn’t feel completely satisfying.
So that’s how I started limiting stocks to S&amp;amp;P 500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I am going to finally eat my curry (“Hooray!” says my stomach).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="investing" /><category term="stocks" /><category term="coding" /><category term="mini-project" /><summary type="html">Imagine that you have 1000 USD on the evening of 31st of December, 2017. In addition to that you happen to know daily prices of all US stocks in 2018. How much money could you make by taking into account the future and investing perfectly?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 7)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 7)" /><published>2019-05-14T07:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-14T07:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-7">&lt;p&gt;Slowly (but steadily) going through the Sapolsky’s course. Lecture 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-7-behavioral-genetics-ii&quot;&gt;Lecture 7: Behavioral Genetics II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genetic-packages-metro-dogs-example&quot;&gt;Genetic packages (metro dogs example)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example similar to the domesticated Siberian foxes case is metro dogs in Russia.
They are effectively selected for avoiding humans, being in packs and aggressive temperament.
As a result, they start looking like wolves very fast (e.g. tail shape). This appearance is not needed
for their survival, but it comes as one genetic package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behavioral-genetics-approaches&quot;&gt;Behavioral genetics approaches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern version of behavioral genetics tries to find a gene for something. 
In the classic version, a phenotype was considered and then individual genes
were compared in individuals, which have different phenotype trait (e.g. eye color),
i.e. something external. Alternatively one can look at proteins and how they function (i.e. an intermediate step between
genes and traits). Finally one can investigate differences of protein sizes (without knowing
the precise function). However, this works only in “simpler” cases, like looking for a gene
for a specific disease like PKU, cystic fibrosis (but not TV taste). Now find a family where
approximately half has the disease. Find a segment of DNA which everyone with the disease 
has, but no one without. This usually gives you a stretch of DNA consisting of 10-30 genes.
Somewhere in this sequence there is “the gene”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges&quot;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One must be very certain in the conclusions before claiming anything
(e.g. ways to detect diseases can be used to decide whether to abort pregnancies).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bio ethics - there is a very low statistical chance that you’ve got a wrong marker.
Should people get tested for the disease using these markers anyway?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finding “the gene” - most diseases are not caused by one gene. There are ways to find multiple genes,
e.g. gene microarrays (which involves forcing a cell to produce all RNA it has and then gluing it on a chip,
keyword: QTL).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-with-gene&quot;&gt;Starting with gene&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach is to start from a gene and to study it across species.
E.g. you have 2 different versions of a gene and try to see differences in behavior,
protein function or size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Issue - this way you look only where “the light is shining”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vasopressin hormone - in rodents (vole) its receptor defines
whether an individual is monogamous or polygamous. The difference is in promoter.
After discovering this, one can ask whether this holds for people and try to see the differences.
It does actually hold - if you have the monogamous promoter - more stable relationships. How good one at reading faces also
depends on this. Families with autism have mutations in vasopressin receptor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BNDF protein - prompts growing new neurons. In rats causes creation of new connections in amygdala
and impacts anxiety levels. There are different versions of it. You can study this in rats and then in people (this has been done). In humans the type of this protein identifies likelihood of anxiety disorder and level of stress hormones in blood.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dopamine (DF4 in rodents) - defines levels of risk-taking behavior in humans (novelty seeking).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NPY - differences of levels of anxiety in humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, all of these explain only a small portion of overall variability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;role-of-random-events-chance&quot;&gt;Role of random events (chance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brownian motion - intrinsic movements of molecules (completely random).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mitochondria has their own DNA and there can be different mitochondria DNA in one cell (mitochondria divides on its own). When a cell splits, the resulting set of mitochondria DNA in each daughter is random (based on 
position of mitochondria in the cell during the split).
The same is true for transcription factors and splicing enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, it is not “Nature + Nurture”, but “Nature + Nurture + Chance”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;heritability&quot;&gt;Heritability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All such studies result in some statement like “this trait has 53% heritability”.
The meaning of this is often misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heritability does not tell how genes affect average value of a given trait,
but instead the degree of variability around the average.
E.g. imagine a trait with values 9, 10, 11 and another trait with values 1, 10, 19.
In both cases the average is 10, but the variability is larger in the second case.
In this example heritability does not tell how much genes determine the average value 10,
but variability instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example - imagine a plant with 3 versions of a gene (A, B and C) defining how well it retains water.
There is a difference of this trait across A, B and C (i.e. this gene has good predictive power).
At the same time environment affects it much more, thus, heritability is actually low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/7_environment_vs_genes.png&quot; alt=&quot;A histogram showing environment affecting the trait value much more than the gene&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you happen to study only one environment, it will look like genes are much more important than they actually are.
Unfortunately, that’s how science mostly works (take one species like some dessert rat and study it, i.e.
control for environment). This removes ability to see the role of environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random peculiar fact - how to measure protein size - put them somewhere where they move as a
function of their size and measure difference in position (e.g. sinking in a gel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you had to predict trait level - would you choose environment or genes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans inhabit a lot of environments. There are gene-environment interactions, which can change gene effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying only one environment inflates heritability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Heritability of number of fingers in humans. Genes define “5”, but not variability. The variability is 
e.g. due to industrial incidents. Thus, 0% heritability.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Men with earing in 1950 were rare, but almost all women had earrings. The variability is caused by gender,
thus, 100% heritability (if you had to guess, you would love to know individual’s gender).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;environment-is-important&quot;&gt;Environment is important&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples where environment plays crucial role in the outcome:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PKU is related to a disorder, when toxic phenylaline cannot be turned into a safer thing inside the body. 
To predict the disease, would you like to know where the person lives or whether there is a mutation
in the enzyme? Obviously, mutation, 100% heritability. But the disease highly depends on food.
One can avoid certain foods and don’t be affected by the disease.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider another gene, which is related to depression.
  There are 2 versions - “good” and “bad”, which affect how prone to depression one is.
  However, this also depends on number of major childhood stressors they had 
  (divorce, loss of parent). What do these genes do? It depends on your environment.
  If you have no stressors, then the “bad” version actually makes you less prone to depressions
  (the study observed tiny differences).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/7_depression_gene.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing the &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; gene being better without any stressors, but much worse with stressors.&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The number of stressors actually defines level of stress hormones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is a gene, which affects predisposition to aggression. The graph is the same as above, but the horizontal
axis is “child abuse”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FAD2 - predicts IQ abilities and is involved in carbohydrates metabolism.
The environment in this case is “breast feeding”.
I.e. it predicts IQ abilities, if you have a diet high in carbohydrates very early in life.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On average men are better at math than women. 
However, is this genetic? When studied all over the world, 
the greater the gender inequality was, the larger was the difference in math scores.
It is not a function of gender, but the society type. In Iceland (smallest gender inequality)
girls are even slightly better at math than boys. If we wanted to guess, we would rather 
known whether they are from Tunisia or Iceland. Even when considering top 1%, this is still
not much about genes (in the US in 1950 the ratio was 13 boys to 1 girl, nowadays - 3 to 1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more environments you study, the lower heritability is going to be. We are giving more opportunities to
say “it depends”. As a result, it is meaningless to ask “what does this gene do?”, instead it should be
“what does this gene do in this particular environment?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single genes define a lot for flies. Even when you see a gene for X,
is it just an indirect effect (like height causing being an extrovert)?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Slowly (but steadily) going through the Sapolsky’s course. Lecture 7.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your time networth</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-networth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your time networth" /><published>2019-05-12T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-12T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly_networth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-networth">&lt;p&gt;Many people know how many percents of their networth is invested in X.
However, occasionally it is much more important how you invest your time.
I call this  (surprise) “time allocation”. Let’s see how to do this and a couple
of unexpected examples, where percentage looks much scarier than the plain number of hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trigger&quot;&gt;Trigger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started looking into this topic to estimate how much “free” time I normally
have per week. The idea was to make sure that, when I plan something for a given week, I don’t set
obviously unreasonable goals. At first this wasn’t anything special,
I just used some quick spreadsheet and got the numbers. However, then I checked
the percentages (i.e. how many percent of my weekly time a given activity takes)
and was surprised by how much I underestimated them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beauty&quot;&gt;Beauty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way of looking at your time allocation has many interesting properties.
For example, if you do some activity every week (let’s imagine for the rest of your life),
then this weekly time allocation becomes “rest of your life” time allocation.
This definitely makes you feel differently. This implicitly forces you to prioritize:
“Wait, this will take 10% of my life, do I actually need to do this?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another observation is that time is your main resource.
Yes, you can use money for some approximation, but money is just 
a representation of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I know how you spend your money and your asset allocation, I do know
a lot about you. But knowing how you spend your time, gives away almost everything about you,
except your reasons for doing something, i.e. “why”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common advice to look at what people do and not what they say.
This exercise partially helps you to look at what you do, instead of what you 
feel you do or want to do. People are bad at estimates and it is very easy to say
I am X (e.g. writer) and feel like you spend enough time on this activity.
What if you discover that only 5% of your weekly time goes to X?
Are you then just 5% of a writer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be peculiar to know at the end of a life how much time went 
into something. This could be some kind of ultimate measure, how much of a writer
a person was. Obviously, different activities consume time differently, so it may be
that you are indeed a writer, this just didn’t require that much time.
I agree. I don’t claim that this “answers your life question” or that it is completely perfect.
No, but it gives an interesting perspective, which I enjoy and find useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it may be tricky to get a complete picture, since majority
of things we do are not repeated across weeks. I suggest you to start with at least
something and just consider activities you do weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely plan to explore better time tracking (probably at a very low granularity
for a short period of time). I do track my expenses, so optimizing time is an obvious next target.
Having this data would help me to get a better picture of my actual time allocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to&quot;&gt;How to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you are now intrigued enough to give it a try.
I prepared 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qa4PZYtSACpZm2HEDDgZvoeXUAIYOmeBvLWaJYeERyQ/edit&quot;&gt;a spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;,
which you can reuse (just make a copy).
5 minutes granularity was reasonable for me, so that’s what
the spreadsheet has, however, you are welcome to use 1 hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically each cell means “how I spend the next 5 minutes”.
Below there are cells with all the calculations (sums and ratios).
The data is just an example to give you an idea what you can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how various activity durations correspond to percentages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour daily -&amp;gt; 1 hour / day * 7 days / (168 hours / week) = 4.1% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour every working day -&amp;gt; 1 hour / day * 5 days / (168 hours / week) = 2.9% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour once a week -&amp;gt; 1 hour / (168 hours / week) = 0.59% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 minute daily -&amp;gt; 1 minute / day * / (60 minutes / hour * 168 hours / week) = 0.069% week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is anyone asking your for a commitment taking 1 hour once a week
for the rest of your life? If you agree, you will “spend” 0.59% of the
rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-improvements&quot;&gt;Possible improvements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously everyone has to sleep and do exercises and this is good.
However, when these are taken into account in the denominator, we are
implicitly incentivized to spend less time on them. This feels wrong.
Thus, you may subtract some activities from denominator (i.e. from 168 hours per week, sleep is
an obvious candidate) to mitigate this issue. For my use case,
this was not needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy conscious time planning!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="exercise" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="self improvement" /><category term="different perspective" /><summary type="html">Many people know how many percents of their networth is invested in X. However, occasionally it is much more important how you invest your time. I call this (surprise) “time allocation”. Let’s see how to do this and a couple of unexpected examples, where percentage looks much scarier than the plain number of hours.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRE is a marathon, not a sprint</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-marathon-not-sprint" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRE is a marathon, not a sprint" /><published>2019-04-30T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-30T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_marathon_not_sprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-marathon-not-sprint">&lt;p&gt;I’ve caught myself delaying a lot of (mostly pleasant) stuff to post FIRE times (i.e. quite far in the future).
Let’s see what caused this, what the risks are and how I now avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trigger&quot;&gt;Trigger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that I have somewhat burned myself out recently. This is definitely not the complete
burn out and I am getting much better now, but this made me revisit my lifestyle
and priorities. Overall, my wellbeing definitely suffered: I had pessimistic mood, which
changed often, and too much interest in food (aka overeating, mostly of sweet and fatty foods).
Previously I definitely had periods where I felt somewhat down, but I never experienced such
overeating before, which obviously scared me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis&quot;&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to find out what’s wrong and… googled it. I could have gone to the doctor,
but I prefer to spend couple minutes (ok, this is a lie, couple hours, whatever) researching
on my own to save the trip if the issue
is not too bad. There happens to be a lot food related psychological disorders and
some of them are very bizarre. I probably won’t go into many details here, since it is not
the most pleasant thing to read about. But one bit caught my eye - basically some website claimed
that one can overeat to compensate deficiency of fun in life. Eating sugary and fatty foods
is similar from chemical perspective in brain to consuming drugs and having fun and if you have too little fun
your body just tries to fix this by binging and overeating (as the last available resort to have some fun).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-causes&quot;&gt;Possible causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suspicion is that aiming for FIRE can promote such state.
It may sound weird, but doing something fun actually requires some effort
(at least you have to do something not-so-fun before it becomes fun, like going somewhere or
preparing something). So if one uses their energy efficiently (aka just being lazy), they are
in some sense disincentivized to do something fun due to the effort involved.
Normally, the positive side of the activity is so strong that people don’t even notice
the effort involved at all or it is masked by anticipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, FIRE adds another reason against doing something - money.
You’ve already cut out a bunch of unimportant stuff from your life and pretty much got 
used to this way of thinking - do I really need this? What I am actually paying for here with my money (i.e. time)?
So when considering doing something fun, now we have at least 2 reasons against it.
First, it requires some effort. Second, money. It is also peculiar that this “money saving
perspective” affects one’s default choice. Normally people would rather do 
some fun activity by default if they are not sure. But after cutting out so much garbage,
a person aiming for FIRE will rather have “not go” by default. Moreover, sometimes answering 
“do I actually like or need this at all and which exactly part of it and why?” is tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if one does side hustling to reach FIRE faster, this can produce another
heavy argument against doing something fun. In particular, one can think:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I will rather reach FIRE sooner by side hustling now. Then I will have all
the fun in the world. Ok, back to side hustling now instead of this “fun” activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is already the third brick against the fun activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it is very easy to focus on FIRE and delay (or even ignore) everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risks&quot;&gt;Risks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One risk is your body disagreeing. This is just my personal anecdote, but I suspect that
this is a very likely outcome. A peculiar consequence of this (a wild speculation) is the risk
to change your overall view to FIRE. Imagine that you work hard, focus on FIRE and ignore everything 
else. Your dissatisfaction may grow and get collected inside you. At some point you can just snap
and overcompensate all the way out of FIRE completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting option is that this may affect your post FIRE life negatively.
Imagine that you’ve been finding reasons why a bunch of fun activities (like going to a
theater, but insert something else if your opinion of fun is different, I understand)
are not that interesting to you.
And then on one magical day you conclude that you are now FIRE and have plenty of time
to actually do all the fun… Oh, wait, is there anything fun left? You’ve been finding
reasons against going to the theater for years, will reaching FIRE magically switch
something in your brain and you will forget all these reasons? I doubt that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this boundary between having fun and spending too much is very faint and narrow.
So you probably might overshoot a bit. To avoid that I would suggest to see by how much having fun
does delay your FIRE date. If it is something like 1-2 month, this is comparable to
error margin (e.g. due to the market mood swings) and seems pretty safe. I understand that you
can be very rational and having your fun budget invested will improve your FIRE chances
and date, but if you then overstretch yourself, forget rationality and drop FIRE idea completely?
So 1-2 months seems fine, everything else is up to you. This is your life and your money
and you probably shouldn’t trust Internet when deciding what to do with them (but I use 1-2 month
approach, just FYI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I made &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/pages/calculator.html&quot;&gt;a calculator&lt;/a&gt; precisely for that
 (disclaimer: this is the very early version, so early that I can’t even call it first). Basically it allows
you to answer question “if I decrease my investing by X once/every month/year, how much does this delay my FIRE date?”
and X is meant to be your fun budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally started to catch myself whenever I have some positive feeling towards doing something fun.
Instead of shooing it away with “I am busy, perhaps come back later?”, I stop and remind myself that
I haven’t been doing anything fun for ages and my wellbeing has taken a hit and occasionally it is
tricky to understand what I really enjoy, so I should probably do this activity. I definitely keep in
mind the money aspect (e.g. I still have fun efficiently, for example, by choosing the cheapest theater ticket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also hope to stop delaying various ideas and projects. I understand that they may not speed up
my FIRE process, but I would rather build my small scale version of FIRE life now and then upscale it
once reaching FIRE instead of being completely demotivated and having no clue what to do with all
the free time I’ve got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish you a fun path to your FIRE!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="FIRE" /><category term="perspective" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">I’ve caught myself delaying a lot of (mostly pleasant) stuff to post FIRE times (i.e. quite far in the future). Let’s see what caused this, what the risks are and how I now avoid this.</summary></entry></feed>