<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-17T12:49:26+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lectures 1-3)</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lectures 1-3)" /><published>2019-03-17T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-17T12:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3">&lt;p&gt;I watch “Human Behavioral Biology” course by Robest Sapolsky (from Stanford) on Youtube.
It is very interesting. Here is my summary of the first three lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-1-introduction-to-human-behavioral-biology&quot;&gt;Lecture 1: “Introduction to Human Behavioral Biology”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-the-course-is-about&quot;&gt;What the course is about&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is common between “having a period”, “having a brain tumor”, “eating a lot of junk food” and “taking anabolic steroids”?
All have been succesfully used in courts as a defense for a murderer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points of the course:
1) Sometimes what happens in your body can dramatically influence what happens in your brain (examples above).
2) Sometimes something in your head can affect your entire body (e.g. when one imagines that they will die
their heart starts beating faster).
In other words, the course is about the connection between physiology and behavior, emotions, memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;categorical-thinking&quot;&gt;Categorical thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We divide everything into categories, because this makes it easier to store information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/1_spectrum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of spectrum divided into categories&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. it is much easier to remember whether you saw a triangle, a square or a circle than some weird shape,
because we don’t have a word (i.e. a category) for latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages of categorical thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t differentiate two facts that fall in the same category (b &amp;amp; p in Finnish or two similar colors) - you underestimate their difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have trouble seeing how similar things are right across the category boundaries (e.g. 65% on the test leads to fail and 66% to pass) - we overestimate the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you pay attention to boundaries, you miss the big picture (e.g. phone numbers are supposed to be 3 digits followed by 4).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoiding-categorical-thinking&quot;&gt;Avoiding categorical thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the course is to think about biology of behavior without falling into categorical thinking.
The category (bucket) you are in affects how you explain the world. We want to avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 main challenges - recognizing when we:
1) just like other animals and accepting that. E.g. ovulation syncronization in females living together.
2) we appear to be like any other organism, but do something very different.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chess master capturing a piece feeling like a baboon who won a fight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we get stressed when reading something bad happening to a character in a novel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can feel compasionate about other species. This is the same physiology as in other animals, but we use it in unrecognizable ways.
3) do something that no other animal even remotely does (e.g. non=reproductive sex, language use).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course we will overview various buckets first - evolution, molecular genetics.
Then we will look at behaviors and consider them through each bucket separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-2-behavioral-evolution-i&quot;&gt;Lecture 2: Behavioral Evolution I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darwin didn’t discover evolution. He came up with a mechanism for it - natural selection.
Darwinian evolution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are heritable traits (i.e. genetic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is variability among those traits (ways in which they can occur)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some versions of those traits are more adaptive (work better for you) then others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is not about survival, but reproduction.
When you have all of these, you get evolution and populations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you add mutations - you can get large changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies well to physiology, but how to apply this to behavior? Exactly the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are heritable behaviors (i.e. behaviors have genetic components, this is an important assumption)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;types/classes of behaviors have variation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some are more adaptive than others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a false belief that &lt;del&gt;“animals behave for the good of the species”&lt;/del&gt;.
Actually animals behave to pass as many copies of their genes as possible (reproduction of the fittest).
Sometimes this may look like behavior for the good of the species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ways to pass your genes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individual selection - maximize number of times you reproduce through natural selection (useful traits improving
adaptability) and sexual selection (arbitrary trais).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kin selection - helping out relatives to reproduce (cooperate with relatives to a different degree, which depends on how
closely they are related to you) by decreasing your own reproductive success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reciprical altruism - cooperation among non-relatives, but it must be reciprical (you must get something out of it and not
more than you put it), e.g. group hunting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prisoner-dilema&quot;&gt;Prisoner Dilema&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reciprical altruism leads to cheating and being good at detecting cheating against you. When to cheat and when to cooperate is studied in game theory. The basic “model” is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&quot;&gt;Prisoner Dilema&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tit-for-tat-strategy&quot;&gt;“Tit for Tat” strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cooperate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next time:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If they cooperated last time, you cooperate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Otherwise you cheat&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nice (kind)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retaliates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forgiving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deterministic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drives other strategies into extintion when multiple agents play multiples games with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a vulnerability - signal error. 
What if there is a posibility of a mistake (noise in the signal),
e.g. cooperation looks like cheating.
This wipes out 50% of cooperation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  ++-+-+...
  +++-+-...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;forgiving-tit-for-tat-ftft&quot;&gt;Forgiving Tit for Tat (fTfT)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improved version of TfT. 
Like normal TfT but after “saw pattern” for 5 rounds - forgive and cooperate.
fTfT outcompetes TfT when you can have signal error.
It has another vulnerability - it can be exploited by strategies without forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tft---ftft&quot;&gt;“Tft -&amp;gt; fTfT”&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start off with pure TfT. If for N rounds the other party didn’t cheat, switch to fTfT.
I.e. you begin to “trust” someone and this protects you from signal error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pavlov&quot;&gt;Pavlov&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I do something and I get rewarded, do it again next time. If I lose, I switch.
This allows you to exploit someone, who is forgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random mention: “The political uses of madness” - an article by Daniel Ellsburg on the optimal benefits of perceived madness 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ThePoliticalUsesOfMadness&quot;&gt;source1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia600102.us.archive.org/20/items/ThePoliticalUsesOfMadness/ELS005-001.pdf&quot;&gt;source2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;examples-in-nature&quot;&gt;Examples in nature&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vampire bats. Females share their nest with non-relatives. Everyone feeds all babies.
When they think that one female cheats on them, they stop feeding her kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;black hamlet fish. They can change their gender. Pair of them flip their gender back and forth. Being female
is more “expensive”. If one fish ends up being a male too many times, other fish will stop cooperating with them
(TfT).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lion. Non-relatives in a pride. If you fake a sound of other lion in the bush, in many prides one lion
stays behind the group, while all other go to check and risk by doing this. However, this lion is not punished.
In real world you can have many ongoing games at the same time or others just don’t pay attention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;naked mole-rat. Big cooperative colonies (possibly non-relatives). 1-2 animals don’t do any work, but no 
one punishes them. They are even larger, because they eat more. However, when the rainy season comes
they plug the entry to the tunnel with their bodies (example of another ongoing “game” and role
diversification).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-behavior-analysis&quot;&gt;Application to behavior analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to use the fact that species maximize copies of their genes to analyze behavior? 
Imagine that we have two skulls - one male and one female.
Just by their relative size to each other we can conclude a lot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Males much larger&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Males the same&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;male aggression&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (their body is built for this and females select for this)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;variability in male reproductive success&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (5% males do 95% of reproduction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low (every male gets 1-2 kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;what females want&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;large body size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;“good personality” - parental behavior (e.g. male birds bring food to females as
evidence that they can feed kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;parental behavior in males&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low (not interested in kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (care about kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;life span&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high variation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;no difference by gender&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;twinning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rare (impossible to feed on your own)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more frequent (male helps to feed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;kids abandonment by females&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rare (kids will die for sure, male won’t take care)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more frequent (male will feed them anyway)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;species kind&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;tournament&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pair bonding monogamous&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;example&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;peacock (feathers show that you can waste a lot of energy)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;tamarin monkey (one can’t distinguish males and females visually)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could see this only by ratio of male and female skull sizes.
Humans fall in between these two kinds of species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-3-behavioral-evolution-ii&quot;&gt;Lecture 3: Behavioral Evolution II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use “individual maximizes number of copies of their genes” to explain more behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;explaining-infanticide&quot;&gt;Explaining infanticide&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babies are cute - they are trying to reduce aggression by this. There are species with infanticide (e.g. lions).
Patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adult male is the one killing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infants who are most likely to be offsprings of other males are killed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;average interbirth interval in females is larger than the average tenure of high ranking male.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the new alpha male e.g. just killed the previous one, but all females won’t ovulate
for 2.5 years, while you will be alpha male only for 1.5 years. Thus, by killing kids:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reproductive success of other males is decreased&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;females will start ovulating sooner (by stopping nursing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates that individuals optimize number of copies of their genes instead of doing good for the species.
Another example is mountain gorilla. They have infanticide even though they are at risk of extinction. 
In other words, they even endanger their species more to increase their own reproductive success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peculiarly infanticide does not happen if previous alpha was a relative.
Two male lions can even share a pride of they are brothers (adelphic polyandry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Females have developed number of adaptations due to this as well.
In some species females have spontaneous abortion due to smell of the new male
(there is no point to invest more resources into the kid, since it will be killed anyway).
Females can also try to protect their kids. If they are older, they will risk their life more
(they are less likely to have another kid). Maternal grandmothers defend even more (they won’t
reproduce at all).
Another strategy is to have pseudo estross (i.e. fake ovulation) during pregnancy.
The new male mates and thinks that the kid is his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons do blackmail kidnaping of kids. If alpha attacks an individual, they can grab
alpha’s kid implying “attack me and I will kill the kid”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gender-ratio-fluctuations&quot;&gt;Gender ratio fluctuations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tournament species having a son is a volatile way (gamble) to pass your geans (may work out
very well, but most likely won’t). Having a daughter is a conservative way (they will have few kids,
but with high probability). However, giving birth to a male requires more energy. Higher 
ranking females have more sons (can take the risks). During environment distress (e.g. famine)
more daughters are born. This can produce sex ratio fluctuations (having sons is better
when there are few males).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intrasexual-competition&quot;&gt;Intrasexual competition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Males and females can have different reproductive goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be achieved by means of imprinted genes - their effect depends on which parent they come from.
There is a genetic mechanism to achieve this. Examples of such genes and their usage in intrasexual competition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imprinted genes coming from father tend to improve fetal growth (i.e. the kid should get as much energy from
the female as possible, males in migratory species do not care about future reproduction of a particular female,
but only about their kid).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From mother - slow down fetal development (this particular kid is less important to a female than their overall
reproductive life).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mechanism malfunctions if one of the genes gets disabled due to a mutation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are imprinted genes, which work only after birth. E.g. from male one can get “suck more milk” (i.e.
get more calories from female). You only see this in tournament species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have imprinted genes. By their quantity we are again in between pair bonding and tournament species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sperm competition in polyandrous species.
In some fly species sperm makes toxins that kill sperm of other males.
However, they cause harm to females too.
This makes no sense for the good of species,
but does for individual success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direction-of-male-aggression&quot;&gt;Direction of male aggression&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are species (e.g. chimpanzee) with exogamy (individuals leaving the group after puberty to avoid
interbreading). If males leave the group - you get high aggression inside the group among males (they 
are not relatives). If females - among groups (chimpanzee genocide and border patrols). Human military tries
to create this kinship artificially, chimpanzees have it by nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooperation&quot;&gt;Cooperation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start cooperation by reintroducing highly interbread group (close relatives) into general population.
This small group can outcompete others (due to their kinship) and others are forced to start cooperating as well.
This is a push towards group selection (highly interbread group with kinship cooperation can drive others who don’t cooperate
to extintion). In humans - trust in business or low interest loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be the case that strategy A dominates B when there is only one individual in each group,
but A is dominated by B when there are many individuals in each group. E.g. a group of aggresive chickens would
injure each other. However, when there are only two chickens, an agressive one will outperform non-agressive.
This is a group selection as well (but due to personal benefit in the end).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we observe multilevel selection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;single gene level&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;individual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;critisism&quot;&gt;Critisism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critisism of applying Darwinian principles to behaviour:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heritability of behavior - what are the molecular principles driving this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adaptivenes - everything you see has an adaptive explanation for
why it emerged evolutionarily - there are non-adaptive traits. 
Why do humans have chins? Otherwise you can’t get a flat face. These are so called
spandrel traits, they are just an inevitable result of other traits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gradualism - evolutionary change occurs in gradual incremental steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also political critisism - founding social bioligists were whire south american males (i.e. 
they could just be justifying male domination because this is positive for them).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I watch “Human Behavioral Biology” course by Robest Sapolsky (from Stanford) on Youtube. It is very interesting. Here is my summary of the first three lectures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Crazy pistachio</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/crazy-pistachio" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crazy pistachio" /><published>2019-03-17T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-17T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/crazy_pistachio</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/crazy-pistachio">&lt;p&gt;I saw such an expensive package of pistachio in a supermarket that I couldn’t help not to share my find with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was strolling around the supermarket, busy checking all the discounts available.
I quickly checked the baking section and then noticed something odd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/crazy_pistachio/crazy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dr.Oetker choped pistachio for baking, 2.49 euro for 25 grams&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, we are offered here 25 grams of pistachio (already peeled and choped) for &lt;em&gt;mere&lt;/em&gt; 2.49 euro.
How kind of them. In other words 100 grams of this goodness brings you back by 9.96 euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oops! That’s a lot. 100 euro per kilo. I can’t remember any other product in an ordinary supermarket
costing something like that (except spices).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I normally try to vaguely remember average prices for things I buy, I quickly checked my ordinary source of
pistachio:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/crazy_pistachio/sane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;Bravo&amp;quot; non-peeled pistachio, 3.19 euro for 250 grams&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, just looking at them makes me feel better (after 100 euro per kilo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here your suspicion level should raise and you should ask me: “Wait, but these are not peeled, are you trying to fool us?”.
Yeap, they are not peelled. However, &lt;em&gt;peeling loss percentage&lt;/em&gt; for pistachio is 38.26%-43.39%. No worries, I just learned
that there is “peeling loss percentage” as well. Now you are wondering how I knew that. Apparently people write peer reviewed
articles about this and I took the numbers from “Physical properties of pistachio nut and its kernel as a function of moisture content and variety. Part II. Gravimetrical properties” by Seyed M.A.Razavi et al. Google scholar reports that this article
has 53 citations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our pistachio. Let’s say the shell takes 50% of weight. Thus, in the second case after peeling pistachio on our own
(I know, it is hard to believe that this is possible (at least according to Dr.Oetker), but bear with me) we get 125 grams for 3.19 euro, which is equivalent to 2.55 euro for 100 grams, i.e. almost 4 times cheaper than the first options. “Hey, wait, but these are not choped?” - em, we can chop them as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the saddest part is that I saw this in the supermarket, which means that this is actually pretty profitable,
otherwise they would have stopped doing this much earlier. I honestly can’t imagine people buying this.
Perhaps they are in extreme hurry to bake a pistachio cake and then they run as fast as they can to the supermarket,
directly to the baking section, grab everything chaotically and run away paying as they leave. Or they need precisely 25 grams
of pistacio and they have less than 3.19 euro available to them. Or they don’t know that 3.19 euro option exists. Or they are scared
of peeling pistachio. Or they don’t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I needed exactly 25 grams of pistachio (not sure why, but oh well), I just couldn’t buy this Dr.Oetker package.
I would rather buy 250 grams, peel them, take 25 grams and freeze the rest or just eat it thinking about how peculiar the
world is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that even though we just saved a bunch of money by peeling and choping some pistachios on our own, pistachio is still
on the expensive side (25 euro per kilo). You should definitely keep this in mind when selecting your nuts.
You may get the desired effect (or pretty comparable) by buying much cheaper nuts and, thus, saving even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy conscious shopping!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="saving" /><category term="expenses" /><category term="fun" /><summary type="html">I saw such an expensive package of pistachio in a supermarket that I couldn’t help not to share my find with you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Overview of brokers in Germany</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/german-brokers-overview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overview of brokers in Germany" /><published>2019-03-06T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-06T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/german_brokers_overview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/german-brokers-overview">&lt;p&gt;There are many brokers and choosing one is non-trivial.
Let’s see how they differ from a perspective of a long term ETF investor living in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;assumptionssimplifications&quot;&gt;Assumptions/simplifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the investor buys ETFs monthly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at some European or German stock exchanges&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;directly without a saving plan (Sparplan)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pays German taxes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stock exchange fees are ignored (they are mostly the same across brokers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview-table&quot;&gt;Overview table&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a high level overview.
You can find more details and explanations below the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Broker (pricing mode)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Account fee&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Transaction fee&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;!-- amount --&gt;
&lt;!-- min --&gt;
&lt;!-- max --&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;English&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;German taxes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Peculiarities&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;amount&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;min&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;max&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;flatex&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (but not everything)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;-0.4% yearly on cash (negativzinsen), stock dividends fee&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;onvista (festpreis)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Only some nationalities, owned by comdirect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;onvista (free buys)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0 with “free buy” or 0.23% (without or when selling) &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.99 without “free buy” or when selling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;39 without “free buy” or when selling&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Only some nationalities, only some ETFs, amounts and not forever, owned by comdirect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;finanzen.net&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wrapper around onvista, only some nationalities&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ing diba&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;69.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comdirect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0 for 3 years, then 1.95 EUR/month unless two trades per quarter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;59.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;max blue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;49.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;owned by Deutsche Bank&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DKB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 EUR if &amp;lt;= 10k EUR transaction, 25 EUR otherwise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Consorbank&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9.95&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;69&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Interactive Brokers (fixed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 USD (unless having 100k USD)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Interactive Brokers (tiered)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 USD (unless having 100k USD)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.08%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lynx&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.14%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;99&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Maybe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;German wrapper around IB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Degiro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0.038%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;infinity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Controversial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;german-brokers-all-do-german-taxes-for-you&quot;&gt;German brokers (all do German taxes for you)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All German brokers do all the taxes for you and take the money to pay the tax away before you get your dividends.
This is convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;constant-transaction-fee&quot;&gt;Constant transaction fee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these brokers your transaction fee does not depend on the amount of money in the transaction.
I’ve already wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;/post/underestimating-ter&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; why this is good and how
much money one can save with such a broker (spoiler: more than you think).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flatex&quot;&gt;flatex&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flatex takes a constant fee (5.9 EUR). Some pages are available in English, but the trading interfance
and customer service aren’t (however, some people there agreed to speak English). Still better than nothing, since I am
not aware of any other German broker having anything in English.
As was said above, Flatex (like any other German broker) does taxes (they even take the money for tax away before you actually get your dividends).
If you hold EUR with them, you will pay 0.4% per year from its amount. However, this applies
only to EUR, not ETFs or stock. If you are going to buy stocks, there is a 5.9 EUR fee for stock dividends
larger than 15 EUR (this does not apply to ETFs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;onvista&quot;&gt;onvista&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Onvista has been bought recently by comdirect. They also have a constant fee (5 EUR), but only
in their Festdepot. If you use Free-buy mode, selling (or buying without a free buy) costs
0.23% (min 5.99, max 39 eur), which is comparable to all other percentage-based fee brokers. Moreover, Free-buy mode
seems to be a temporary deal and the current end date is 31.12.2019. Moreover it applies only to some
ETFs and only to some amounts of money (&amp;gt;= 1500 EUR per order) and to actually get at least one free
buy you have to have done a 2000 EUR transaction in the previous month. They do German taxes as well.
The only disadvantage is that they accept only citizens of Germany, France, Ireland, Austria, Luxemburg, Hungary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;finanzennet&quot;&gt;finanzen.net&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a wrapper around onvista Festdepot (even their price conditions have exactly the same formating and styling, just a 
different color). And guess what - they also accept only citizens of Germany, France, Ireland, Austria, Luxemburg, Hungary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;percentage-based-transaction-fee&quot;&gt;Percentage-based transaction fee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these brokers your transaction fee depends on the amount of money in the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ing-diba&quot;&gt;Ing Diba&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.25% (min 4.9, max 69.9). Nothing special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;comdirect&quot;&gt;comdirect&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.25% (min 9.9, max 59.9). The account is free only for the first 3 years,
after that it costs 1.95 EUR per month, unless you do at least 2 thread per quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;max-blue&quot;&gt;max blue&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.25% (min 8.9, max 49.9). Owned by Deutsche Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dkb&quot;&gt;DKB&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DKB decided to be original with their pricing.
For transaction below 10k, you pay 10 EUR, above 10k - 25 eur.
This is actually extremly expensive when investing monthly,
e.g. for 1k you lose 1% due to this fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consorsbank&quot;&gt;Consorsbank&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.25% (min 9.95, max 69)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;non-german-brokers-no-more-german-taxes-for-you&quot;&gt;Non-German brokers (no more German taxes for you)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brokers in this category don’t do any taxes for you.
You can get a list of your transactions from them,
but you will have to figure out how much taxes to pay yourself.
May be not fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interactive-brokers&quot;&gt;Interactive Brokers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IB has 2 modes of pricing - fixed and tiered.
In fixed you pay 0.1% (min 4, max 29), in tiered 0.08% (min 1.25, max 29).
I wrote in great details about them &lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;,
including which one is better and when (spoiler: tiered, practically always).
IB is a very advanced broker. Many use it for professional trading. 
As a result the learning curve is steep.
E.g. just buying ETFs is already non-trivial 
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-buying-etfs&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is my post about this).
On the other hand you get access to a lot of exchanges and this access is much more
direct than what you get at any of the german brokers (they simplify the process a lot).
Also IB has good currency exchange fees (0.2%) and API, so you can automate the process.
The downside - 10 USD fee per month, which is counted against your transaction fees.
That is if you spend 5 EUR for transactions, you pay only 10 USD - 5 EUR at the end of 
the month. If you have more than 100k USD with them (or equivalent, e.g. ETFs or stocks or EUR),
the fee is waived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lynx&quot;&gt;Lynx&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;German wrapper around IB.
Each transaction costs 0.14% (min 5.8, max 99),
which is cheaper than normal German brokers, but you get no taxes done here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;degiro&quot;&gt;degiro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;0.038% (min 2). Degiro is cheap, but there is a lot of controversy around them.
First, they have two kinds of accounts - basic and custody.
In basic one, they can lend your securities to other people to make money,
but not for you. As a result, there is some risk that the people won’t return
your securities. Theoretically the broker should manage this risk, but stuff happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting peculiarity is that Degiro is associated with a hedgefund and there is
presumably &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amsterdamtrader.com/2015/09/degiro-clients-as-counterparty-for-hedgefund.html&quot;&gt;some evidence&lt;/a&gt;
that this hedgefund has abused their position and took advantage of Degiro clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/EuropeFIRE/comments/6j50yz/brokers_you_get_what_you_pay_for/&quot;&gt;This great post on reddit&lt;/a&gt;
considers all the disadvantages in more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since investing in ETFs is a long term game, using a controversial broker sounds silly,
so I personally wouldn’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you prefer easy level of difficulty for your German taxes, then go with some of constant fee German ones (flatex or onvista).
If you happen to use the percentage based fee one, consider switching. I wrote about this already,
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/underestimating-ter&quot;&gt;working 2.4 month full time just for your broker&lt;/a&gt; does not sound
fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t mind doing the taxes on your own, but want more hard core experience and more possibilities,
go with IB. This works especially well when you expect to have 100k USD with them soonish or 
do frequent currency exchange or buy some exotic financial instruments. This will also be cheaper 
than using any constant fee German brokers (assuming 100k USD with them and investing 1-2k EUR per month).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy investing with a great broker!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="investing" /><category term="expenses" /><category term="brokers" /><summary type="html">There are many brokers and choosing one is non-trivial. Let’s see how they differ from a perspective of a long term ETF investor living in Germany.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life as Dominion (board game)</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/life-learning-and-dominion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life as Dominion (board game)" /><published>2019-03-04T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-04T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/life_learning_and_dominion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/life-learning-and-dominion">&lt;p&gt;I’ve played &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominion_(card_game)&quot;&gt;Dominion&lt;/a&gt; and I really liked how the game
could be used as a model for learning and life in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-overview-of-the-rules&quot;&gt;Brief overview of the rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominion is a deck building game. The building happens during the game itself in constrast 
to collectable card games. In other words, there is no way to buy fancy cards in advance and have
advantage in the game. Instead all players start with the same default set of cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each player has their own deck and they draw cards from there.
When they have used their entire deck, they just shuffle the cards and use it again.
Each card has some meaning (either as a currency or allowing you to do some action).
One can buy new cards and add them to their deck.
The set of actions (as a result, cards) is very diverse (e.g. they can directly affect other players or allow you to remove cards from your deck). 
Some cards represent “victory points” (usually with no value appart from that, so getting them in your hand
is inconvinient, because you can’t play them). One maximizes number of victory points in their deck to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;analogy&quot;&gt;Analogy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Dominion one needs to buy good cards as early as possible.
This way they maximize card lifetime utility - the earlier it is bought, the more it will be used.
I find this a good analogy for learning in life. One should learn good skills as early as possible.
As a result, this will increase skill utility by increasing the time when you could apply them.
Thus, buying a card in Dominion is like learning something in life. You want to do it as early as possible.
It will probably be useful and there is cost attached as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing the analogy, shuffling the deck and drawing random cards in Dominion can be seen as
encountering random challenges and opportunities in life. How you react to them depends on your skillset.
Having a good cards (skillset) makes it easier to buy new cards (learn new skills).
This way you can get something similar to skill “compounding”. E.g. if one skill saves you time, 
you can use this time to learn more skills, which can save even more time and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a limited number of cards available to the players overall and players in some sense compete for them.
Thus, the same card can have very different utility in different games based on decisions of other players.
For example, you can buy some card to attack others, but if they all bought plenty of “protection” cards blocking
your attack, this makes your attacking card much less valuable to you. 
Similarly with skills, each skill can have different utility depending on how many other people have it.
Thus, one should keep in mind the demand when assessing skill usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-analogy-breaks&quot;&gt;Where analogy breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just a random analogy, which I found interesting enough to share.
Obviously, for some parts of the game it does not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in Dominion everyone starts with the same deck, which is definitely not true in life.
One may get approximately same skillset when they are born, but they definitely
have different opportunities later in life (e.g. due to financial status of their parents or their nationality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another difference is that in Dominion one buys special victory point cards to win.
That’s for sure not how life works. Just understanding what it means to “win” in life
can easily be a life long goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn good skills early!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy learning!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="philosophy" /><category term="my thoughts" /><category term="analogy" /><category term="learning" /><category term="life" /><summary type="html">I’ve played Dominion and I really liked how the game could be used as a model for learning and life in general.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do you underestimate Total Expense Ratio effect when investing?</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/underestimating-ter" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do you underestimate Total Expense Ratio effect when investing?" /><published>2019-02-28T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-28T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/underestimating_ter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/underestimating-ter">&lt;p&gt;I suspect that it is very easy to underestimate the difference between paying 1% and 0.1% in yearly fees.
Let’s calculate this difference. Moreover, let’s consider other kinds of fees and their impact on a long-term ETF investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classes-of-fees&quot;&gt;Classes of fees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When investing, I define 4 classes of fees based on their nature (i.e. how and when they are applied):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yearly percentage-based&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One time percentage-based&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yearly constant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One time constant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider examples for each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yearly-percentage-based&quot;&gt;Yearly percentage-based&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your financial adviser (fund) takes X% of the money they manage every year as a fee.
For funds, this is called Total Expense Ratio (TER).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-time-percentage-based&quot;&gt;One time percentage-based&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your broker takes X% of the money during the transaction e.g. when buying or selling ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yearly-constant&quot;&gt;Yearly constant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your broker takes X euro each year e.g. as an account management fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-time-constant&quot;&gt;One time constant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your broker takes X euro during the transaction e.g. when buying or selling ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;their-impact&quot;&gt;Their impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classes above are ordered based on how badly they can affect you when you invest long-term.
Yearly percentage-based fee is the worst offender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yearly-percentage-based-1&quot;&gt;Yearly percentage-based&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you feel when you see 1% yearly fee? Before I started looking into investing,
I did consider this cheap and not that important. I speculate that we get conditioned
during our life to some scale of numbers, which mostly works in ordinary life situations.
E.g. if the price for a bus ticket increases 1%, this would be a minor nuisance.
And we natually use the same logic when we first get to investing.
1% yearly fee - sounds low enough to be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, investing is different from ordinary life due to compounding
and exponential growth, which we rarely observe otherwise. As a result, our heuristical rules
 don’t work here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider an example. We invest 1000 euro in two assets (e.g. funds). Both assets 
have 4% after inflation yearly return, but the first asset has 1% yearly fees, while the second &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; 0.9%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first year, we will have 1000 * 1.04 = 1040 in both assets before applying the fees.
After the fees it is 1040 * 0.99 = 1029.6 in 1% fee asset and 1040 * 0.991 = 1030.64 in 0.9% one.
At this stage the difference is only 1.04 euro. However, we are long term investors here and our timeline spans 30-60 years.
As a result, we are also missing future returns attached to this 1.04 euro. E.g. with 4% yearly growth, in 30 years it becomes
1.04 * 1.04^30 = 3.37 euro. 
Please note that the growth is after inflation, so these are today’s euros in terms of inflation.
As a result, 1.04 euro we payed in the fees in the future becomes 3.37 inflation adjusted euros, they just don’t go
into our pocket (or rather brokerage account) anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, it still may look like I am crazy. We are discussing here 3.37 euro in the future 
and losing ~5 euros is not a life changing event.
However, this fee is applied each year and the numbers add up.
After 30 years, the difference is 69.23 euro (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1t02HivZF_u40cJXL_E_osgcCK_6dEeoJ8NAhv5CRkDs/edit&quot;&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;, make a copy if you would like to play with it). This doesn’t look much, but the overall value of your
0.9%-fee investment after 30 years is 2399.4 euro and this difference is 2.88% of the overall value.
In other words by choosing 0.9% yearly fee investment instead of 1%, you get 2.88% more money in 30 years
(assuming investing only once and 4% after inflation return).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, investing 1000 euro once is unusual, we all invest monthly instead. What happens in this case?
The relative effect of this fee difference decreases, because the later investments have less exposure to the yearly fee.
However, since the overall value now is much larger, the absolute effect of the fee is much larger as well.
E.g. if we invest 1000 euro every month, after 30 years the difference is 1.61%
(8810 euro difference with 548068 total, &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1t02HivZF_u40cJXL_E_osgcCK_6dEeoJ8NAhv5CRkDs/edit#gid=1042145595&quot;&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is not too bad, right? What is all the fuss about?
It is actually pretty bad. Above I took a pretty mild case of 0.9% vs 1%.
In real life you can easily get 1% mutual fund yearly fee and 0.1% ETF fee.
If you invest 1000 euro once (under same assumptions as above), after 30 years the difference between
1% and 0.1% yearly fee funds values will be 23% (699 euro difference with 3029 total for 0.1% one fund).
So going from 1% to 0.1% brings you almost a quarter more money in 30 years.
Would anyone here by any chance like to improve your investment return by guaranteed mere 23% in 30 years (equivalent to 0.6% yearly)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you invest 1000 euro monthly, the difference is &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; 13% (85834 euro with 625092 total for 0.1% fund).
As a reminder, these are inflation adjusted (i.e. today’s euros). So going from 1% to 0.1% fee fund brings you almost 100k more here. Looks like this is a good compensation for paying attention to fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that now 1% yearly fee brings some weird feeling of opposition deep inside you
and you immediately imagine 0.1% (or even 0.07%) instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-time-percentage-based-1&quot;&gt;One time percentage-based&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have considered the elephant in the room (yearly percentage based fees), but there are 
more ways to lose (or save) money when investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider one time percentage-based fees. In order to invest you need a broker and all
brokers want something in return for their service.
Some brokers want a part of the money you invest as a fee for the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany I often see 0.25% per transaction (e.g. Ing Diba, maxblue). 
Sometimes brokers have “saving plan” &lt;em&gt;deal&lt;/em&gt; and there it can be even larger (0.4% at maxblue).
Worth noting that they also have minimal and maximal fees per transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For maxblue the limits are 8.9 and 49.9 if you use normal brokerage and no limits for saving plans.
On one hand this is nice for us, because if you decide (for some weird reason) to sell all your ETFs
and they are worth 1 million, you will pay not 2500 euro, but just 49.9 euro.
Unfortunately, this is the only advantage and how often do you do 1 million transactions these days?
On the other hand, the minimal fee penalizes you &lt;em&gt;badly&lt;/em&gt; if you buy ETFs monthly (not as badly as yearly percentage
fees above, but we like to optimize stuff). E.g. if you buy with 1000 euro, you won’t pay 2.5 euro, but 8.9.
If you buy with 100 euro, the situation is even worse - instead of 0.25, you still pay 8.9 (almost 10%, don’t do this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, when investing moderate amounts monthly, minimal fee affects your return badly.
I think the default solution to this is to have a saving plan instead.
E.g. for maxblue, you will pay 0.4% of the transaction amount, but only when &lt;strong&gt;buying&lt;/strong&gt;, and
0.25% with 8.9 and 49.9 limits when selling. So when buying for 100 euro, you pay 4 euro instead of 8.9 above.
A bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you have your own unique circumstances, so you should see for yourself what the best way is.
My main point here - if there is a one time percentage-based fee, take it into account.
E.g. if your broker takes 0.25% without limits for each transaction and you are a long term ETF investor,
effectively you are giving away at least 0.5% of &lt;em&gt;all your networth&lt;/em&gt;. If the already familiar feeling
of opposition from the previous section didn’t visit you here, please read it again. You pay 0.5% of 
&lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; your networth (my feeling of opposition makes me feel bad even to write this). It’s like you take all
what you earned in your life and then say - oh, I don’t need this two hundreds part of it, please help yourself
my lovely broker.
If your working career was 40 years, this is equivalent to you working at least 2.4 months full time just for your
broker to pay this fee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also saying “at least” 0.5%. When you buy, you will definitely pay 0.25%. However, when you sell, the fee
also affects all the growth of your investment. You could consider this as your networth as well, but this 
is definitely more than 0.5% of all the money you invested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can say - oh, this is all very nice, but what do you suggest? 
Yeap, we still need a broker to buy and sell, I agree.
However, there are brokers who don’t have explicit percentage based fees.
E.g. flatex and Onvista (be careful with Onvista, only some account modes (festpreis) don’t have this fee at all,
the free buys one has well hidden 0.25% fee when selling). So check your broker and consider switching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that percentage based fee per se is not bad. E.g. flatex takes 5.9 per transaction.
If you invest 100 euro per month, 0.4% at maxblue will be a better deal for your.
Here you should be worried about selling (are you?). As of now, one can theoretically move
their assets from one brokerage account to another (even probably for free, but I am not familiar with this topic).
Thus, theoretically you can buy all your ETFs at one broker for a very long time and after reaching your 
financial goals, just move all your assets to another one, where selling is cheaper for you.
This also partially protects you against your broker changing their fees (e.g. flatex starting to take 10% instead of 5.9).
However, I have no clue whether this applies to saving plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also said “explicit” above. Technically a broker could try to take a percentage based fees
in some other ways (e.g. through spread or poor asset price). I wasn’t able to detect this myself
by comparing prices at different brokers and I assume that govermental regulations forbid this (hey, MiFiD and friends).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yearly-constant-1&quot;&gt;Yearly constant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, easy ones now.
Some brokers take some money just for having an account with them (hi, Interactive Brokers).
This is likely much cheaper than 0.5% of all your networth (otherwise, RUN from a broker like that).
Still you may take it into account. E.g. for Interactive Brokers it is 10 USD assuming that you have
less than 100k USD (or equivalent) with them, so overall 120 USD per year. Not too bad, but spare ~120 USD per year won’t hurt.
However, they count your transaction fees against this monthly fee. In other words in the end of the
month you pay either 10 USD or all your transaction fees if they are in total larger than 10 USD.
So it will be somewhat smaller than 120 USD per year, but not too much if you buy one ETF and only once a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, by the way here is a funny fact about Interactive Brokers and percentage based fees. They have a percentage based fee,
but it is so low that it may be in the end twice cheaper than flatex’s 5.9 euro. So do your math when choosing a broker!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-time-constant-1&quot;&gt;One time constant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I already explained above some brokers just take some constant fee for each transaction.
I assume that normally you would do 12 transaction per year (+ perhaps 1-5 to rebalance).
So with flatex we are talking about ~5.9 * 12 = ~71 euro (this does not take into account stock exchanges fees,
but we can’t avoid them anyway).
This one has the smallest impact, but you are welcome to take it into account as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose funds with low TER. Train your feeling of opposition when seeing 1% yearly fee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider brokers without percentage based fees transaction fees, but do your math for your specific situation and investing plans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you fancy - take into account broker account fees and constant transaction fees.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy low fee investing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="etf" /><category term="investing" /><category term="expenses" /><summary type="html">I suspect that it is very easy to underestimate the difference between paying 1% and 0.1% in yearly fees. Let’s calculate this difference. Moreover, let’s consider other kinds of fees and their impact on a long-term ETF investor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment: losing everything</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment: losing everything" /><published>2019-02-15T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-15T09:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/thought_experiment_losing_everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything">&lt;p&gt;Imagine that one day you wake up and find out that all your savings have been completely wiped out (e.g. by a cybercriminal).
That’s how the new thought experiment by SavingNinja starts. Here you can see my thoughts about this unfortunate situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we get to my response, let me introduce you the concept, so that you understand all the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/category/thought-experiments/&quot;&gt;“Thought experiments”&lt;/a&gt;
is a project by SavingNinja. The idea is that some hypothetical situation is posted every 2 month
and participants must write down their thoughts without any preparation or major editing.
This should uncover their inner views and feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-lost-everything-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;“If You Lost Everything” thought experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment’s page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/if-you-lost-everything&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (it also contains links to other bloggers’ posts)
and the “problem” statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You wake up one rainy morning and after checking on your accounts you find out that you’ve been ‘wiped-out’ by a cybercriminal. You’ve lost all of the money and assets that you’ve ever owned and you can’t get them back. What will you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-reply&quot;&gt;My reply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh… That’s unfortunate. So I definitely would feel like shit for some time.
Probably, at first I would assume that it is a bug in the online banking or something.
Probably, even call them to confirm. Once I understand that it is not a bug
and the situation is real, I will probably try to calm myself down by saying that
bank will try to do something about this. I think they would try to do something,
but for your experiment let’s assume that it is was my fault (e.g. I used a compromised
computer) and there is no way to return the money. So I would be dissapointed for some time.
It is not clear from the experiment statement whether I lost my job as well,
but I assume - not. So that would definitely be a very good thing. Since I rent, it is hard
to imagine losing my accomodation so fast, but perhaps someone could write something to
the landlord pretending to be me and screw this as well. Since the option with accomodation
and work is pretty easy and boring, let’s consider it first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-still-have-accomodation-and-job&quot;&gt;I still have accomodation and job.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would continue going to work, I have couple months worth
of expenses in cash at home - thank you for giving me one example how this could be useful.
So I could definitely weather this until my next salary.
Would I go for FIRE again? Oh, that’s a very tricky question.
On one hand this wouldn’t change my lifestyle, frugality and tendency to efficiency,
but on other hand going for the second time through something you already did (like
writing a report which got lost due to some computer error) feels very bad.
The loss would for sure demotivate me badly. However, it won’t help me to spend more by any means,
so I technically won’t have any other option, and, thus, I will continue spending moderately
and perhaps try to get to FIRE again as a result. (BUT this feels so frustrating, I can feel this frustration in me right now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-job-and-no-accomodation&quot;&gt;No job and no accomodation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s say that a very malicious (and determined) cybercriminal pretended to be me and screwed up
my job (this one hard to imagine, even if they say that I did something wrong there would be some kind
of investigation first (I hope)) and my accomodation as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am standing in the street with my wallet and some clothing and that’s it.
I have 100-200 euro in my wallet, so this would be enough for one night.
Also I have my phone, so I could call my friends and ask them to host me for one night
(or more….). I would definitely call police immediately, just in case there is any chance 
they could still do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that I would try to find a job. I would probably couch-surf at my friends’ places for some time.
Meanwhile applying into various companies and asking them to speed up the process.
I would definitely help my friends in their houses (perhaps cooking, cleaning) as a way to 
partially repay for my prolonged presence. I could extend this to other people as well
(finding various small hustles). The goal here is to get to net 0 with my living expenses (mostly food 
and accomodation). I hope that I would be able to find some job pretty fast
and start looking for a new appartment (very likely some WG (shared appartment) for the first time to save some
money). After that the problem is reduced to “accomodation and job”, which was described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fire-after-starting-from-0&quot;&gt;FIRE after starting from 0?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am curious to look more into my feelings about FIRE after losing everything.
I definitely thought about something similar before, but in a different context.
Occasionally I have some doubts inside me about the stock market and I get this thought
“What if I missed something and all my investments get completely busted to 0?”.
How would I feel about this? What would I do?
By the way, this case feels much harder to me emotionally, because here this is my mistake
and I am the one solely responsible for the loss. In your example, it felt more like
an external impact, which was outside of my control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to believe that I would accept losing my investments. In some sense I know that it is
some kind of a gamble. I could save cash without investing, but then it would take me forever
to reach anything FI like (basically, without passive income I would collect money constantly for some
time and when I have enough money to cover my expenses before I die, I would be FI, but this time
would be pretty short I assume). Wow, I should try to calculate this and write a post about this.
So this case (no investments) is extremly sad and this basically means just working full
time my entire life and having almost conventional retirement, which makes me sad
(but I understand that I am privileged and many people didn’t/don’t have even that).
And that’s why I started looking into stock market and kind of accept the risk.
So my feeling would be: “Yeah, I screwed up very badly, but the possible positive outcome
was still much better than completely no investments”. So I would consider this as
a very expensive lesson. However, this would be sad as well, since if the stock market
does not work, then there would probably be no achievable way for an average person to become FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So trying to become FI again would probably be very hard. I could still try to come up
with some business of mine. But this is very tricky and highly volatile effort,
so reaching FIRE this way seems very uncertaion to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, Saving Ninja, thank you for this pleasants thoughts right before I go to bed.
I hope I won’t have any dreams like that.
So now I will turn all my positivity to compensate. Yeah, they can take my money away, but
they can’t take my skills and my brain (unless they kill me, but then I probably don’t get 
to think about what to do next), so I will be sad for some time just due to the sudden change,
but then I will gather all my will, start working even harder and bounce back.
Probably even stronger and better than before (but a couple years older as well).
And I will definitely pay much more attention to cyber security. Or don’t use computers at all?..&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><summary type="html">Imagine that one day you wake up and find out that all your savings have been completely wiped out (e.g. by a cybercriminal). That’s how the new thought experiment by SavingNinja starts. Here you can see my thoughts about this unfortunate situation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Brokers commissions: fixed vs tiered</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Brokers commissions: fixed vs tiered" /><published>2019-02-13T21:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T21:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive_brokers_fixed_vs_tiered_commissions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions">&lt;p&gt;I continue exploring Interactive Brokers and today I will compare their fixed and tiered pricing models.
I will also tell how to actually switch to tiered pricing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers have 2 pricing models: fixed and tiered (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interactivebrokers.com/en/index.php?f=1590&quot;&gt;details on their website&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fixed&quot;&gt;Fixed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here everything is simple. Interactive Brokers just takes some part of your money as a commission and that’s it. The exact conditions depends on what and where you buy, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;US stocks - 0.005$ per share (min 1$, max 1%)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ETFs on Xetra - 0.1% (min 4 EUR, max 29 EUR)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stock on Xetra - 0.1% (min 4 EUR, max 99 EUR)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, people who invest in ETFs from Germany will likely just pay 4 EUR per transaction (unless they buy more than 4000 EUR at a time) and if you buy ETFs for 10k EUR, the fee is 10 EUR and for 30k EUR it is 29 EUR (the upper bound).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tiered&quot;&gt;Tiered&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it gets a bit more complex. Interactive Brokers again takes some part (smaller than above though) of your money + exchange itself takes some part as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;US stocks - 0.0035$ per share (min 0.35$, max 1%) - this gets even cheaper if you buy more than 300k shares + exchange fees (but I am not familiar with US exhanges to comment on this)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers fee on EUR denominated products (e.g. ETFs and stock on IBIS, which is just another name for Xetra exchange) - 0.08% (min 1.25 EUR, max 29 EUR), this gets better if you trade 1kk EUR per month, but I don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IBIS exchange fee for ETFs - 0.0048% (min 0.6, max 18) + 0.03 EUR + min(0.001%, 5) + 0.01&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IBIS exchange fee for stocks - same as above, but max 72 EUR instead of 18.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so the pricing description is much less simple this time, but let’s see how much we can save. If one buys ETFs for 10k EUR, the fee is 8.74 EUR = max(0.08% * 10k, 1.25) + max(0.0048% * 10k, 0.6) + 0.03 + min(0.001%*10k, 5) + 0.01 = 8 + 0.6 + 0.03 + 0.1 + 0.01. To invest 1000, one will pay 1.9 EUR and the minimal fee is 1.89. Around 33750 your tiered fee becomes larger than 29 EUR and after this you should switch back to fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve prepared &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1mclAd0O2nWY4F96n4Jv3h5hPZkxmIcAS2k8fvRbqs9Y/edit&quot;&gt;a Google Sheets document&lt;/a&gt; to calculate the fees, so if you would like to play with numbers yourself, please go ahead (make a copy in File &amp;gt; Make a copy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: the only constant thing is change and the pricing might have changed as well. Thus, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interactivebrokers.com/en/index.php?f=1590&quot;&gt;details on their website&lt;/a&gt; if you want to know for sure. Otherwise, IB shows the commission before submiting an order, so you could verify my calculations there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you buy some ETFs montly from Germany, tiered pricing is a much better deal for you. If you transaction amount is larger than 33750 EUR, fixed fee is better for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-switch-to-tiered&quot;&gt;How to switch to tiered?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part is funny, because I did not manage to find any documentation anywhere about this. As a result I just randomly traversed all IB interfaces until I just found it. So to enable tiered pricing model on Interactive Brokers do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in into your “Client Portal” (i.e. not a hardcore trading interface, but just general overview)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then click “Menu” (top left) &amp;gt; “Account Settings”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for “Commissions Pricing Structure” and click on a gear icon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Switch to “Tiered”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this does not have an immediate effect on actual prices (even though the interface shows “Tiered”). Looks like someone needs to approve the switch and for me the change took effect only the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy investing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="investing" /><category term="brokers" /><category term="Interactive Brokers" /><category term="saving" /><summary type="html">I continue exploring Interactive Brokers and today I will compare their fixed and tiered pricing models. I will also tell how to actually switch to tiered pricing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buying ETFs on Interactive Brokers (from Germany)</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive-brokers-buying-etfs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buying ETFs on Interactive Brokers (from Germany)" /><published>2019-02-10T19:01:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-10T19:01:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive_brokers_buying_etfs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/interactive-brokers-buying-etfs">&lt;p&gt;I started using Interactive Brokers to buy ETFs and there was quite a steap learning curve.
Thus, let me share what I learned, so that you don’t have to go through this yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I suspect that investing in ETFs longterm on Interactive Brokers is cheaper than on any other broker in Germany. 
That’s why I decided to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-ticker-from-isin&quot;&gt;Getting “Ticker” from ISIN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first confusion was that Interactive Brokers did not understand what ISIN is. Previously I always used ISIN codes to buy all the ETFs and everything worked, but in IB nothing was found. However, there is a way to convert ISIN to another code (“Ticker”), which IB understands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in into WebTrater (i.e. fancy complicated trading interface)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Press on “Search” tab (this should open a new window)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Simple” tab and enter the ISIN you are interested in (e.g. IE00B5BMR087). The ETF should appear below.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/buying_etf_on_ib/search_result.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interactive Brokers search result window for IE00B5BMR087.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open ETF’s page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/buying_etf_on_ib/etf_page.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interactive Brokers search result for IE00B5BMR087 showing which exchanges it is traded on and with which symbols.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can see which exchanges this ETF is traded on. Usually different exchanges have different currencies, so just choose by the currency (IBIS2 for EUR in this case). In “Symbol” column you can see which symbol is used to denote this ETF on a given exchange, thus, if you want to buy IE00B5BMR087 in EUR on Interactive Brokers, you should do so by buying SXR8 symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively this information is available on JustETF as well in “Listing” tab (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justetf.com/en/etf-profile.html?groupField=index&amp;amp;from=search&amp;amp;isin=IE00B5BMR087&amp;amp;query=IE00B5BMR087&amp;amp;tab=listing&quot;&gt;e.g. for IE00B5BMR087&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally to verify you can search the symbol in Google and this should lead to the official fund website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;buying-by-ticker&quot;&gt;Buying by ticker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigating the fancy super complicated investing interface of WebTrader was not easy at first.
So here is how you can buy SXR8:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to “Market”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Add row”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paste the symbol you found above (e.g. SXR8 for IE00B5BMR087)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is only one option for exchange at this step - SMART, but no worries. SMART is just an Interactive Broker’s wrapper, which redirects your orders to presumably the best exchange for you. However, you can choose a specific exchange manually as well when filling the order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Press “Add”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The symbol should appear in your Market View&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click on price in “Ask” column&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Order management view should get populated with the symbol
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/buying_etf_on_ib/order_view.png&quot; alt=&quot;Interactive Brokers order management view for SXR8.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change the quantity (by default it is 100)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everything else is usually sane by default. Order Type “LMT” means limit, i.e. your order won’t be executed unless the price is below or equal to “Limit Price”. “TIF” means how long the order should be active. You can change the exchange if your have any preference. However, if you are using a proper ticket, all of the exchanges should use the same currency (EUR in this case), so there is not much difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click preview order&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For some exchanges you can see exact commission at this step. Unfortunately I was not able to understand why this works only for some exchanges and not always&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Submit order”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy investing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="investing" /><category term="brokers" /><category term="Interactive Brokers" /><summary type="html">I started using Interactive Brokers to buy ETFs and there was quite a steap learning curve. Thus, let me share what I learned, so that you don’t have to go through this yourself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A peculiar story about DHL, UTF-8 and Skype</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/funny-story-about-utf8-skype-and-dhl" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A peculiar story about DHL, UTF-8 and Skype" /><published>2019-02-10T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-10T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/funny_story_about_utf8_skype_and_dhl</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/funny-story-about-utf8-skype-and-dhl">&lt;p&gt;Recently I needed to send a parcel and I decided to use DHL and pay online.
Unfortunately the form always showed me an obscure error. I tried to debug it. In the end I managed to find out the precise cause of the error and it happened to be related to UTF-8 encoding and Skype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already tried to pay online for sending through DHL long time ago and didn’t manage due to precisely the same error. Still this time I was eager to try again, because it was more convenient than filling everything in a hurry in a store (and 1 Euro cheaper, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything starts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhl.de/content/de/de/privatkunden/pakete-versenden/online-frankieren.html?type=ShipmentEditor&quot;&gt;DHL online franking form&lt;/a&gt;.
The form itself looks pretty usual - sender, recipient, customs. I filled everything in.
This took quite some time (customs part is the most unpleasant).
And then the final part of the form comes - what to do with the package if delivery fails?
Destroy or return to the sender? I felt like receiving my stuff back, so please return to the sender.
And that’s where the story starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/dhl_form_error.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of DHL form asking what to do when delivery fails. &amp;quot;Return to sender&amp;quot; is selected and below there is an error &amp;quot;Please give a valid telephone number&amp;quot;.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “delivery failed” part of the form shows an error and clearly asks for a valid telephone number.
Hm, probably they would like to call me when returning the parcel, seems reasonable, but they did not even ask for my phone above (there is no such field).
Moreover the recipient phone number looks ok to me (I’ve checked international phone number format). I was confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious workaround is to let them destroy the parcel (presumably they don’t need my phone for that), but the error does not go away.
Even if you fill in the form from scratch (yes, I did this), you just get exactly the same error when choosing to destroy the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time I had exactly the same issue and I just concluded that the form is buggy. I needed to send the parcel soon, so I went the old way - to a shop and that was it. However, this time I was curious to understand what was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis-1-form-field-missing&quot;&gt;Hypothesis 1: Form field missing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My original hypothesis was that they indeed wanted my phone number, but the form was buggy and the field was not shown. Since the form just sends a POST request, I could modify the request and resend it manually without the form. Indeed the form posts to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;https://www.dhl.de/int-versenden/gw/rest/api/ShipmentEditor&lt;/code&gt; and the sender part has an empty &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;phone&lt;/code&gt; field. So I copied the request as cURL command, modified the phone number and got precisely the same error back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the error in raw json response had &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;property&lt;/code&gt; field and the value was &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;address.receiver&lt;/code&gt;. So they did not like the recepient phone, just the error message was positioned very poorely (hey, DHL, I hope you are reading this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis-2-recipient-phone-number-problem&quot;&gt;Hypothesis 2: Recipient phone number problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrong-format&quot;&gt;Wrong format&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked international phone number format again just in case. Everything seemed correct. I tried using my own phone number exactly in the same format and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;their-phone-validation-does-not-know-the-country--area-code-i-am-sending-too&quot;&gt;Their phone validation does not know the country / area code I am sending too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my phone number worked, I assumed that their validation is not very familiar with the destination country.
I tried a phone number from the destination country, but from another carrier - error.
I tried imitating my phone number (i.e. length and positions of zeroes), but with other country area code - same error.
Then I decided to go to their website in the destination country and just take their phone number. This worked, but their area code was different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;their-validation-does-not-know-area-code&quot;&gt;Their validation does not know area code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They had another phone with a different code and it worked too. This felt weird, but I still needed to send the parcel.
Theoretically I could just use their customer support number as the recipient telephone number and provide a proper one in “additional address details” field, but this felt risky. Fortunately, I decided to play a bit more and modified the area code in their number to match the one I needed.
It still worked. Then I modified the remainder of the number to fully match my original number and it actually worked. But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;something-is-wrong-with-my-original-recipient-number-string&quot;&gt;Something is wrong with my original recipient number string&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I had two phone numbers looking exactly the same, but one caused an error and another one worked. Here I remembered that I copied the first number from Skype (to avoid making any typos), the second one I copied from DHL website and then edited it in the form itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saved both strings into separate txt files and looked at their byte representations (whitespaces are mine for convenience):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;from Skype
e280aa 2b34343031323334353637383930 e280ac 0a
from their website + modification
       2b34343031323334353637383930        0a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from Skype we get the phone number with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e280aa&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e280ac&lt;/code&gt;. Since I used &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web.skype.com&lt;/code&gt; for this, I looked at the code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/skype_phone_html.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Web Skype html code with &amp;amp;#8234\; and &amp;amp;#8236\; around the number.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and there were these characters, just encoded differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some googling, I found out that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e280aa&lt;/code&gt; is a UTF8 charachter called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LEFT-TO-RIGHT EMBEDDING&lt;/code&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fileformat.info/info/unicode/char/202a/index.htm&quot;&gt;(U+202A)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e280ac&lt;/code&gt; - &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;POP DIRECTIONAL FORMATTING&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fileformat.info/info/unicode/char/202c/index.htm&quot;&gt;(U+202C)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;victory&quot;&gt;Victory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so now I knew what was causing the issue and could bypass it and send my parcel. Did I just do that? Obviously not.
I was curious why these characters were in Skype in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just looking at the UI did not help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/skype_web_ui.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Web Skype UI showing a phone number. Nothing unusual.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, left-to-rigth and directional formatting ringed a bell - this may have something to do with right-to-left languages.
Let’s check the UI in some right-to-left language:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/skype_web_ui_ar.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Web Skype UI in some right-to-left language (AR), everything is &amp;quot;mirrored&amp;quot;, except the phone number.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, so everything is mirrored, but not the phone number. Now let’s remove these characters&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/skype_modified_phone_ar_html.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Web Skype html code without &amp;amp;#8234\; and &amp;amp;#8236\; around the number.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/story_about_dhl/skype_web_ui_ar_without_chars.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Web Skype UI in some right-to-left language (AR) without &amp;amp;#8234\; and &amp;amp;#8236\; around the number, the number is written as 440123456789+ now.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; just jumps behind the number (i.e. gets written from right-to-left due to the language).
This now seems reasonable. The Arabic numerals are written and read from left-to-right (i.e. like in English) even in right-to-left languages, so the phone number itself is just a number and should not change. However, the unary plus &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; could move and these 2 UTF characters just do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;browser: &amp;lt;prints some text right-to-left and meets e280aa&amp;gt;
e280aa: hey, browser! How-dee-do? Could you do me a
        favor and print left-to-right for a bit?
browser: oh, sure, not a big deal. &amp;lt;prints the
         phone number with '+' on the left of it and meets e280ac&amp;gt;
e280ac: hey, browsee! How are html standards these days?
        e280aa asked me to ask you to go back
        to right-to-left, thanks a lot for helping us out!
browser: oh, whatever &amp;lt;continues printing right-to-left&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I just sent the parcel and indeed the experience was much better when prepaying online (+1 Euro cheaper as well).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="funny" /><category term="bugs" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Recently I needed to send a parcel and I decided to use DHL and pay online. Unfortunately the form always showed me an obscure error. I tried to debug it. In the end I managed to find out the precise cause of the error and it happened to be related to UTF-8 encoding and Skype.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Frugal travel or how much does FIWE 2019 cost</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how-much-travel-to-fiwe-2019-cost" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frugal travel or how much does FIWE 2019 cost" /><published>2019-01-27T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-27T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how_much_travel_to_fiwe_2019_cost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how-much-travel-to-fiwe-2019-cost">&lt;p&gt;I’ve accidentally discovered that there will be another &lt;a href=&quot;https://whatlifecouldbe.eu/fiwe/fiwe-2019/&quot;&gt;Financial Independence Week Europe (2019)&lt;/a&gt; in Budapest in May. 
I felt like it might be interesting to go there. However, before commiting, I definitely should know how much it will cost,
since my willingness to go is a function of cost. For example, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fichautauqua.com/&quot;&gt;Chautauqua 2019&lt;/a&gt; everything is extremely simple - 
€2300 is just too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s see how much FIWE 2019 actually costs (at least for me) and consider some frugal (aka cheap) ways of attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before we start, we can break down our task into multiple subtasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One needs to get to Budapest and back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One needs to stay somewhere in Budapest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conference fee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are inevitable expenses (assuming that you are going to the conference) and they provide a good lower bound,
which we can improve later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conference-fee&quot;&gt;Conference fee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;€25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was easy, wasn’t it? While we at it, thanks a lot to the organizers, this is the real frugal conference fee (do you still remember €2300?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-to-budapest-and-back&quot;&gt;Getting to Budapest and back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is less obvious, but still manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May I will likely be in Munich, so that’s my starting point. The main part of the conference happens from 2nd to 4th of May,
but since I will be travelling there anyway, I consider it reasonable to stay for FIWE Extra as well (i.e. until evening of 8th of May).
Thus, our constraints are Munich, 2nd-8th of May. Let’s consider travel options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bus&quot;&gt;Bus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geography wasn’t my favorite subject, so let’s check the bus first (in case if Budapest is not that far from Munich).
Flixbus is a somewhat default bus option in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/flixbus.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Flixbus website with trips from Munich to Budapest. The prices are 30-40 euros and duration is at least 13 hours.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Ok, Budapest is much further than I thought. Spending 13 hours in a bus is just inefficient and for 40 euros one way there must be alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight&quot;&gt;Direct flight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be naive and see how much it costs to have a flight from Munich.
We can do this in Google flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/google_flights_direct.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Google Flights website showing a Lufthansa flight. No price is shown.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it costs 140 euros. Plus 11.2 * 2 to get to and back from the Munich airport. Plus something for Budapest airport (but I am lazy to look it up now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 22.4 (MUC &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; MUC airport) + 140 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight)  + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-dates&quot;&gt;Other dates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes playing with the dates helps (e.g. ticket price difference is larger than one night stay), but not in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/google_flights_direct_other_dates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Google Flights website showing price matrix for different dates around 2nd and 8th. 140 is the cheapest.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight-but-not-from-muc&quot;&gt;Direct flight, but not from MUC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to know about Memmingen airport, which has a bunch of lowcosters.
Check Google Flights again  - and no flights whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t give up yet. I know about azair.com flights search engine, which is very flexible.
By default it suggests me to search starting from MUC,SZG,FMM,INN,NUE and this works well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are really cheap (like €36 for a return flight cheap) flights from Nuernberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_nuernberg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with cheap flights from Nuernberg.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to get to NUE airport. There is blablacar, but this does not sound good before a flight.
So Flixbus, it is. Unfortunately, they don’t have a schedule for May and April yet,  but in March
the prices are 5-6 euros. The only issue is that the outward flight is pretty early (10:40am),
but there are no early morning buses. So I could come one day earlier and explore Nürnberg as well.
Or the schedule for May may change. Or my application for FIWE won’t be approved. We will see. Also the return flight
is pretty early too, so I might need to stay in BUD until 9th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 12 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE) + ? (a night in NUE) + ? (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE airport) + 36 (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight-but-not-from-muc-1&quot;&gt;Direct flight, but not from MUC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a typo. Didn’t I say that azair.com is very flexible? It also has a list of nearby airports and knows about various local lowcosters.
Moveover it allows you to search for all trips e.g. from 7 to 9 days between two dates. Pretty cool, huh? So let’s add all airports close to Munich&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_airports_close_to_muc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with list of airports close to Munich.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, how I could have forgotten about Stuttgart. Sorry, Stuttgart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_airports_close_to_muc_to_bud.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with flights from airports close to MUC to BUD. Stuttgart is cheapest.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still magically low 36 euros, but a bit better timing. Wrong date though, but I don’t mind spending additional day in Budapest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Flixbus again - direct early bus from MUC to STU airport, 3 hours, 10-14 euros.
Getting back is a bit less pleasant (on 8th there is a bus at 12:35 from the airport, but the next one is at 22:00).
But I don’t have to commit now, I just consider my options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 20-28 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;STU) + 36 (STU&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-budapest-just-a-part-of-vacation&quot;&gt;Making Budapest just a part of vacation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually you can make the problem even harder by allowing traveling with changes and spending time in stopover cities.
Inside Europe this works well with buses and blablacar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually you should start by looking at the map and checking which cities between the target cities sound interesting.
I’ve been to Vienna, so I am not interested for now. Bratislava sounds interesting. However, I don’t want to visit
the same city on the return trip (picky). So probably Graz in Austria is the second. But then it is not connected well to Budapest.
And Bratislava is not connected well to Munich. So blablacar, but this is a risky territory if you want to be at a given 
time at a given place with high probability (especially since one can’t book well in advance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the optimization problem gets too large here. And if you allow more than one stopover… Don’t do this, it is just too tricky to plan
(unless everything is well connected with a bus or you don’t mind unexpectly spending additional day in one of the cities visited).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, nope for now. But if I hadn’t visited Vienna…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;travel-options-overview&quot;&gt;Travel options overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from MUC &amp;gt;= 162.4&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;22.4 (MUC &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; MUC airport) + 140 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight)  + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from NUE &amp;gt;= 48&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;12 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE) + ? (a night in NUE) + ? (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE airport) + 36 (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from STU &amp;gt;= 64&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;20-28 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;STU) + 36 (STU&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fill in accomodation prices later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accomodation&quot;&gt;Accomodation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With accomodation there is less room for optimization. Usually it is just Airbnb or hostels depending on my prediction how social I will feel during the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;airbnb&quot;&gt;Airbnb&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Airbnb it is important to remember that you can filter by price (especially if you save money):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/airbnb_price_filter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of airbnb price filter.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say average nightly price is 74, but there are plenty of options cheaper than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, there are some options for 15-18 euros per night, which might be too extreme.
But 20-25 range seems ok and 30 per night should be plenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a way to optimize, I could cooperate with fellow conference goers and book something together.
This is definitely quite far fetched (I haven’t even applied yet), but it would bring the price down
for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 15-30 per night&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hostels&quot;&gt;Hostels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hostels booking.com seems to work okeyish. I definitely couldn’t ever recommend it just due to how pushy the UI is, but it is the only site I know, where I can quickly see for how many people a room in a hostel is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the prices are from 8 to 13 euro for a bed. 8 euro is a mind-boggling number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 8-13 per night&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food is tricky to estimate, since we will likely eat as a group. However, we can give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually numbeo.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.numbeo.com/cost-of-living/in/Budapest?displayCurrency=EUR&quot;&gt;Budapest’s page&lt;/a&gt;) is very handy for this task. 
So meal in an inexpensive restaurant is 5.6 euro on average (7.78 upper bound), 12 eggs - 1.7, bananas - 1.34, apples - 1.06.
Let’s say I will have 2 eggs - banana - apple breakfast (~0.76 euro) and lunch/dinner in an inexpensive restaurant (~14 euro). I could do all three meals myself in airbnb’s or hostel’s kitchen, but the main goal is the conference, so let’s not waste time and focus on it. I would rather spend time in a restaurant talking with others than saving 3-5 euros per meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 15 euro per day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fun&quot;&gt;Fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun is impossible to estimate at this stage, since the plan is not known.
So let this be a surprise. In worst case I could drop out of any pricey group-goings, but again this is a FI conference and I would be extremly suprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;total&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€25 conference fee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\&amp;gt;= €64 flight from Stuttgart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€8-30 per night for accomodation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~€15 per day for food&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€? for some fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grand total is &amp;gt;= €265 - 419 + fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s see whether my application will be approved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="frugality" /><category term="travel" /><category term="FIWE" /><category term="FIRE" /><summary type="html">I’ve accidentally discovered that there will be another Financial Independence Week Europe (2019) in Budapest in May. I felt like it might be interesting to go there. However, before commiting, I definitely should know how much it will cost, since my willingness to go is a function of cost. For example, with Chautauqua 2019 everything is extremely simple - €2300 is just too much. So let’s see how much FIWE 2019 actually costs (at least for me) and consider some frugal (aka cheap) ways of attending.</summary></entry></feed>