<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-30T14:54:13+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #6 overview: unpopular opinions</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions-overview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #6 overview: unpopular opinions" /><published>2019-06-30T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-30T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_6_unpopular_opinions_overview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions-overview">&lt;p&gt;Saving Ninja had a new thought experiment recently (#6, about unpopular opinions).
I again felt like making an overview of responses. Thus, here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the general description of these experiments, see 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;my last post-response&lt;/a&gt;.
I previously did &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;an overview&lt;/a&gt;
for the experiment #5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main goal here is to try see whether there are any peculiar similarities and differences.
This is also a good excuse to read all the responses (otherwise I would not find time for it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it is just interesting. I still remember &lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;“A Way to Less”&lt;/a&gt;
goal to learn to handstand from the previous overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experiment official page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
You can find links to posts in the Notes section below. I will refer to people by their twitter username for simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the group happened to be very diverse and majority of opinions were mentioned only once.
Therefore, this time I will just describe my observations and highlights without making a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common unpopular opinion was FIRE or something related (@SavingNinja, @financeyourfire, @FretfulFinance, @merely_curious_).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both @TheIndeedably and @DrFIREUK didn’t like peer-to-peer landing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For @asimple_life and @merely_curious_ (i.e. me) there happened to be almost a bingo situation.
Both of us happen to consider alcohol unnecessary (thus, don’t drink as much as others normally do)
and think that the society affects other people lives too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@SavingNinja believes that doing more yourself makes one happier. @TFSRetireEarly suggests, on the other hand, that
people should DIY less and it is overrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peculiar to read responses of Andy and James from Rebo. They took different sides of the same
argument - whether one should be altruistic and how moral this is. The posts resembled a light duel or a debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@SavingNinja has touched relationships a bit. The opinion is to split expenses 50/50 in a relationship.
@FretfulFinance went all in on a relationship path. She never had a relationship, does not want to live 
with someone else, does not like weddings (but not anti-marriage), does not want children and does not
like public displays of affection. The post felt very personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were all the matches and below are remaining unique opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@MoneyModernGirl finds Italy too traditional and welcomes more innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@financeyourfire believes in crypto currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@TheIndeedably has multiple unpopular opinions and presented a compilation of them: simpler tax code, more efficient social security,
one should own wealth generational assets, leverage is good, P2P landing is bad, innovation is slowing,
luck plays a large part in life (especially health), nothing really matters (we will be dead anyway), life is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@ditchthecave believes that our appearance affects our lives more than we think. Also everything can be learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. @awaytoless finds electric cars not so environmentally friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs. @awaytoless reminds us that we are not entitled to anything and feeling so can even have negative impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@DrFIREUK suggests to invest in equities, pay more attention to personal finance, avoid credit card debt and P2P investing. 
For them early retirement is not a goal (they plan to work). Also the last season of Game of Thrones was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@fi_left finds public ownership better than private. In other words, we need more parks, libraries,
free health care and good public transport instead of buying something for yourself for your short term happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@TFSRetireEarly believes in no free market. Also not everyone can become FIRE. One can beat the market and win money
by gambling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I my notes from what I read.
I have no clue why you would like to read this,
but I don’t see any harm in putting them here either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;saving-ninja&quot;&gt;Saving Ninja&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavingNinja&quot;&gt;twitter @SavingNinja&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thought experiment to take part in, since the topic was from Indeedably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weird one in private (reading, FIRE), with some quirks leaking externally (money saving tips guy at work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matched betting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being into FIRE is already weird, but let’s not focus on this, since majority of readers are into it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief that “spending less makes you happier”, e.g. outsourcing to a bread maker instead of doing it with your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splitting expenses 50/50 with one’s partner independently of income difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-indeedably-&quot;&gt;{ in·deed·a·bly }&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/against-the-tide/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheIndeedably&quot;&gt;twitter @TheIndeedably&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing disapproval at board members meeting showing that an approach won’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to the experiment is “peer”.
If you don’t care about someone’s opinion, they are not your peer.
As a result, you can have very small peer group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to live in a society where one can have and even express unpopular opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our opinions can be used to other parties for their own benefit (e.g. through media).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax code should be simple (a single-sided sheet of A4). All income should be taxed the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better social security. Evaluate the actual need for social security (e.g. whether one has
assets to sell). If the money are needed urgently (before being able to sell an asset), the
help should be a loan. Free education and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Own wealth generating assets (i.e. work for your own wealth instead of someone else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leverage is good (if used correctly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peer-to-peer lending is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation is slowing (and goes backwards in some areas due to short term views).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luck plays a large part (especially in one’s health).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing really matters (you will be dead anyway). Deadlines are arbitrary.
Stress is mostly self inflicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is pretty good. It could be so much worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caveman--ditchthecave&quot;&gt;Caveman @ DitchTheCave&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ditchthecave.com/unpopular-opinions/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ditchthecave&quot;&gt;twitter @ditchthecave&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People don’t share their REALLY unpopular opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How you look matters and impacts how successful you are in life. But the “good look” is defined by the culture and society itself and
changes with time. There is “beauty premium” (physical beauty affects wages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything can be learned (i.e. natural ability is a myth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can do anything, but you can’t do everything&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mr-a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;Mr A Way To Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-6&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/awaytoless&quot;&gt;twitter @awaytoless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric cars aren’t environmentally friendly. The batteries can have negative effects.
Power generation still can be environmentally unfriendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;miss-a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;Miss A Way To Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-6-miss-way/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/awaytoless&quot;&gt;twitter @awaytoless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not entitled to anything. Feeling entitled affects your work - why working for something if you “have” a right for it? 
People feel entitled to start a family even when their financial position is nut suited for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We [Mr and Mrs Way] are entitled to be treated fairly. However, we have to remind ourselves that this is not a given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merely-curious&quot;&gt;Merely curious&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;twitter @merely_curious_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about “peers” is good, because with “people in general” answering the question would be impossible.
Estimate rarity by remembering anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I should not drink alcohol aka there is no point in alcohol” (only 2 peers share).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRE is good (only 1 peer shares).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Average” opinions in society are often wrong and one should treat them less seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Age agnosticity when it comes to communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marc--financeyourfire&quot;&gt;Marc @ FinanceYourFire&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/06/15/thought-experiment-oh-hi-marc/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/financeyourfire&quot;&gt;twitter @financeyourfire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A part of me wants to be an outlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The room” - because the movie is so bad, it is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going against the grain just for the sake of it makes no sense, instead you should believe into something and have strong character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an outlier is relative to the group you compare with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My FIRE plans make me an outlier when compared to my work colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in crypto currency. This does not fit the general FIRE narrative well (too risky).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dr-fire&quot;&gt;Dr FIRE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drfire.co.uk/unpopular-opinion/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DrFIREUK&quot;&gt;twitter @DrFIREUK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invest in equities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pay attention to personal finance (e.g. seek the best deals, get sign up bonuses)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid credit card debt&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid P2P&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Early retirement is not a goal (i.e. continue working after FI)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last season of Game of Thrones was good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-simple-life&quot;&gt;A Simple Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/2019/06/14/saving-ninja-thought-experiment-6/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/asimple_life&quot;&gt;twitter @asimple_life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to drink alcohol when I was a teenager.
You don’t have to drink alcohol to have good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People struggle to challenge peer pressure to conform to the unwritten rules of society.
If you want to reach FIRE, you need to learn not to follow the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money-for-the-modern-girl&quot;&gt;Money For The Modern Girl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneyforthemoderngirl.org/my-unpopular-opinion-italy-traditions-and-innovation/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MoneyModernGirl&quot;&gt;twitter @MoneyModernGirl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italy is too traditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italians live off their country and have no innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a black market in Italy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;people reporting incomes of less than 20,000 euros (about $26,000) per year cumulatively own 188,000 supercars, 
(such as Ferraris, Lamborghinis, Porsches, or BMW coupes), 518 private airplanes or helicopters, and some 42,000 yachts.”
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2012-01-12/italy-poor-drive-ferraris&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fretful-finance&quot;&gt;Fretful Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fretfulfinance.co.uk/im-a-relationship-and-romance-outlier/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FretfulFinance&quot;&gt;twitter @FretfulFinance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dilemma which topics to choose and how open to be when writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retirement planning could be an option, but readers enjoy it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political views (slightly left)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing details about relationship history feels much harder than personal finance numbers (even though the blog is anonymous).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never had a relationship (early 30s) and wouldn’t be surprised to never have one.
Hard to imagine living together with the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t like wedding, but not anti-marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t like public displays of affection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t want children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t understand obsession with sex and can live without ever having it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a relationship is dictated by the popular culture (music, films, TV).
I actually preferred to be alone (but it took time to understand this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50% preferring being single, 40% happy to wait and see if something comes along and 
10% actively wanting a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10% above are coming from the fear of loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I manage to form a long-term relationship, I would ideally live close but separately.
In practice, I could imagine moving in for financial reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marriage can be good for tax purposes and to show one’s commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a wedding itself is absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not an asexual, rather the attraction is rarely strong enough to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;left-fi&quot;&gt;Left FI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leftfi.home.blog/2019/06/15/my-unpopular-opinion-public-is-better/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fi_left&quot;&gt;twitter @fi_left&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public ownership is better than private. One can buy something to maximize their short term happiness. 
At the same time, the public sphere (library, park, free health care, public transport) improves life a lot too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andy--liberatelife-on-rebo&quot;&gt;Andy @ liberate.life (on Rebo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reboapp.co.uk/blog/2019/06/17/andys-unpopular-opinion/?__s=rcyijymopus5qozgh6si&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reboapp&quot;&gt;twitter @reboapp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-founder of Rebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Altruism is not self-evidently morally good/necessary. Rather, people act in ways that
appear to be self-sacrificial only when it benefits them (even if that benefit is just making them feel ‘good’).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altruism - acting in such a way that seems to harm your own self interest in order to benefit somebody else’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;james--rebo&quot;&gt;James @ Rebo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reboapp.co.uk/blog/2019/06/17/jamess-unpopular-opinion/?__s=rcyijymopus5qozgh6si&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reboapp&quot;&gt;twitter @reboapp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-founder of Rebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As someone on the path to financial independence, or who has achieved financial independence,
you are in an enormously privileged position, and positions of privilege like that come with
increased responsibility for helping others who are less fortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with more independence in how they spend their time, or with more money, has a larger
duty to help others than someone with fewer resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thefirestarter&quot;&gt;theFIREstarter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thefirestarter.co.uk/the-contrarian-thought-experiment-6/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TFSRetireEarly&quot;&gt;twitter @TFSRetireEarly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no free market and the ones we have are highly inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The favorite argument is that advertisement industry is meant to prevent rational buyers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.randomthoughts.fyi/2014/04/free-market-vs-capitalism-what-is-free.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). Another one is absence of the perfect information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone can become FIRE (e.g. some people already live frugal enough to have no room for downscaling and no money to save).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible for one to beat the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t DIY everything (trying to do it once yourself is sufficient).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can win money gambling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Saving Ninja had a new thought experiment recently (#6, about unpopular opinions). I again felt like making an overview of responses. Thus, here it is!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How not to get angry?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/not-getting-angry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How not to get angry?" /><published>2019-06-23T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/not_getting_angry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/not-getting-angry">&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered a peculiar trick for coping better with negative events
in one’s life. The idea is to try to find a reasonable explanation.
I suspect that this may be connected to meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays it is very easy to be reactive in life. In other words, letting
external events to drive you - your emotions and your actions. The most
prominent example is getting angry when something goes wrong. More often
the target of one’s anger is another person, but it can be a company
or just the situation itself. I don’t see any benefit of such anger. It
does not help to solve the problem, but instead biases your perspective,
can make the problem worse (especially when other people are involved)
or in the best case just takes your time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-little-trick&quot;&gt;My little trick&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve understood that I’ve been using a peculiar trick
in such situations without recognizing it. Imagine that something negative for me happens, which
normally would make me angry. For now, let’s assume that there is another
person involved and this is their fault. The moment this happens, I am immediately
ready to jump into a negative reaction. However, instead of doing this, I try
to take other person’s perspective and see why they could have done what they did. 
In particular, I try to find some plausible explanation of their action.
Ideally the explanation should be such that, if I were in a similar situation,
I could imagine myself doing exactly the same as they did. Somehow once I find such
an explanation (usually this happens very quickly), I don’t feel an urge to
jump into the negative state at all. Unfortunately, I don’t know why this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider an example. You take an underground and there are construction works.
As a result your train does not go directly to where you need (as it normally would),
instead you have to e.g. stop and switch trains. Our natural reaction would be -
“this is a bad service, why do I have to pay for this, I hate this company, they
always have these problems, I am angry”. However, one can pause for a moment and try
to imagine themselves leading such a company. It is actually hard. And stuff breaks
a lot, so one needs to repair and maintain. Thus, I would likely do exactly the same
closures to be able to do construction works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is crossing a street on a crosswalk. Let’s say we are in a country where it is common
for cars to give way to pedestrians on crosswalks. Then imagine that a car
does not give way. I.e. you had to stop for them to drive by, otherwise, you would 
probably get hit. Again, the first reaction is exactly the same as above. 
However, if I were a driver, I could imagine various situations. First, this is just
a game of probability, so even if I were a very strict driver, eventually some coincidences
would align and I could do something similar (e.g. just not noticing pedestrian by
chance). Or perhaps the driver was really badly in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is easier to do in situations involving other people (since there is some
other perspective to take). However, with some practice one can do something
similar for general situations. E.g. one started having foot pain. It is very
easy to be sad and angry about this. Instead one can remember that they did
a lot of aggressive running recently and shouldn’t have pushed that far.
Somehow this helps to cope with the situation better and avoid emotional
reaction at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that meditation can be a prerequisite for this trick.
In other words, whenever an emotional reaction happens, one needs to stop
and don’t follow that reaction, but start reflecting instead. I speculate
that meditation helps with this. That’s partially how meditation works - you
get thoughts, but choose not to follow them. Thus, if you have difficulties
with going to the meta level instead of an emotional reaction - perhaps try a meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may also be related to emotional intelligence and empathy. In order to find
a plausible explanation, you really need to take other person’s perspective and
imagine yourself in it. This can be non-trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanism&quot;&gt;Mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, I don’t know how or why this works. I suspect that finding a
plausible explanation may be not the key. E.g. it could be that getting
distracted is the most important part. In other words, perhaps if you just
start dancing when you feel an emotional reaction to a negative effect,
this could have a similar distracting effect. This is an open question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-step-further&quot;&gt;One step further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to just somehow rationalize a situation or look at it from a different
perspective instead of getting angry. In our underground example, one can try to remember
how often does something like this happen. In my case, it was not often and this did help
me to have a healthier view on the situation. Alternatively one can treat almost any situation
as an adventure. E.g. in the underground case, one was passing this station numerous times
and it just felt boring, but here something new is happening and this feels like an adventure
and adds variety into life. I agree that this may sound artificial, but I hope that you
see the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy conscious reactions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="perspective" /><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">I’ve discovered a peculiar trick for coping better with negative events in one’s life. The idea is to try to find a reasonable explanation. I suspect that this may be connected to meditation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Brokers monthly fee</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Brokers monthly fee" /><published>2019-06-18T23:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T23:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive_brokers_monthly_fee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee">&lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers have monthly “inactivity” (aka Monthly Minimum) fee.
It is not obvious how one can see this fee being applied.
Here is one way (spoiler: through statements).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers have somewhat unusual fee structure 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interactivebrokers.com/en/index.php?f=4969&quot;&gt;official source&lt;/a&gt;),
which is always a pain to explain. Basically, they require one to spend at least
10 USD for trading transactions per month. If one spends less, they anyway charge the difference
up to 10 USD and call this “inactivity” fee. However, they remove this fee
if one has 100k USD (or equivalent, e.g. in stocks) with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an account for quite some time with IB now, but I have never seen this “inactivity” fee
in action. In other words - when is it charged? How much did I actually pay?
What if I misunderstand the system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I have found only one way to observe this fee - through statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Left Menu &amp;gt; Reports &amp;gt; Statements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Default Statements”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Activity” statement type.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose  “Year to Date” period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Run Statement”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for “Fees” section and open it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/ib_monthly_fee/fee_statement_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fee section from the statement showing the fee for April applied in May.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, in this case the fee for April was applied in May and it was 2.37 EUR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy transparent and easy to understand fees!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Interactive Brokers" /><category term="fees" /><summary type="html">Interactive Brokers have monthly “inactivity” (aka Monthly Minimum) fee. It is not obvious how one can see this fee being applied. Here is one way (spoiler: through statements).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to connect a Namecheap domain to Linode?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting-namecheap-domain-to-linode" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to connect a Namecheap domain to Linode?" /><published>2019-06-11T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T23:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting_namecheap_domain_to_linode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting-namecheap-domain-to-linode">&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I need to link a domain parked at Namecheap to a Linode
and each time I forget how to do it. Thus, here is a guide
(i.e. a cheat-sheet for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linode-part&quot;&gt;Linode part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-link-a-domain-to-your-linode-account&quot;&gt;To link a domain to your Linode account&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Linode account dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Create” dropdown and select “Domain”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Master”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type the domain (without www).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter some email as “SOA Email Address” (this will be public, e.g. can be looked up with 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mxtoolbox.com/SOALookup.aspx&quot;&gt;this tool&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Do not insert default records for me”. Alternatively you can select “Insert default records
from one of my Linodes” and select the target Linode machine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Create” button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-link-a-domain-to-a-specific-linode&quot;&gt;To link a domain to a specific Linode.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you linked a domain to your account, you can connect it to a specific Linode:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Linode account dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy the target Linode machine IPv4 address.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open “Domains” on the left.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select the target domain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add A/AAAA record with the IPv4 address and empty hostname.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy IPv6 address.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add A/AAAA record with the IPv6 address and empty hostname.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;namecheap-part&quot;&gt;Namecheap part&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to a given domain dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set “Nameservers” to “Custom DNS” (by default it is Namecheap BasicDNS).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add “ns1.linode.com”, “ns2.linode.com” and so on up to “ns5.linode.com” as nameservers
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linode.com/docs/platform/manager/dns-manager/#use-linode-s-name-servers-with-your-domain&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To save, click at the green checkmark (righthand side from “Custom DNS” dropdown).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait until the change is propagated across the world (1-2 days, but often 5-10 minutes can be enough).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linode.com/docs/platform/manager/dns-manager/&quot;&gt;Linode docs about DNS Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="how-to" /><category term="technical" /><summary type="html">Occasionally I need to link a domain parked at Namecheap to a Linode and each time I forget how to do it. Thus, here is a guide (i.e. a cheat-sheet for me).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment 6: unpopular opinions</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment 6: unpopular opinions" /><published>2019-06-09T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-09T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_6_unpopular_opinions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions">&lt;p&gt;The new thought experiment is live and this time it is about unpopular opinions,
which your peers don’t share with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concept&quot;&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, let me tell a couple words about the concept.
Every 2 months SavingNinja &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/category/experiments/&quot;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;
a hypothetical question about FIRE or life in general. Then one is encouraged to write their
answer in one go (just putting their raw thoughts as they come) without
editing afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already took part twice 
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;losing everything&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;projects when FIRE&lt;/a&gt;
and 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;overview of other people responses&lt;/a&gt;)
 and I definitely enjoy the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I am again writing this in the morning (in case it is something scary,
the “losing everything” impact still didn’t wear out).
SavingNinja thanked &lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/&quot;&gt;{ in·deed·a·bly }&lt;/a&gt; for a subject, so I am definitely curious.
Also did SavingNinja start running out of ideas or was indeedably’s idea so irresistibly good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;“Unpopular opinion”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new experiment statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A different opinion is somewhat frowned upon in our clique based society, but some of the greatest
minds of all time were outliers. They weren’t scared to go against the grain and stand up for what
they believed in. So, for this Thought Experiment, I’d like you to reveal yourself: What opinion do
you have that most of your peers do not share?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and there you can read other people
answers, which I definitely recommend. In the last experiment I even did
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;an overview&lt;/a&gt;
of people responses and I definitely enjoyed reading all the diverse opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, that’s a tricky one. 
I.e. I have to enumerate my beliefs and then compare them with beliefs of other people and estimate
the intersection. I definitely like that the question talks about “my peers” and not people in general,
because then it would be completely impossible. Here I can at least estimate by remembering anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure whether I will come up with one concrete answer. So far I have 2 options - the 
positivity of the concept of FIRE and negativity of alcohol. I think my views on alcohol have a good
chance to be the rarest across my peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I happen to be not a fan of alcohol. Somehow when everyone was starting to drink alcohol,
I didn’t like the taste much and didn’t start myself (but I definitely tried, peer pressure is a strong
motivator especially in the young age). As a result I don’t drink any alcohol. Obviously, this topic gets
raised at almost any celebration. As a result, I suspect that such an opinion is extremely rare across my peers. 
I don’t mean that my peers are constantly drunk, but somehow I can remember only 1 other person who
does not drink any alcohol due to non-religious reasons and one - for religious. It is funny that in the former
case their views were even more extreme than mine - they disallow people to drink any alcohol at celebrations
in their home. I personally don’t mind that. In the end each has their own life and if someone enjoys
drinking (even people who I care a lot about), but they don’t overdo it, then it is fine with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that this view may be quite rare across the general population as well.
I think the keyword is a teetotaler (Teetotalism). I am not part of Teetotalism per se,
but I suspect that for an external observer it will look like I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I suspect that alcohol abstinence (to clarify, I don’t restrain myself from alcohol and I often have
to actively refuse) is my opinion, which the fewest of my peers share (so far I can remember only 2 people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could I probably beat this number? Is there something one person or no one else shares?
Thus, let’s get to the second point. FIRE. Obviously, I don’t talk much to my peers 
about the concept. I work at a normal job and even though my colleagues are very understanding,
this might be too dramatic for them. Across my immediate peers (e.g. not FIRE related people in the Internet who
I actively tried to meet) I know only 1 other person, who is into FIRE and considers this to be a positive thing.
I assume that others either don’t know about it (majority) or find it unattractive or unattainable.
Why didn’t I put this before the alcohol? Because I did actively go to FIRE related meetups and I met
quite a few people interested in or even pursuing FIRE. I have no clue whether I should classify them as my peers or not.
Probably not, but I am not sure. Thus, it is up to you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall this experiment does not invite to write a lot. I wrote a couple paragraphs and already
have 2 opinions. Oh, let’s also phrase them as opinions. So, the first one is “I should not drink any alcohol
aka there is no point in alcohol” (this is just my opinion, if you see a point in alcohol, that’s your opinion
and I will actively force myself to accept it as yours and to respect it). The second one - “I should pursue FIRE, FIRE is good and
will make me happier and improve my life”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I would like to go a bit meta. In general I try to avoid using society opinions when making my decisions.
I speculate that “average” opinions in society are often wrong and misleading and may even be artificially created
e.g. by some companies or the system in general 
(see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak&quot;&gt;my post on how capitalism benefits from this&lt;/a&gt;). 
One concrete example is other people age.
I think that society has unwritten rules “advising” one not to communicate across large age gaps.
I consider this very weird, because when two people communicate, age plays very little or no role at all.
Imagine that there is a set of people, with whom you would enjoy spending your time (this can be any activities,
e.g. just talking, doing sport, walking, hiking). Then if you add an artificial limitation based on age, you just
remove some people from this set, i.e. make finding interesting people even harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously I can see where this is coming from. This indeed works as a stereotype and a heuristic.
Most of the time people with a large age gap may have different interests, goals and problems in life
and, thus, establishing the communication may be hard. However, if you somehow happened to see that another
person is in your “interesting” people set, not building a relationship due to their age would be
a waste of opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I don’t try to do opposite to mainstream opinions. That would be weird. 
I just try to assign them an artificially smaller weight in my decision process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this artificially lowered weight of mainstream opinions could be another example of an opinion
which few of my peers share. I think I know only 1 other person like that, but they are just a random acquaintance
and we don’t talk much these days. Obviously, I don’t discuss this much either.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">The new thought experiment is live and this time it is about unpopular opinions, which your peers don’t share with you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Capitalism wants you to be weak</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalism wants you to be weak" /><published>2019-06-04T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-04T18:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism_makes_you_weak</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/capitalism-makes-you-weak">&lt;p&gt;Mr. Money Mustache wrote multiple times about weaknesses and inconvenience. 
This made me think about the modern world mechanics around them.
I then understood that capitalism benefits from people being weak
and avoiding inconvenience. Let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By capitalism I mean privately owned companies, which operate exclusively for profit.
I am not trying to say that the system is bad - the modern world operates like that anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By weaknesses I mean people choosing options, which are too easy (perhaps even harmfully easy)
for them. Similarly for inconvenience - choosing options, which are too convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;capitalism&quot;&gt;Capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A company’s goal is profit. There are artificial limitations created by governments,
because, otherwise, company’s actions can be even harmful for the customers. E.g. they could
use substances, which are harmful in the long term, to save costs. Alternatively they
could become a monopolist and then start rising prices to have more profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the company’s goal is the profit, whenever there is an opportunity to increase the
profit - the company is likely to take it. For simplicity, let’s consider only 
net-positive opportunities (i.e. ones which are in the end overall positive for the company,
even if at the beginning they can be negative).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;humans&quot;&gt;Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, humans have hedonic adaptation and get used to any current state
and stop enjoying it. Majority of situations can be improved, so the current state can
even be considered inconvenient or too hard. There are also many people, so from probabilistic
view, some of them (outliers) will over-exaggerate and require unnecessary (from majority’s 
perspective) simplification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;both-together&quot;&gt;Both together&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then when someone signals their desire for simplification, this can be a good opportunity 
to make money. As a result, if enough people happen to have this desire and are ready to
pay for its solution, this may become profitable for some company. Since the company’s goal
is profit, they don’t care about how weird or absurd the problem can be. The customers will
pay, this is enough. At the same time the company can even claim that they are improving 
customer lives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;customers want this solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are paying for it (i.e. consider it valuable enough)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thus, they must have a problem and we are solving it for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we get a positive feedback loop. Enough people want some simplification. Some company
fulfills this need. People get used to it due to hedonic adaptation (just start considering it
normal) and want more simplification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own example is washing clothes.
One can have a washing machine or wash them manually. The former saves a lot of time
and effort. However, one still needs to hang the clothes to dry up. I got so used
to the washing machine that I now consider hanging up the clothes as quite inconvenient.
Basically I completely forgot how manual washing would have felt. I can imagine other
people having similar feelings and then some company coming and fixing this issue.
However, I personally remind myself that washing machine already solves 99% of the problem
for me and going for that remaining 1% is an overkill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-step-further&quot;&gt;One step further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously we considered people having a problem and wanting a solution. However, the companies
are also incentivized to create a problem when there is none. In other words, people may consider
something to be ok and normal, but this does not bring any money to for-profit companies. Thus,
they are incentivized to come and “teach” people that their current state is inconvenient, 
sub-optimal, can and should be improved - just pay for the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consider this much more dangerous than fulfilling weird-but-real needs coming from people. In this case,
the company itself affects people. What is even scarier, the company is interested in making
money and they don’t need to consider entire scope of their effect on people. In other words, if
they can make people to buy something, but at the same time there will be some unintended consequences,
the company does not care as long as the customers pay and this is inside governmental boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming with particular examples is hard. I can imagine someone trying to define “beauty” in a way
which helps them sell their product. E.g. some nose shape and plastic surgery or body weight and 
products for losing weight. It is peculiar that companies still can claim that they are improving
people lives (e.g. people still buy their product in some sense voluntarily), but this is
objectively questionable. E.g. if someone would consider themselves ok, but then they get affected
by company advertisement and start considering themselves ugly, then the company just made them less happy.
In some sense, this is caused by people’s irrationality. Yes, they may want to buy something,
but the source of this desire may be external.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is fear. Whenever one fears something, they greatly value protection against it.
Thus, the companies can be incentivized to over-exaggerate how bad something is or just create the fear
artificially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Freakonomics, one particular example are mouthwashes (they use Listerine as an example).
They are incentivized to make you scared of bad breath. According to the book, before Listerine
the bad breath was not considered that bad, but their ads changed this perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/05/fashion/weddings/how-americans-learned-to-love-diamonds.html&quot;&gt;the New York Times&lt;/a&gt;,
diamonds is another example. At some point in history diamonds were not that popular.
However, companies selling diamonds wanted this to be different. As a result, they
managed to convince many that having diamonds (and giving them as present) is good.
This in some sense created a fear - “if I don’t present a diamond, my partner will be less
happy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the human nature, looking at products for kids often illustrates this even better.
Each parent intrinsically wants the best for their children. As a result, 
creating artificial fears and simplifications here is even easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;remarks&quot;&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I considered only existence of people wanting “weird” simplifications, while their quantity
is actually much more important for estimating the actual effect. However, I don’t think such an estimation
is feasible, so I just hypothesize how the mechanic works without any quantitative data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also worth noting, I am not saying that these people are bad. This is their own choice
and they are free to want something. I am just interested how some weird and absurd things end
up on the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important observation is that the actual definition of weakness depends on your own
life situation. E.g. I could say that having a dish washer is unnecessary and such people are weak.
I can imagine someone else saying that having tap water is unnecessary and I am weak.
Nevertheless I suppose that there are some products, which are considered unnecessary by the
majority (e.g. 99%) of the population (hi, &lt;a href=&quot;/post/crazy-pistachio&quot;&gt;crazy pistachio&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I am not against all the simplification. I definitely enjoy having a washing machine, physical safety,
medicine, grocery shops and so on. I think these and many others did improve my life and made it quite better.
In some sense, these do solve major part of some problem for me. I don’t think that the remaining small part
of such problems has to be solved. E.g. I don’t need groceries to be delivered to my place, I am fine with just going
and buying them. Delivery companies could try to create a perspective that buying your own groceries 
is not cool (like not having diamonds during a wedding). I am definitely against such artificial perspective.
Please note that for others this may make more sense, e.g. they are very busy and want to save time.
However, I struggle imagining being so busy (like not having 1-2 hours per week).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">Mr. Money Mustache wrote multiple times about weaknesses and inconvenience. This made me think about the modern world mechanics around them. I then understood that capitalism benefits from people being weak and avoiding inconvenience. Let’s see how.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impro games for non-impro group</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-non-impro-group" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impro games for non-impro group" /><published>2019-06-02T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-02T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/impro_games_for_non_impro_group</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-non-impro-group">&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that some impro games can be played in a group unrelated to impro 
(e.g. work colleagues at a party). Here is my compilation of such games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many impro games one needs a special crowd, which won’t judge and so on
(for more details see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/beauty-of-impro&quot;&gt;my post-reflection about impro in general&lt;/a&gt;).
However, there are many other games, which are just fun and would work even
for people outside of impro. The main requirement is that they don’t require
too much free-form input. E.g. if it is a work party and you suggest to make a scene,
either everyone will feel uncomfortable (the context is wrong) or someone will
say something too dramatic and this will be misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I have previously collected
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/impro-games-for-two&quot;&gt;impro games for two people&lt;/a&gt;,
which might be of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer-about-the-source&quot;&gt;Disclaimer about the source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t make up any games here, I just reference them from &lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/&quot;&gt;improwiki.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compilation&quot;&gt;Compilation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/alien_tiger_cow&quot;&gt;Alien Tiger Cow&lt;/a&gt; - 
on count of 3, everyone represents one of 3 figures. The goal is to converge
to one figure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/be_my_fan&quot;&gt;Be My Fan&lt;/a&gt; -
people play Rock-Paper-Scissors, the one losing becomes a fan of the winner and cheers them up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/blind_stalker&quot;&gt;Blind Stalker&lt;/a&gt; -
people wander around the room (with people-bouncers at the walls) with closed eyes,
there may be a vampire (when they catch someone that person should shout and stop)
and person reviving (they can revive someone who was caught).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/bunny_bunny&quot;&gt;Bunny Bunny&lt;/a&gt; - pass the bunny
with a special hand-finger motion (people around the bunny can do something special as well).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/digits&quot;&gt;Digits&lt;/a&gt; - count to 21 without 
any synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hand Loops (no source, played at a workshop) - everyone gets into a circle and looks down. Then people go towards 
each other with their hands in front of them. They hold on one other hand with each hand.
Then they try to undo “the knot” without releasing the hands.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/forming_molecules&quot;&gt;Forming molecules&lt;/a&gt; -
everyone wanders around, a leader shouts a number, everyone tries to form groups
of this size. When the group is formed they hold hands and sit down.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/group_stop&quot;&gt;Group Stop&lt;/a&gt; - everyone wanders
around, when someone freezes, everyone should freeze. When all freeze, everyone starts
wandering around again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/triangle&quot;&gt;Triangle&lt;/a&gt; - each player takes two other players
as references without telling anyone. Then they try to form an equal triangle with them.
Another variation - try to keep one selected person in the middle between you and the other person
(like a bodyguard and a killer).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/you&quot;&gt;You&lt;/a&gt; - define a chain randomly. Pass “You” across the chain.
Define another chain e.g. with fruits. Pass “fruits”. Add more chains (e.g. sounds, movements).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/samurai&quot;&gt;Samurai&lt;/a&gt; - one establishes eye contact with someone,
raises their sword with “Heeee!”, the other person catches the sword with “Hu!”, then they do their
“Heeee!” and people around them “cut them in half” synchronously with “Haaaa!”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/3_x_different&quot;&gt;3 X different&lt;/a&gt; - two players count 1, 2, 3
one by one. Then they replace 2 with a movement. Then they replace 3 with e.g. saying a name of a famous
person (each time different).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;names&quot;&gt;Names&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/cross_circle&quot;&gt;Cross Circle&lt;/a&gt; - ones names someone,
when the receiver acknowledges, one starts walking towards them. The receiver has to name
someone else and start walking before the first person reaches them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Name Pointing (no source, played at a workshop) -&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 1) point at someone, say your name.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 2) point at someone, say their name.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;(level 3) point at someone, say third person name, the second person has to point at the third person.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;no-interaction&quot;&gt;No interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/circle_up&quot;&gt;Circle Up&lt;/a&gt; - 
shake each hand and leg 7 times, then 6 and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="compilation" /><summary type="html">I’ve noticed that some impro games can be played in a group unrelated to impro (e.g. work colleagues at a party). Here is my compilation of such games.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beauty of impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty-of-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beauty of impro" /><published>2019-05-28T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-28T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty_of_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/beauty-of-impro">&lt;p&gt;As you have already read, I started doing impro recently. I enjoy it enormously. 
This is my reflection on what I enjoy and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a couple words about the concept just in case. Basically a group of people gather together and play
so-called improvisational games. There are many kinds of such games, but the main idea is to be very
spontaneous and just channel your ideas outside. Usually there is a suggestion from the group for the 
theme, so that the players are forced to be spontaneous and couldn’t prepare anything in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the contrast to games in general, here it is rarely about winning or losing. You mostly fight yourself (being shy,
indecisive, blocking your ideas). The mechanics often has no way to win or lose. Very often
the game forces people to cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common class of games is based around “scenes”. Here two or more
players get on the “stage” (this can be just part of the room), get some suggestion from the audience (e.g. their
location and relationship) and then just do the scene without any script. There are multiple variations, which usually
add some limitation to the scene mechanics or just spice things up. E.g. I like “new choice” game a lot. 
There two players do the scene and a moderator can say “next choice”. The player who did something before
“next choice” was said has to redo their action or phrase again, but differently. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IPfkJo3e7_M&quot;&gt;This youtube video&lt;/a&gt; gives a nice example,
but keep in mind that folks there are extremely good at this and had a lot of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;necessary-conditions&quot;&gt;Necessary conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that impro won’t work if group tries to judge participants or use what they say and do against them later.
This must be a safe space for experimentation without any long standing consequences for the participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering why, but it is simple. Once one stops blocking their ideas, they start getting a lot of them,
but majority (especially at first) can be perceived as weird (especially from a mainstream point of view).
This is definitely not person’s fault. I feel that brain just works that way. In our normal everyday life we learned 
very deeply to cut such ideas quickly and never express them. Impro is about trying to reverse this process. You just get
some idea and go with it, because usually you have no time to evaluate it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This non-judgment part feels very bizarre at the beginning. The first couple times you come, you still block your ideas
just in case. You don’t want to look weird and scare people off. But at the same time if the group happens to have
experienced people (you should aim for such groups), you will observe that they do pretty crazy stuff and people
react perfectly fine to this. The most common examples are insults, swearing and sexually related topics.
After some time observing others, you start trying a bit crazier ideas yourself and notice that no one objects.
Eventually, you will stop blocking yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding long lasting consequences - the impro group can be non-judging, but the mainstream society (or your non-impro friends)
may be not like that. Thus, I personally prefer to keep stuff which happens at impro sessions just there. E.g. majority
of people outside of impro would not understand what happens there at all. But they don’t have to.
As long as the group understands you and everything is kept inside the group, you are fine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-yourself&quot;&gt;Understanding yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After starting impro I noticed that this thought post-processing mechanism (the one blocking ideas)
sits very deeply in my mind.
Consider a game “free association”. Basically each player says a word, the next player has to say the first thing
that comes to their mind. This is extremely hard at first. You get some word very quickly, but then all this machinery
jumps in and in no time you get thoughts like “this word makes no sense, it is not related to the previous word,
should I say it? Will it be embarrassing?”. I personally found this very surprising. Fortunately, this gets better
with practice. But still it is extremely peculiar to observe our brain “low level” machinery so vividly. 
In some sense this is similar to mediation. In mediation, you try to keep your thoughts under control. Here you 
try to avoid wandering away as well. In some sense impro helps to go on meta level and observe how you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;Experimentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This safe space is actually extremely valuable, because you can try out new stuff there without worrying of being judged.
Normally if you can’t or never tried singing, you feel scared to try, especially in front of other people.
They may get upset and tell you that they don’t like your singing. One is scared to embarrass themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read somewhere that this fear to embarrass yourself is an evolutionary advantage. If you imagine 
prehistoric people, each of them separately was quite weak against all various dangers in nature. But when they gathered into
groups it worked out much better (basically, they used their ability to communicate to their advantage). However, when the group
does not like you, they will kick you out. Then you are on your own, which is not a pleasant experience,
especially in prehistoric times. Thus, people started fearing being rejected by a group, which could happen as a result of
misbehaving or embarrassing yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that desire to keep the group happy is bad per-se.
E.g. in work context, being scared to embarrass yourself sounds fair.
However, the modern society propagates this to other branches of life. As a result, one is scared to try new stuff,
to take risks and to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to our singing example, one could easily try singing at an impro workshop. Since the group is non-judgmental
(e.g. due to the nature of impro itself), they won’t judge singing either. Obviously, this is not a hard rule, but
I would be extremely surprised if someone said you something negative (that would not be very kind of them).
Once you try, you can see how you feel and whether
you like it. Perhaps by trying multiple times you can even improve your skill a bit. Or, on the other hand,
you can understand that you actually don’t enjoy singing that much and just drop it completely.
Either outcome sounds like a good progress to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that this could work especially well for learning languages. Very often people who learn new languages, feel
self conscious. They don’t want to embarrass themselves in front of others by making mistakes, taking too long to speak
or talking weirdly. Obviously, non-native language at impro is a handicap. However, at the same time, since the group is
non-judgmental, at impro one can get through their own language embarrassment barrier and just get used to using the language
and observe that others do understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This definitely applies to various artsy stuff like dancing, singing, playing music instruments,
writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-boundaries-and-possibly-getting-through-them&quot;&gt;Understand your boundaries and possibly getting through them&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern society has plenty of unwritten rules, especially about behavior, communication or relationships.
Everyone is highly incentivized (aka forced) to be “normal”. Yes, there are ways to differentiate yourself,
but they are all highly preselected, like templates from which you can choose. You can have
some other kind of clothing or even a tattoo, but there are plenty of other people who will do this as well.
Overall, you are encouraged to be predictable and easy to understand to simplify everyone’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I find extremely funny is that when growing up one just gives up their unpredictability and curiosity. When you were a kid,
you didn’t know “rules of the game”, i.e. norms of the society. That’s why crying loudly on a plane didn’t bother you as well
as wearing dirty clothing. In some sense, there is nothing intrinsically wrong with either, just the society happens
to be against. With time you get directed more and more and eventually just accept these new norms and become an adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During impro you hit these boundaries quickly. Normally you don’t observe them explicitly in your life. They are just there like
invisible walls, but you probably never went that far, so from your perspective these limitations didn’t exist. Impro encourages
you to go all the way and you very quickly discover that, yes, there are plenty of blocks and boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering them is already extremely valuable. But with impro and safe space you can go even further - to the other side.
I am not saying that you should drop all the norms in the society completely.
No. But understanding that they are there is useful and getting through them at least at impro sessions is a nice exercise as well.
Then it can be your own explicit choice to follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If growing up adds blocks and limitations to your life and impro helps you to become aware of them and to remove some,
then impro is equivalent to trying to become a child again. In other words, ungrowing up. If you think about it, you did
actually play such games as a child a lot. You would gather with other children, come up with some shared fantasy world
or some life situation (doctor or fireman) and then explore that world together with others according to its mechanics.
If someone suggested you to consider a stone to be your spaceship, you would easily accept that.
If someone says that you are attacked by aliens and you need to run, you would run and shout. This is precisely how impro works.
You do a scene with someone in a shared reality, either of you can suggest something and other can either accept it or refuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;confidence&quot;&gt;Confidence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not being scared of embarrassing yourself (i.e. taking risks) looks like confidence for an external observer. 
From this perspective, impro helps you to gain confidence. Another peculiar fact is that you can get used to people being non-judgmental. Then assume the same in other situations, e.g. when you make a presentation for a large crowd.
Obviously, people there are much more likely to be judgmental, but in majority of cases people just don’t care at all.
I know, this is hard to believe, because from your perspective you are the main hero of everything in your life and everyone
seems to care about you, but from their perspective they are the heroes. Thus, assuming that people are non-judgmental
can help you in situations outside of impro and improve your confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, not judging others yourself is also extremely cool. When someone does something unusual, you are tempted to
stop them quickly, e.g. if it is inappropriate or you don’t understand it. But during impro you learn
to notice this and instead just let it be. In the end, it is other person’s choice and their action.
Thus, this skill can help you to support people in creative situations, especially when they take risks and can
embarrass themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;people&quot;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, such an unusual activity gathers peculiar people as well. Very often they come from various backgrounds,
but somehow find a common language and collaborate. Learning cool people is definitely another benefit of impro
sessions, which I enjoy. As well as socializing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acting&quot;&gt;Acting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Majority of games culminate with acting, so you get to practice acting a lot and in various situations.
This is definitely nice. You get to experience situations, which you would not encounter normally. This helps
to understand other perspectives better. You obviously improve your acting skills too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;play-and-fun&quot;&gt;Play and fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, impro is all about play and having fun! I believe that all people are very playful and enjoy
free-form playing, but are unfortunately limited by the society and opinions of others. Impro gives you
a chance to play. In some sense it allows you to be yourself. Once you
are not limited by society it is easier to express your own views, emotions and just represent your inner self.
As a result, this is often a very fun process. Obviously at first there is some introduction period where you get
used to the concept, stop being scared and slowly experiment while crossing your own boundaries.
Eventually, you get there and this kind of play just brings a lot of joy. It is also extremely funny. I do laugh
a lot, because some scenes are surprisingly hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy ungrowing up!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="improv" /><category term="improvisation" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">As you have already read, I started doing impro recently. I enjoy it enormously. This is my reflection on what I enjoy and why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impro games for two</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-two" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impro games for two" /><published>2019-05-26T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-26T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/impro_games_for_two</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/impro-games-for-two">&lt;p&gt;I tried impro recently (aka improv, improvisation theater). I did extremely enjoy the experience, but also felt like I
didn’t get enough out of the workshops (they are surprisingly crowded). Thus, I will try to practice in much smaller
groups (like 2 people). This can be challenging since majority of games are for more people. Here is my compilation
of warmup and “main course” impro games for 2 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start, a couple words about impro in general. The main idea is to come on stage without any preparation
and to develop some theatrical scene on the go, possibly with some artificial limitations or a forced format.
This may sound extremely challenging. And, yes, it is challenging, but the important detail is that the crowd
has to be special. They must be very open-minded, non-judging and not to take what you say personally.
This allows you to just say the first thing you have in your mind. Yes, it may be extremely embarrassing and
scary (especially at first - “this people will be aware of the weird thoughts / ideas I am having”). But after 
some time and observing others, one starts realizing that everyone occasionally has weird ideas and people just 
accept and celebrate that. No one criticizes and blames. No one takes your ideas against you. Basically you
start trusting the crowd. But as I said above you need a special crowd for this, this won’t work with random people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally there are various “workshops” where you can practice impro with others. Usually these are just
gatherings of people, where they play “impro games” - games which require one to improvise. Using my notation
above, these games add artificial limitations to what you can say or do. Usually there is also a moderator - an experienced
person, who gives the high level direction - which games to play, how and when to stop. They may also give advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such gatherings are definitely fun, but there are often a lot of people.
Sometimes the games require a participant “to die” when they make a mistake (i.e. just leaving the stage).
Thus, the active play time can be very limited (too many people in the first place and then “losing” quickly).
As a result, one mostly observes. So now I am trying to form a smaller “unofficial” group (starting with only
me and someone else) to play these games on our own and to practice more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not meant as a replacement for the workshops. I think that at workshops one gets new ideas from others
or a moderator and tests their skills in “real” scenarios with audience. In a smaller group one
can actually practice what they observed at the workshop and hone their skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worth noting that there are usually two major kinds of games - warmup and the main games. They have different goals.
The warmup games are meant to activate you and to bring you in a cheery mood, so that you improvise better.
They may involve some improvisation, but just a little bit (e.g. one suggestion at a time). Usually they involve
concentrating on what others do and paying attention to them. They also may involve physical activity - jumping, dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer-about-sources&quot;&gt;Disclaimer about sources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not making up any games on my own here. This is just a compilation and I just reference games from &lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/&quot;&gt;improwiki.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;games&quot;&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For brevity, players are denoted as A and B.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may use Wikipedia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Random&quot;&gt;random article link&lt;/a&gt; as a source of suggestions,
when a game requires some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;warmup&quot;&gt;Warmup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warmup for 2 people is extremely tricky, because the majority of exercises are meant for groups.
It is also easy to pay attention to others, when there is only one other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;Interaction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/call_and_reply&quot;&gt;Call and Reply&lt;/a&gt; - set 
the rhythm, A sings a line in Gibberish, B repeats the line together with A.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/follow_the_king&quot;&gt;Follow the king&lt;/a&gt; - 
A moves around the room while avoiding invisible obstacles, B follows A
and avoids the same obstacles at the same places (as if they are really there).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/last_word_-_first_word&quot;&gt;Last word - first word&lt;/a&gt; - A says a
line, B has to say a line starting with the last word A said.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/free_association&quot;&gt;Free Association&lt;/a&gt; -
association game without thinking - A says a word, B says what came to mind first
as is. One can play in Gibberish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/peculiar_neighbor&quot;&gt;Peculiar neighbor&lt;/a&gt; - 
A says to B something that stands out, B must accept, explain and clarify.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/what_is_a_what&quot;&gt;What is a what?&lt;/a&gt; -
rhyming. Everything must be said in “What is a &amp;lt;word X&amp;gt;, without a &amp;lt;word Y&amp;gt;?” format.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-interaction&quot;&gt;No interaction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/block_of_ice&quot;&gt;Block of ice&lt;/a&gt; - imagine 
that A is frozen in a block of ice which melts from the top. As their body parts
get free, they can move them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;physical&quot;&gt;Physical&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/circle_up&quot;&gt;Circle Up&lt;/a&gt; - shaking hands
and legs 7 times, 6 and so on until 1 (while counting).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/sword_of_samurai&quot;&gt;Sword of samurai&lt;/a&gt; -
slow motion - hands = swords, when they touch = sword sounds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/what_are_you_doing&quot;&gt;What Are You Doing!&lt;/a&gt; -
A mimes, B - “What are you doing?”, A says something they didn’t mime,
B mimes what A said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;main&quot;&gt;Main&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/3_x_different&quot;&gt;3 X different&lt;/a&gt; - count
1, 2, 3, one by one and replace each number with something (e.g. an action).
The action can be non-repetitive (e.g. say a famous person name, each time different).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/gibberish_circle&quot;&gt;Gibberish Circle&lt;/a&gt; -
A explains something in Gibberish (with gestures), B translates into English, but using
the same gestures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/story_solo&quot;&gt;Story Solo&lt;/a&gt; - A tells a story,
B can say a word, A has to use it in their next sentence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scenes-with-limitations&quot;&gt;Scenes with limitations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/talk_at_touch&quot;&gt;Talk at touch&lt;/a&gt; - 
one can speak only when they touch the other player.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/emotional_replay&quot;&gt;Emotional replay&lt;/a&gt; - 
play a scene. Then choose an emotion, replay a scene with that emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/scene_mix_10x20&quot;&gt;Scene mix 10x20&lt;/a&gt; -
play 10 scenes (20 seconds each) and try to establish the scene ASAP.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/he_said_she_said&quot;&gt;He said, she said&lt;/a&gt; -
A says their line, B says “he said while &amp;lt;some action&amp;gt;” and A has to perform
&amp;lt;some action&amp;gt;. To make the flow more natural, one can swap the order, i.e.
A says “he said while…” and then B says something while doing what A said.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/new_choice&quot;&gt;New Choice&lt;/a&gt; - 
play a scene. When “New Choice” is said, the player has to replace their last
line or action with something different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/pen_friends&quot;&gt;Pen Friends&lt;/a&gt; - two
pen friends meet and remember what they read in the letter and find affirmations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/an_illustration&quot;&gt;An illustration&lt;/a&gt; -
both players suggest a pose for each other, play a scene and each end up
in suggested poses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/the_conscience&quot;&gt;The Conscience&lt;/a&gt; -
play a scene, any player can become other player Conscience (i.e. give commands,
express doubt etc) for some time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://improwiki.com/en/wiki/improv/countdown&quot;&gt;Countdown&lt;/a&gt; - perform a scene
in time X, then exactly the same scene in X/2 and so on until you get to
10 seconds. After that do “a photo moment” - just one pose from the scene.
This works better with a lot of movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general any game where 2 players do something and moderator somehow affects
them (like “New Choice”) can be attempted just by 2 players alone. Each player then can affect
the other player in the same way (like saying “New Choice”). You may need to agree on your
intention before the game, e.g. saying “Next Choice” can be done to make the scene funnier
or when the person does not like what the other person said.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><category term="improv" /><category term="improvisation" /><summary type="html">I tried impro recently (aka improv, improvisation theater). I did extremely enjoy the experience, but also felt like I didn’t get enough out of the workshops (they are surprisingly crowded). Thus, I will try to practice in much smaller groups (like 2 people). This can be challenging since majority of games are for more people. Here is my compilation of warmup and “main course” impro games for 2 people.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 8)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-8" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 8)" /><published>2019-05-21T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-21T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-8">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 8, recognizing relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;follow-up-to-previous-lecture&quot;&gt;Follow-up to previous lecture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;heritability&quot;&gt;Heritability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that humans have 5 fingers is an inherited trait.
However, the variability of #fingers is exclusively due to environment, thus, heritability
is 0%. People often assume that heritability tells whether a trait is inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;previous-disciplines&quot;&gt;Previous disciplines&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous three approaches (behavioral evolution, molecular genetics, behavioral genetics)
are just descriptions at different levels. For example one can view epigenetics as either of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way how culture and environment affects biology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the way in which environment turns genes on/off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;regulation of chromatin, remodeling, regulation of genes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;behavioral-genetics&quot;&gt;Behavioral genetics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;classical - adoption studies, good at showing that environment has less impact than assumed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modern - we suspect that a given gene has some behavioral effect, let’s see which.
Alternatively, we suspect that this behavior is genetic - let’s see the link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;observed-effect-size&quot;&gt;Observed effect size&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When evaluating studies, keep the observed difference size in mind.
For example, there was a study of 250k 18 years old in Norway, which has shown that 
first borns have higher IQ than second borns. There could be multiple ways to explain this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parental investment - no, they controlled for this, if you are the only child, you have
lower IQ than first born with younger siblings.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Tutoring” phenomenon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mother age (egg quality) - they controlled for this too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each pregnancy causes immune suppression, a mother could become less healthy after the first pregnancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to age 12 second borns have higher IQ than first borns. By age 18 it gets other way around.
A second born IQ reverts to the level of first born, if the first born dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the difference was only 2.3 IQ points (as Sapolsky says “sneeze at the IQ test
and you get this difference”), i.e. not important at all (even though the study has been done
in a very elaborate fashion).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-8-recognizing-relatives&quot;&gt;Lecture 8: Recognizing relatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ability to recognize relatives can be present even in very primitive organisms. E.g. deer mice have 2 strains -
monogamous and polygamous, the later has sperm competition. When sperm forms a clump,
it travels better. However, in polygamous strain sperm tries to form a clump only with its own kind. 
In the monogamous strain, this is not the case (happily forming a clump with any sperm).
In the polygamous case, sperm “knows” who it is related. This is example of single cells recognizing
relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can show innate relative recognition by cross fostering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanisms&quot;&gt;Mechanisms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pheromones&quot;&gt;Pheromones&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pheromonal communication can be used for relative recognition. 
One needs qualitative differences e.g. in urine (reflecting genetic makeup)
and some mechanism to process the differences. This is achieved by creating a completely
unique protein (major histocompatibility complex), which functions like a fingerprint.
This protein is attached to each of your cells (at the surface). Your immune system
uses it to detect your own cells. This protein can become soluble
(saliva, urine) and give unique signature to pheromones coming off of you.
These protein structure is also more similar in closer relatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxytocin and vasoprasin tune cells in olfactory system for better accuracy to recognize relatives and,
if the match is good, take care of them (e.g. baby after birth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only 2 areas in the brain, which have neurogenesis (new neurons generation) in adults  - hippocampus (learning) and behind olfactory bulb.
In rats, new neurons in the olfactory bulb are created before giving birth. This way the mother can detect her babies better and
bond to them. This can explain weird sense of smell during pregnancy as well as a desire for unusual
foods. Basically, olfactory system gets heavily renovated to improve accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons distinguish social implications of dominance reversal depending on family relatedness
(if rank 4 submits to rank 27 - others have no interest if 4 and 27 are from the same family - “crazy relatives”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mating, one has contradicting goals - prevent inbreeding, but to pass as much of their own genes as possible.
As a result, mating with the 3rd cousin (i.e. two of your grandparents are siblings, i.e. had the same parents) is the optimal solution.
This is observed in nature. Humans also find the odor of 3rd cousin the most appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;non-innate-recognition&quot;&gt;Non innate recognition&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non innate recognition requires imprinting, i.e. learning who’s mother / baby.
The fact that learning occurs is innate. One can learn sounds, odor or appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goats don’t have innate ability to recognize relatives. Instead there are other approximations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“smells like my vaginal fluids”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lick the kid and “smells like my saliva”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scent mark and “smells like me”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mouth smells like my milk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be used to detect siblings as well, e.g. “smells like my mom vaginal fluid”.
This can be proven by cross fostering, the goat will take longer to decide (“hm, it does not smell
that much like my vaginal fluid”), but in the end will take care of the kid anyway (“but there is no other baby,
so yeah, it must be mine”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cognitive&quot;&gt;Cognitive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humans do it cognitively. Hey, I see this one baby around me, it must be the one I just gave birth too.
Who was the father? The only guy with whom I had sex. To detect sibling - “I saw mom giving birth to them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons can also do this. Males care about kids more when they are sure.
E.g. “if I am the only one who mated with her” (for example, female can be too young and
not that fertile, thus, no interest from higher rank baboons and, as a result, mate with exactly one lower rank baboon).
They also consider probabilities - the closer to female’s prime fertility point a baboon mated with her,
the more likely he is to take care of the kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works even in fish. In sunfish males are very paternal. If you bring another male
(e.g. in an transparent container) between a female and a male (closer to the female), the latter male will assume
that he is not the father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fusiform cortex is used to recognize faces.
Normally it fires more for relatives (e.g. mom &amp;gt; stranger &amp;gt; chair).
In autistic people it does not work well (mom ~ stranger ~ chair).
Sheep and pigeons have it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babies can distinguish mom smell after birth (but not dad’s) - when given two sources of smell,
they prefer one with mom’s smell. The can recognize mom’s voice (by learning it from inside),
but not dad’s (hard to hear it from inside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this affect your decision who to mate with?
One study considered Kibbutz in Israel, a collective community, which raises their kids all together.
If two kids were raised in the same age group up to 6 years of age, they never marry each other.
In other words, if it is someone, who you spend a lot of time before 6 years of age, you don’t mate with them
(they are more like a sibling).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ways to manipulate us to feel more/less related than we are (pseudo kinship / pseudo speciation).
Military does this a lot (us - brothers, them - non-humans).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 8, recognizing relatives.</summary></entry></feed>