<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-12T22:17:12+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Your time networth</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-networth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your time networth" /><published>2019-05-12T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-05-12T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly_networth</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-networth">&lt;p&gt;Many people know how many percents of their networth is invested in X.
However, occasionally it is much more important how you invest your time.
I call this  (surprise) “time allocation”. Let’s see how to do this and a couple
of unexpected examples, where percentage looks much scarier than the plain number of hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trigger&quot;&gt;Trigger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started looking into this topic to estimate how much “free” time I normally
have per week. The idea was to make sure that, when I plan something for a given week, I don’t set
obviously unreasonable goals. At first this wasn’t anything special,
I just used some quick spreadsheet and got the numbers. However, then I checked
the percentages (i.e. how many percent of my weekly time a given activity takes)
and was surprised by how much I underestimated them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beauty&quot;&gt;Beauty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way of looking at your time allocation has many interesting properties.
For example, if you do some activity every week (let’s imagine for the rest of your life),
then this weekly time allocation becomes “rest of your life” time allocation.
This definitely makes you feel differently. This implicitly forces you to prioritize:
“Wait, this will take 10% of my life, do I actually need to do this?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another observation is that time is your main resource.
Yes, you can use money for some approximation, but money is just 
a representation of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I know how you spend your money and your asset allocation, I do know
a lot about you. But knowing how you spend your time, gives away almost everything about you,
except your reasons for doing something, i.e. “why”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common advice to look at what people do and not what they say.
This exercise partially helps you to look at what you do, instead of what you 
feel you do or want to do. People are bad at estimates and it is very easy to say
I am X (e.g. writer) and feel like you spend enough time on this activity.
What if you discover that only 5% of your weekly time goes to X?
Are you then just 5% of a writer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be peculiar to know at the end of a life how much time went 
into something. This could be some kind of ultimate measure, how much of a writer
a person was. Obviously, different activities consume time differently, so it may be
that you are indeed a writer, this just didn’t require that much time.
I agree. I don’t claim that this “answers your life question” or that it is completely perfect.
No, but it gives an interesting perspective, which I enjoy and find useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it may be tricky to get a complete picture, since majority
of things we do are not repeated across weeks. I suggest you to start with at least
something and just consider activities you do weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely plan to explore better time tracking (probably at a very low granularity
for a short period of time). I do track my expenses, so optimizing time is an obvious next target.
Having this data would help me to get a better picture of my actual time allocation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to&quot;&gt;How to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that you are now intrigued enough to give it a try.
I prepared 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qa4PZYtSACpZm2HEDDgZvoeXUAIYOmeBvLWaJYeERyQ/edit&quot;&gt;a spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;,
which you can reuse (just make a copy).
5 minutes granularity was reasonable for me, so that’s what
the spreadsheet has, however, you are welcome to use 1 hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically each cell means “how I spend the next 5 minutes”.
Below there are cells with all the calculations (sums and ratios).
The data is just an example to give you an idea what you can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how various activity durations correspond to percentages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour daily -&amp;gt; 1 hour / day * 7 days / (168 hours / week) = 4.1% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour every working day -&amp;gt; 1 hour / day * 5 days / (168 hours / week) = 2.9% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 hour once a week -&amp;gt; 1 hour / (168 hours / week) = 0.59% week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 minute daily -&amp;gt; 1 minute / day * / (60 minutes / hour * 168 hours / week) = 0.069% week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is anyone asking your for a commitment taking 1 hour once a week
for the rest of your life? If you agree, you will “spend” 0.59% of the
rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-improvements&quot;&gt;Possible improvements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously everyone has to sleep and do exercises and this is good.
However, when these are taken into account in the denominator, we are
implicitly incentivized to spend less time on them. This feels wrong.
Thus, you may subtract some activities from denominator (i.e. from 168 hours per week, sleep is
an obvious candidate) to mitigate this issue. For my use case,
this was not needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy conscious time planning!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="exercise" /><category term="productivity" /><category term="self improvement" /><category term="different perspective" /><summary type="html">Many people know how many percents of their networth is invested in X. However, occasionally it is much more important how you invest your time. I call this (surprise) “time allocation”. Let’s see how to do this and a couple of unexpected examples, where percentage looks much scarier than the plain number of hours.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">FIRE is a marathon, not a sprint</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-marathon-not-sprint" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FIRE is a marathon, not a sprint" /><published>2019-04-30T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-30T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_marathon_not_sprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-marathon-not-sprint">&lt;p&gt;I’ve caught myself delaying a lot of (mostly pleasant) stuff to post FIRE times (i.e. quite far in the future).
Let’s see what caused this, what the risks are and how I now avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trigger&quot;&gt;Trigger&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that I have somewhat burned myself out recently. This is definitely not the complete
burn out and I am getting much better now, but this made me revisit my lifestyle
and priorities. Overall, my wellbeing definitely suffered: I had pessimistic mood, which
changed often, and too much interest in food (aka overeating, mostly of sweet and fatty foods).
Previously I definitely had periods where I felt somewhat down, but I never experienced such
overeating before, which obviously scared me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis&quot;&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to find out what’s wrong and… googled it. I could have gone to the doctor,
but I prefer to spend couple minutes (ok, this is a lie, couple hours, whatever) researching
on my own to save the trip if the issue
is not too bad. There happens to be a lot food related psychological disorders and
some of them are very bizarre. I probably won’t go into many details here, since it is not
the most pleasant thing to read about. But one bit caught my eye - basically some website claimed
that one can overeat to compensate deficiency of fun in life. Eating sugary and fatty foods
is similar from chemical perspective in brain to consuming drugs and having fun and if you have too little fun
your body just tries to fix this by binging and overeating (as the last available resort to have some fun).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-causes&quot;&gt;Possible causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suspicion is that aiming for FIRE can promote such state.
It may sound weird, but doing something fun actually requires some effort
(at least you have to do something not-so-fun before it becomes fun, like going somewhere or
preparing something). So if one uses their energy efficiently (aka just being lazy), they are
in some sense disincentivized to do something fun due to the effort involved.
Normally, the positive side of the activity is so strong that people don’t even notice
the effort involved at all or it is masked by anticipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, FIRE adds another reason against doing something - money.
You’ve already cut out a bunch of unimportant stuff from your life and pretty much got 
used to this way of thinking - do I really need this? What I am actually paying for here with my money (i.e. time)?
So when considering doing something fun, now we have at least 2 reasons against it.
First, it requires some effort. Second, money. It is also peculiar that this “money saving
perspective” affects one’s default choice. Normally people would rather do 
some fun activity by default if they are not sure. But after cutting out so much garbage,
a person aiming for FIRE will rather have “not go” by default. Moreover, sometimes answering 
“do I actually like or need this at all and which exactly part of it and why?” is tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if one does side hustling to reach FIRE faster, this can produce another
heavy argument against doing something fun. In particular, one can think:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I will rather reach FIRE sooner by side hustling now. Then I will have all
the fun in the world. Ok, back to side hustling now instead of this “fun” activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is already the third brick against the fun activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, it is very easy to focus on FIRE and delay (or even ignore) everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risks&quot;&gt;Risks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One risk is your body disagreeing. This is just my personal anecdote, but I suspect that
this is a very likely outcome. A peculiar consequence of this (a wild speculation) is the risk
to change your overall view to FIRE. Imagine that you work hard, focus on FIRE and ignore everything 
else. Your dissatisfaction may grow and get collected inside you. At some point you can just snap
and overcompensate all the way out of FIRE completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting option is that this may affect your post FIRE life negatively.
Imagine that you’ve been finding reasons why a bunch of fun activities (like going to a
theater, but insert something else if your opinion of fun is different, I understand)
are not that interesting to you.
And then on one magical day you conclude that you are now FIRE and have plenty of time
to actually do all the fun… Oh, wait, is there anything fun left? You’ve been finding
reasons against going to the theater for years, will reaching FIRE magically switch
something in your brain and you will forget all these reasons? I doubt that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this boundary between having fun and spending too much is very faint and narrow.
So you probably might overshoot a bit. To avoid that I would suggest to see by how much having fun
does delay your FIRE date. If it is something like 1-2 month, this is comparable to
error margin (e.g. due to the market mood swings) and seems pretty safe. I understand that you
can be very rational and having your fun budget invested will improve your FIRE chances
and date, but if you then overstretch yourself, forget rationality and drop FIRE idea completely?
So 1-2 months seems fine, everything else is up to you. This is your life and your money
and you probably shouldn’t trust Internet when deciding what to do with them (but I use 1-2 month
approach, just FYI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I made &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/pages/calculator.html&quot;&gt;a calculator&lt;/a&gt; precisely for that
 (disclaimer: this is the very early version, so early that I can’t even call it first). Basically it allows
you to answer question “if I decrease my investing by X once/every month/year, how much does this delay my FIRE date?”
and X is meant to be your fun budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally started to catch myself whenever I have some positive feeling towards doing something fun.
Instead of shooing it away with “I am busy, perhaps come back later?”, I stop and remind myself that
I haven’t been doing anything fun for ages and my wellbeing has taken a hit and occasionally it is
tricky to understand what I really enjoy, so I should probably do this activity. I definitely keep in
mind the money aspect (e.g. I still have fun efficiently, for example, by choosing the cheapest theater ticket).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also hope to stop delaying various ideas and projects. I understand that they may not speed up
my FIRE process, but I would rather build my small scale version of FIRE life now and then upscale it
once reaching FIRE instead of being completely demotivated and having no clue what to do with all
the free time I’ve got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish you a fun path to your FIRE!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="FIRE" /><category term="perspective" /><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">I’ve caught myself delaying a lot of (mostly pleasant) stuff to post FIRE times (i.e. quite far in the future). Let’s see what caused this, what the risks are and how I now avoid this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The worst that can happen</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-worst-that-can-happen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The worst that can happen" /><published>2019-04-28T13:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-28T13:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/the_worst_that_can_happen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-worst-that-can-happen">&lt;p&gt;Asking yourself “What is the worst that can happen as a result of a given activity?” can help you
to start doing tasks where you are scared to fail or to avoid dangerous activities. Let’s see
how it helps me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like feeling embarrassed, failing or showing my incompetence. 
I’d bet many of you are the same. However, these fears are pretty irrational
and they can prevent me from doing or even trying to do something where I can
fail. I especially observe this in creative work and large complex tasks.
In creative work there is always something sitting inside you and
whispering (or shouting) “this is shit, no one will like it, people will laugh at you,
don’t waste your time, you know this, just give up and call it a day, do something easy
instead, even you don’t like it” and so on. In the case of large tasks, there are so
many different parts to it that you just can’t have a complete plan. As a result you
are not sure whether what you are doing now actually helps you to accomplish the task. In both
cases this is like an internal built-in heuristic against wasting your time. There are
situations where this makes sense, but nowadays this is rarely the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking “what is the worst that can happen” helps me to get through this heuristic.
In most creative efforts (like writing this blog post or coding a game) the failure is not
as bad as it is perceived to be. For example, I am writing this blog post now
and I am not sure whether it will end up being interesting or useful to anyone. 
But what is the worst that can happen? Someone won’t like this post and may write
me an angry email. Or I won’t like this post myself and just delete it completely without
publishing at all. Asking this question helps me to change my perspective. Instead of 
being scared of this abstract notion of a failure (the last word should be read with a spooky voice),
I actually try to make it explicit - yes, I can fail, but what does that mean precisely? Is it actually
that bad and scary as I think? More formally you just explicitly estimate a lower bound for the outcome.
Instead of saying abstract “failing is bad, I don’t like failing” you say how bad it actually is.
This gives you something precise to cope with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/the_worst_that_can_happen/before_after.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing one large spooky vague failure somewhere far away on the negative
side before asking the question and a bunch of specific failures with definite locations
on the negativity spectrum after.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One negative consequence present in any endeavor is wasting your time.
You did something, it didn’t work out and is of no use now, the time spent doing it is gone
(if I add “forever” here this feels even scarier). However, that’s fine. First, you tried
to experiment with something, to do something risky and unusual and you didn’t manage.
This is much better than just giving up and perhaps you have learned something in the process
which may improve your chances next time. Second, even if you don’t “waste” your time on this task,
how would you use it differently? At least for me this often means consuming some content
(like Reddit or Youtube). But time spent doing this is gone forever too and I am not sure what
is better, since I will very likely learn nothing from Reddit or Youtube in majority of cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formulating a task in a specific way can help as well. One can say “I will do this large cool
game perfectly and publish it immediately and show to millions of people” and this becomes hard.
Just finishing a game is already tricky, doing this perfectly on the first try is impossible.
Furthermore, the commitment to publish it just increases the amount of embarrassment you can get.
Instead you can say “I will create the first version of my game somehow (it won’t be perfect but
will show the concept) and I will show it to 1 person”. This person can even be you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is a good example of me applying “what the worst that can happen” iteratively.
I am definitely not sure whether a given post will be interesting to anyone except me,
but in the worst case it will be just there and people won’t read it (or I delete it instead of 
publishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach can also be used to avoid dangerous and risky stuff. If you ask yourself
“what the worst that can happen” and if the answer does look scary to you (e.g. physical injury
for the rest of your life), you probably shouldn’t do this. However, this approach is not perfect 
and you can’t just follow it blindly. This is just a lower bound of the outcome, which does not
take into account how likely the outcome is. Reasoning with this approach one shouldn’t fly on planes,
drive cars or even get on the street all, because the worst outcome there is death.
Thus, once you feel that the lower bound is too pessimistic, you may consider some more likely outcome instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy highly motivated creative work!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity" /><category term="perspective" /><category term="creative" /><summary type="html">Asking yourself “What is the worst that can happen as a result of a given activity?” can help you to start doing tasks where you are scared to fail or to avoid dangerous activities. Let’s see how it helps me.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">TODOs are your friends</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/todos-are-your-friends" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TODOs are your friends" /><published>2019-04-24T07:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-24T07:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/todos_are_your_friends</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/todos-are-your-friends">&lt;p&gt;I’ve started using TODOs not only in my code. Now I find them very useful
in this new context. E.g. they can be a hint to prioritize and to postpone less important tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-todo&quot;&gt;What is a TODO?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A TODO is just a comment in the code describing a way to improve a given bit of code
(basically what should or could be done later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be various reasons to add a TODO, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the thing it describes is blocked on some other work (e.g. refactoring)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;currently the author does not have time for this much better approach described in a TODO,
while the current approach is good enough for now, but could be improved later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO accomplishes number of functions, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helping the author not to forget to do something&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;informing the reader that
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;a given bit can be improved&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the author knew about this better way, but for some reason decided not to do it yet.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;todos-outside-of-code&quot;&gt;TODOs outside of code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I started using TODOs in my code, I naturally started adding them in other areas of my life as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you do a large enough project (e.g. writing a large blog post or trying to plan
a large event), you have a lot of tasks and can feel overwhelmed. Often there are just
to many of them and some can even pull more further work. As a result, if one is a perfectionist, one can
easily get stuck already at the first task by going too deep into it and producing very little utility
for the entire project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, imagine you are doing some website to test a new idea.
You could setup its backend perfectly, including, for example, plenty of tests, easy one click scalability
and super powerful servers. However, very soon in the process this stops helping much with your original goal -
to test an idea. Perhaps the idea won’t work for some other reasons and all this hard work will be then even wasted.
On the other hand, it can be hard to just say “ok, I will do poor quality work here” and
setup the backend in a poor fashion (especially when one is a perfectionist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here come TODOs (or you could call this “prioritization”, but TODOs sound more exciting). One can accept
that the backend setup could be improved, evaluate the relative benefits and if in doubt just leave a TODO
to do this a &lt;em&gt;bit&lt;/em&gt; later (if later ever comes). Basically, instead of saying “I did shitty job here”, one says
“yeap, this is not my best masterpiece, but, hey, I know how to improve it and if it ever becomes a problem,
I will do that”. If later does indeed come, one can reread the list of TODOs and reprioritize them based
on the new state of the world (new knowledge, demand). If later does not come, one has just saved plenty of
time not by doing that TODO. Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a funny fact, I have a comment with a TODO right above this line to add a link to a post about
importance of time. The post does not exist yet, but once it does I can search for all TODOs
and replace this one with a link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy productive and well-prioritized work!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="productivity" /><summary type="html">I’ve started using TODOs not only in my code. Now I find them very useful in this new context. E.g. they can be a hint to prioritize and to postpone less important tasks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jekyll post_url tag not working</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/jekyll-post-url-not-working" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jekyll post_url tag not working" /><published>2019-04-22T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-22T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/jekyll_post_url_not_working</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/jekyll-post-url-not-working">&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve had Jekyll complaining about &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_url&lt;/code&gt; not working due to a missing file,
but the file was there. This took me some time to figure out and I would like to 
share the issue (a non-obvious stray whitespace in the filename) as well as other ways this could have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-intro&quot;&gt;Brief intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of you may not know what Jekyll or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_url&lt;/code&gt; is.
Let me briefly explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; is a tool for creating static html blogs.
Basically you give Jekyll your blog “source code” and Jekyll “compiles” it 
into nicely looking static html blog, which you can then host somewhere (like GitHub pages).
As an example, this blog is done precisely like that - Jekyll + GitHub pages.
Can’t I write plain html myself without any fancy “compiling”? I can, but that’s cumbersome.
I would have to explicitly care about html when writing my posts and also manually add all the 
boilerplate to each page. Instead I just write a text of the post (i.e. the most exciting part of the process) using
special language called markdown and Jekyll does all the remaining boring stuff for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post_url-tag&quot;&gt;post_url tag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This markdown language has special commands, which one can use to make writing easier.
This can be something simple like making text &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;em&gt;italic&lt;/em&gt; or something more
complex like creating a table or adding a link somewhere. These commands are called tags.
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_url&lt;/code&gt; is a tag for adding a link to another post in your blog.
Obviously, I could just hardcode a direct link, but &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_url&lt;/code&gt; has couple advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complains if the link is broken&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;changes the link if something changes (e.g. domain name or post url change)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allows not to think about what the link will actually be and, thus, saves times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was happily writing 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-4-5&quot;&gt;a summary for lectures 4-5 of Robert Sapolsky’s course&lt;/a&gt; 
and I wanted to add a link to 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3&quot;&gt;the summary of lectures 1-3&lt;/a&gt;.
So I wrote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1-3 - Intro &amp;amp; Behavioral Evolution]({% post_url 2019-03-17-human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3  %})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of the file I just copied. To my sheer surprise this didn’t work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Liquid Exception: Could not find post 
&quot;2019-03-17-human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3&quot;
in tag 'post_url'. Make sure the post exists and the name is correct. 
in /blog/source/_posts/2019-03-26-human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_4_5.markdown
             ERROR: YOUR SITE COULD NOT BE BUILT:
                    ------------------------------------
                    Could not find post &quot;2019-03-17-human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3&quot; 
                    in tag 'post_url'. Make sure the post exists and the name is correct.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After googling for some time, I accidentally noticed that
the filename of the post I was trying to link to had a space right before the extension:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                                                    this little guy here
                                                                        \
2019-03-17-human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3 .markdown
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I copied the filename, the space was copied as well, but Jekyll ignored it, because that’s
how tags work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s funny is that Jekyll tags handle spaces inside the file name well, e.g. a file named&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;2019-03-17-human behavioral biology sapolsky course summary lectures_1_3.markdown
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;works perfectly fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-possible-causes&quot;&gt;Other possible causes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I spent time googling this, let’s collect here other possible causes, which could lead to this error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post is not published. This can happen for multiple reasons, e.g.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;explicit &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;published: false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;published date is from the future (including due to timezone)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;wrong folder (it should be in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the file is missing the date prefix or it is not separated from the rest of the filename with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The post belongs to a collection (use &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/liquid/tags/#link&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;link&lt;/code&gt; tag&lt;/a&gt; instead)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this does not solve your problem (or you are curious), you might look
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll/blob/master/lib/jekyll/tags/post_url.rb&quot;&gt;at the source code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy error free blogging!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="software" /><category term="troubleshooting" /><summary type="html">Recently I’ve had Jekyll complaining about post_url not working due to a missing file, but the file was there. This took me some time to figure out and I would like to share the issue (a non-obvious stray whitespace in the filename) as well as other ways this could have happened.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment overview: projects when FIRE’d</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment overview: projects when FIRE'd" /><published>2019-04-17T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-17T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_overview_projects_when_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire">&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what other people are going to do once they reach FIRE
(based on their responses to SavingNinja thought experiment #5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;my response to the previous thought experiment&lt;/a&gt;
I thought
that it would be cool to write an overview of all the responses. Perhaps
there are some patterns and peculiarities. This is my first attempt at this.
Obviously I have no clue where this will go, but I will just start reading
all the responses and then see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please find it in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uDRC1HheipxzNJWfaS-xhy2aj7NPqLD5ndsu_gRmGMg/preview&quot;&gt;this Google Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions--peculiarities-discovered&quot;&gt;Conclusions / peculiarities discovered&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were 2 ways to understand the problem statement. One is to describe
what you will do once you reach FIRE somewhen in future (i.e. after your normal
FIRE date). Another is to assume that you magically reach FIRE today (at least
3 responses did this).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I forgot about some stuff when was writing my post, like reading and languages.
However, this probably just illustrates that these are less important for me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One can use this overview to find like minded people,
e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/&quot;&gt;Sam @ A Simple Life&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thefireshrink.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;The FIRE Shrink&lt;/a&gt; would both
like to do more gardening once reaching FIRE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surprisingly, at least 4 responses do include part time work
and only one (&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-fire-now-what/amp/?__twitter_impression=true&quot;&gt;Marc @ Finance Your Fire&lt;/a&gt;) says 100% no to work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For some reason, learning French is very popular (at least 3 responses).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only one post was from an already retired author (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youngfiguy.com/retiring-from-retiring/&quot;&gt;Young FI Guy&lt;/a&gt;), I did enjoy their perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-notes&quot;&gt;My notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure why you would like to read them, but below all the notes I took
while reading the responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;savingninja&quot;&gt;SavingNinja&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-will-i-do-when-i-retire/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not fired yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do people want FI? They want time (like during their childhood).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always wanted to be a game developer, but went to mobile development for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dream: having a title on Steam (or Project Stadia).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a novel (an epic fantasy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating my own mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building (shed, sawmill, barn, stables, home)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-deed-a-bly&quot;&gt;in-deed-a-bly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/whats-next/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not fired yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes one project to be done in the nearest future
(next step for personal finance and budgeting software).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get an impression that the author assumed that “they have reached FI today,
what would they do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caveman--ditchthecave&quot;&gt;CaveMan @ DitchTheCave&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ditchthecave.com/when-i-grow-up/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes their experiences during Brexit vote day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to the gym multiple times a week (plus possibly some sword fighting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to bed whenever feeling like it, the same for waking up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning. French and Spanish. Joining a choir, relearning the piano.
Doing a masters degree in Shakespeare.
Doing this already, but giving more time and attention after FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteering (conservation works in the countryside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow travel. Spending weeks rather than days, being able to speak the language and culture immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying 1€ house in Italy. Training at Muay Thai camp in Thailand. Going to India or Bali to become a qualified yoga teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decompressing and understanding real priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fears. Absence of motivation to stay fit, family rejection, busy friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;A Way to Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumption: hitting FI today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably continuing working part time as a transition before the trip to Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Swahili and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport: training better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending more time with family (e.g. niece) and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength training 3 or 4 times a week instead of 2 now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing learning to do handstand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food - interesting restaurants and trying different cuisines from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing DIY projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the trip, probably quiting work.
Doing another trip, but to South America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a family (having a kid).
Full time parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More slow travel.
Spending more time with their partner.
Improve at sports.
Watch sporting events and music.
Play music.
Volunteer.
Building a house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cashflow-cop&quot;&gt;Cashflow Cop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cashflowcop.com/beyond-financial-independence-tracing-my-roots/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dream of not being tied to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of usual “stuff” they could do
(spending time with their wife and kids, traveling, reading, writing, learning to play piano, carpentry, photography, build our forever home, gym, hiking, learning French)
but there is no point to go into this.
Let’s rather consider a project, for which he will have more time and energy once FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes his childhood visit back to the country of origin 9 years after leaving for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is to return to the native country, but not for a holiday.
Understand history and culture. Know their relatives better.
Enable children to understand roots and mother-tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity work in their birth country - helping children to get out of poverty.
Probably introducing financial literacy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their wife is worried, that they will be too busy during FIRE.
Family is the highest priority, especially after FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merely-curious&quot;&gt;Merely curious&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No precise projects, since plenty of time before FIRE to achieve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming, data analysis, making websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing projects differently - sprinting (focusing on one project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects are defined very broadly (a finite chunk of work with a title).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derailing into how to collect ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing more in the blog, including posts requiring more time.
Art (juggling with humor, learning to draw, playing music and composing).
DIY - sewing. 
Cooking - more unusual and time consuming dishes, including for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggests to upscale current lifestyle in FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably stand up comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport (everyday)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubt whether answered Saving Ninja question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving short term examples (FIRE game, making rain-stick, FIRE calculator).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sam--a-simple-life&quot;&gt;Sam @ A Simple Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/2019/04/15/ninja-thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentioning MMM advice to see what you are doing on weekends these days
and to expand it to the full week once FI. MMM suggests to think in terms of
the following categories: outdoors, social, physical, generous and challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More time for garden. Growing vegetables all year round.
Selling some produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being much more active member of existing social groups in the village.
Posting more on Twitter and other social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking more. Cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More direct charity helping work (once a week or once a fortnight).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning French and Italian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubt whether answered Saving Ninja question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gentlemans-family-finances&quot;&gt;Gentleman’s Family Finances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gentlemansfamilyfinances.wordpress.com/2019/03/15/saving-ninja-thought-experient5-from-gff/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving advice to the readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoying art and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on longevity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travel, trying new things, have friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIY,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t ask me exactly what I want to do – I haven’t a clue!
But it will be fun whatever it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marc--finance-your-fire&quot;&gt;Marc @ Finance Your Fire&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-fire-now-what/amp/?__twitter_impression=true&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially: visiting coffee shops, practicing doing nothing, reading books, travel,
contemplating, donating time (volunteering), smiling to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could one get Olympic depression syndrome after FI?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pledging not to return to earning money after FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not going to work either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making music (electronic, DJ skills).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing and painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a book (a novel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t underestimate boredom.
Without it you can’t have its counterpart states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc is not scared of boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traveling more with his brother
(but not for the traveling sake, rather to relax, enjoy life, do nothing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fire-shrink&quot;&gt;The FIRE Shrink&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thefireshrink.wordpress.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-5-the-grid-what-grid/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participating first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably continuing working part time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already started projects.
Learning welding and sheet metal work.
Learning languages.
Overlanding.
More renovation projects in the UK.
Grow more food, keep more animals, experiment with brewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-fi-guy&quot;&gt;Young FI Guy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youngfiguy.com/retiring-from-retiring/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already retired.
“Retire from retiring”.
It is important to put up with shit in your life (like vaccinations).
Complete absence of nonsense makes very minor nonsense seem worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at part time jobs (1-2 days a week).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fretful-finance&quot;&gt;Fretful Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fretfulfinance.co.uk/what-are-my-plans-for-retirement/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the first time participating in “thought experiment”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plans to travel, relax, go to theater more and enjoy leisurely lunches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catch up on a lot of TV (series and movies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part time work (a metaphysical supply store).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteering for a charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rollercoaster and Theme Park blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Let’s see what other people are going to do once they reach FIRE (based on their responses to SavingNinja thought experiment #5).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment: projects after FIRE’d</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment: projects after FIRE'd" /><published>2019-04-14T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-14T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_projects_when_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire">&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have finally FIRE’d and now you are bored. Which projects would you?
This is the new shiny thought experiment by SavingNinja. And I have a lot to do, indeed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get to my response, let me introduce the concept, so that you understand all the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/category/thought-experiments/&quot;&gt;“Thought experiments”&lt;/a&gt;
is a project by SavingNinja. The idea is that some hypothetical situation is posted every 2 months
and participants must write down their thoughts without any preparation or major editing.
This should uncover their inner views and feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took part last time and the topic was “If You Lost Everything” (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;my response&lt;/a&gt;).
Without doubt it was much darker, but nevertheless interesting experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects-after-fire-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;“Projects after FIRE” thought experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment’s page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-will-i-do-when-i-retire&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
(it also contains links to other bloggers’ posts)
and the “problem” statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life is good. You finally did it! You pulled the plug on your day job after reaching financial independence. 
You never have to work for money ever again. But, you’re bored. You need something to do… You need a project! 
You grab a piece of paper and a pen and start thinking. Now that you’re financially free,
what projects do you want to complete? However ambitious, however small,
you now have the time to pursue anything that you like, what will you accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPD Apr 20, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;: FYI, I’ve prepared an &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;the overview of other participant responses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-reply&quot;&gt;My reply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-reading-the-new-experiment&quot;&gt;Before reading the new experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I am doing the writing in the morning to avoid any scary dreams during the night
(I didn’t have any last time, but just in case).
Let’s see what Savings Ninja prepared for us.
In his tweet he wrote that not everyone will be able to “partake” in this one, so I am curious why.
My guesses are that this could be related to gender (but this would be weird) or perhaps FIRE status
(e.g. a question to already FIRE’d people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-reading-the-new-experiment&quot;&gt;After reading the new experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny, this one seems pretty easy.
Basically what I want to do (focusing more on projects side) once I “retire”.
Obviously, I can’t tell precise projects, because I may accomplish some of them before FIRE,
however, I can definitely try to explain the general theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I have plenty of random ideas for projects already today.
These are mostly related to programming, data analysis and making websites.
I would definitely spend more time on these. However, currently almost all of them tend to have some 
money making part and this could go away once I FIRE. I can’t say that I explicitly filter my projects
to make money (I don’t drop ideas, which are unlikely to make money), but I get majority of ideas
like that anyway. So it is probably something inside me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I would probably try doing my projects differently once I FIRE. Currently there is always not enough time
and I can spend only small portion of my time on my projects. As a result they all take multiple weeks.
I would definitely try doing sprinting more (e.g. one week or even entire month for one project full time).
Not sure whether this would work perfectly, because I may then get bored, I like to have many ongoing things at once
and jump back and forth between projects, which interest me the most. However, trying won’t hurt me and having a reasonably
finished project in a reasonable time might feel pleasant too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably should explain more what I mean by projects. As I said, there is not much point
to talk about specific ideas, since I will probably address majority of items on my list
before FIRE. However, by projects I don’t mean something large. It can be pretty small.
I also don’t have any specific limitations for my projects. If it looks like a finite chunk of work
not related to other things I am doing and for which I can define an actionable target
and a title, this is already a project in my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have multiple lists in my life, because ideas (sometimes even good) come randomly,
so I try to make it as easy as possible to record them and whenever there is any urgent need,
I don’t have to come up with ideas, but just check my list. In some sense, I precache my ideas
for some topics to save time later when there is a need for that topic. I should write a post
about this (I can call it “Catching ideas”). Here are couple of ideas for the post, so that I
don’t forget: I suspect that the rate with which ideas appear is constant (assuming that you 
don’t have major lifestyle changes). Thus, one should optimize how easy it is to record them
and time for how long one collects them. It is similar to having a net and just catching some
fruits falling from a tree. It is important to write even “bad” ideas, the first impression may be wrong,
deleting an idea later is easy, you may learn something new later, which will change your perspective.
For me ideas usually come as a reaction to something I saw or read. Occasionally this can be a
combination of multiple sources. You actually saw above how I got an idea for the new post. 
Now I have added this to my internal list of ideas for blog posts. As you might have noticed I have
&lt;a href=&quot;/queue/&quot;&gt;a public list of ideas for blog posts&lt;/a&gt; 
as well. Actually I think I have too many blog post ideas and not
enough free time for all of them. As a result, I publish some of them just as ideas (I should definitely publish a new batch)
and then see which ones people visit the most. This helps me to prioritize. Having too many ideas 
(or in other words choosing which ones to pursue) is the next problem you have pretty quickly
once you develop a good idea “catching” approach. You could say that I could choose the ones I like the most,
the issue is that I like almost all of them :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I got derailed badly. Sorry, sorry. Regarding projects, even a larger blog post requiring 
some research is a project. It has an actionable goal - write a blog post about X - and a title e.g. “blogpost X”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I don’t think I would be able to work full-time on my projects, because it is pretty demanding work.
I can’t be sure, but I suspect that I won’t. E.g. currently on weekends I rarely have 8 hours of 
clean “project” work. I definitely won’t force myself, because then I will just hate all my projects and that’s
not my goal. As a result, I would likely do something else in addition to projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense I may now derail into general “life after FIRE” instead of “projects after FIRE”, but the term “project”
is very broad for me, so it is ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would definitely write more in my blog. Probably even somewhat weirder blog posts, which currently I filter out
because it feels like I am the only one interested, but then I could give a try to a couple. I think I would do
more blog posts requiring more background work. Currently, when I have not that much free time, spending entire week
on one blog post feels wasteful. Sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I would try to develop artistic part of me more. Currently, this feels like it is not worth it, because this is
mostly just for myself, but I definitely feel desire to try. One way would be to improve my juggling skills and then
start juggling for other people entertainment. I enjoy combination of juggling and humor very much and I think that
juggling provides a lot of opportunities (failing can be fun) and I would try to develop some small act of mine
involving juggling and trying to be funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also interested to learn how to draw. However, I am extremely bad at this right now and it feels like this will take
me eternity. So for now it is again not worth it, but when I have more free time I would try for sure. Another similar
area is music (playing music instruments and composing). Here I am probably even worse than with drawing. I would be
interested to moderately develop my skills. Perhaps I am just curious whether I just don’t have ability (which I don’t
believe, but this could be the first example) or just didn’t spend enough time practicing effectively. Currently both drawing
and music look like magic to me. Moving something from “magic” to normal life is a wonderful feeling, which I greatly enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I could do more DIY, e.g. currently sewing interests me as another medium of expression. Making a couple clothing items
looks interesting. Probably now you understand the name of my blog. When I see my lists of things I could do I occasionally
get a feeling that I may be even too curious sometimes. I hope that this does not harm me, but prioritization is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, also cooking. I enjoy cooking. I feel like the result is often multiple times better than the effort involved.
I also like to cook kinds of food, which normally everyone just buys and few people think how to cook it from scratch.
Sometimes cooking such food is extremely
easy, so I end up cooking it every now and then even though everyone else just buys it. One example is bread. After
some practice, baking bread becomes extremely simple and fast (in terms of active time spent - not waiting). After FIRE
I would cook unusual and more time consuming dishes more often. Perhaps even I would cook for other people. 
Currently I often cook something quick, because again - time. I extremely rarely cook for other people these days, but this is
a very important part of cooking in my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, ok, this is much longer text than I originally expected. It also didn’t go that easy at the beginning, but now
I completely missed how I wrote that much. I feel a bit weird, because Savings Ninja might have meant more
concrete project ideas here, but my concrete planning horizon is not that long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also why would I actually wait until FIRE to do something? It becomes apparent from the text above that I will be doing either
more of or just more intensively stuff I am doing right now. I think that this is how it should be, because you should live a good
life now and not somewhen in future. So if I had some super interesting project, I don’t think I would ever say “oh, cool, let’s wait
until FIRE to do it”. Ok, in some sense I am doing this for my artsy ideas (e.g. juggling with humor), but I juggle these
days as well. So again I will be doing something similar, but in a more time consuming manner after FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way stand-up comedy interests me as well, but probably not as much as stuff above since I remembered about it only
now. But I can imagine giving it a try. I would also experiment more with my life and try new things for sure .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would do sport more often (like everyday). This is hard to call a project, but I would love to do more sport
and currently (again) have not much time for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calm down my inner self, I can give you a couple of things I am working right now, which you can use as a basis to extrapolate
what I will be doing after FIRE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger projects:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I am making a FIRE game (it is in some sense a simulator of life with FIRE related bits). This is a very early stage, so
nothing to show yet. I will definitely make a post about it and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I saw an interesting African music instrument in a museum (known as rain-stick) and now I would like to reproduce it at home. 
The original one used some plant parts, which I am going to replace with pistachio shells. Currently I am at “collecting
pistachio shells” stage. Since I don’t eat pistachio that often (even though I avoid expensive 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/crazy-pistachio&quot;&gt;“crazy pistachio”&lt;/a&gt;
I saw recently, they are still pricey enough to be enjoyed moderately), this takes time. This is also an example of a project, which is interesting, but does not have that much of a practical benefit. I should make a blog post about this as well.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pages/calculator.html&quot;&gt;FIRE calculator&lt;/a&gt; which tells how saving or spending X euro affects your FIRE date
(i.e. how many days sooner or later it will be).
I made a rough prototype, but then I got busy with other projects and now this one waits for its golden time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for blog posts you can have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;/queue/&quot;&gt;my public post idea list&lt;/a&gt;.
Every view counts and affects what I will write about next, so
thank you a lot for your help! As I said, prioritization is hard and you help me enormously by somewhat implicitly expressing your interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh and thank you a lot, Savings Ninja, for making me think and even write about all of these. Everyone should do this occasionally,
even people not interested in FIRE. FIRE definitely promotes such thinking and makes “what I want to do with my life” question
much more burning, since you can get more freedom to actually do something with your life. I am pretty sure that my views will
somewhat change by the time I reach FIRE, I don’t think that this will be a major change, but definitely polishing of some details.
I also claim that answering this question can be a game changer for FIRE. I don’t have practical
experience, but I suspect that if you go into FIRE without clear understand what you enjoy and want to do, the free time you will
have will be like a punishment for you. It will be just boring, because there won’t be anything really interesting to do.
So it is better to start thinking about this earlier or even building some version of the life you want already before FIRE 
and then just upscaling this life. I hope that my approach (having a lot of time shortage now and just satisfying this demand
in FIRE) will work. What is also funny, that I have never noticed before that I implicitly cut so many activities due to time shortage.
Without an overview in one place, I noticed that I stopped myself sometimes from doing something time-consuming,
but this felt like rather rare incidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now extremely curious why not everyone may be able to partake in this experiment? Did Saving Ninja mean people who are not
trying to reach FIRE? But they probably won’t read his blog that much. Hm. Something is weird here. I should ask him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I forgot, after the last thought experiment, I thought that it would be cool to compare responses of other people (i.e. 
categorize them and make a table with an overview). This time I am going to do this. Unfortunately, I can’t do this now,
because there is nothing to read yet, so I will have to wait until people start publishing. So if you are curious
to get a general overview, come back in couple days (or perhaps a week to be sure), I will post a link here (and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; as well).
This must be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPD Apr 20, 2019&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;the overview of other participant responses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">Imagine that you have finally FIRE’d and now you are bored. Which projects would you? This is the new shiny thought experiment by SavingNinja. And I have a lot to do, indeed…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are you actually paying for?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/what-you-pay-for-or-second-class-apples" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are you actually paying for?" /><published>2019-04-12T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-12T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/what_you_pay_for_or_second_class_apples</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/what-you-pay-for-or-second-class-apples">&lt;p&gt;I’ve accidentally bought second class apples, which were not bad at all.
This made me think that I’ve been paying more for the first class apples without explicitly realizing this.
Let’s see why this is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a “weekly” discount for apples (1 euro for 2 kilos) in Edeka.
I discovered this in their “prospekt” (I wrote about supermarket discounts 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/weekly-discounts-in-german-supermarkets&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
However, once I bought them (actually 6 kilograms), I discovered that they were
“the second class”. Obviously, they did not look terribly bad, otherwise I would have
noticed this earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home I had a more careful look. Indeed there was something unusual with 90% of apples.
They had small damages or imperfections (at most 1 cm^2 in area, but most of them even much smaller than that).
In my life I definitely have seen and even eaten apples, which were in a much worse condition (I can clearly
remember an apple, which was in such a bad state, that I had to cut out almost half of it, but I ate the rest).
If you compare these second class apples to what I had before, they are then rather 99%
perfect. Here you basically cut out one very small piece and you get a perfectly fine apple.
Obviously, you probably can’t store them as long as the first class apples, but I bought only 6 kilograms
(not a tonne).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this uncovered an interesting issue. Such second class apples is a pretty rare guest in the supermarkets.
I have seen apples for “processing” (Verarbeitung) before, these had no damages, but mostly weird shape instead.
As far as I understood, they were meant for juicing. Obviously I also bought and ate them (and they were just fine).
Apart from that all apples I observed in supermarkets are the first class (i.e. ideal shape and state).
This is probably the first time I explicitly saw second class apples being sold. 
However, when I buy the first class apples, I actually pay premium for them to be the first class.
Since I haven’t thought about this before and never even had a choice, I was doing this implicitly.
And as I learned after buying the second class apples, paying this premium actually makes no sense to me.
I am as happy to consume second class apples as the first class. Basically, someone has made this decision
not to bring second class apples to the market that often and now all buyers are paying more for their
apples to be ideal (due to absence of choice), but without realizing and enjoying this. 
I consider this premium a waste of money from buyer perspective, since without having a reference point
(a concept which I learned during “Science of Wellbeing” course, my summary is 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
of second class apples, they can’t enjoy how the first class apples are better than the second.
For them, these are just normal average boring apples, not “not a second class” apples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am definitely curious which other premiums I’ve been paying for without realizing.
Unfortunately, identifying them is extremely tricky (unless you accidentally stumble on a product
without this premium feature like these second class apples), so I couldn’t come up with anything yet, but I am
now very vigilant. Perhaps you have encountered some other examples already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, happy conscious shopping!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="saving" /><category term="expenses" /><summary type="html">I’ve accidentally bought second class apples, which were not bad at all. This made me think that I’ve been paying more for the first class apples without explicitly realizing this. Let’s see why this is bad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 6)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 6)" /><published>2019-04-07T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-6">&lt;p&gt;Continuing watching and writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”.
Lecture 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-6-behavioral-genetics-i&quot;&gt;Lecture 6: Behavioral Genetics I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how the methodology for studying genetic component of behavior changed with time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;species&quot;&gt;Species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the field started, people assumed that &lt;del&gt;if a trait is universal in a species, it must be genetic&lt;/del&gt;.
This is very limited approach, which works for flies, but does not for more complex organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;families&quot;&gt;Families&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to consider families. The closer related two individuals are, the more genes they share.
If you have a behavioral trait that becomes more common the more closely related two individuals are,
it must have genetic component. However, the more related two individuals are, the more they share their environment
as well. Thus, with this approach one cannot distinguish genetic component of behavior from environmental influence.
This was a classic approach 70-80 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twins&quot;&gt;Twins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then let’s control for environment. Examine relatives in the same environment, but having different genes.
For example, one can consider identical (monozygotic) twins (sharing 100% genes) vs fraternal (dizygotic) twins
(sharing 50% genes). If they all live in the same environment and fraternal twins differ in some way, while
identical twins don’t - this must have genetic basis. Problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes fraternal twins have different sex -&amp;gt; let’s restrict to same sex fraternal twins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These twins are still treated differently as pairs. As a result, there is more environment differentiation for fraternal twins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identical twins can have one or two placentas (based on when the split happened - before or after 5 days since fertilization).
In one placenta case, they have same blood flow. With two placentas - there can be differences in blood flow.
As a result, in one placenta case they have much more similar environment.
For example, they are more likely to have similar IQ when having one placenta (when compared to two placenta case).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;different-sexes&quot;&gt;Different sexes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we have everything exactly the same except sex? Does not work either.
1 hour old boys have more arm movement than girls. However, moms already (from the first time 
they hold the child) treat them differently (holding for different duration of time and in different proximity to
their face).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sat-scores-and-gender-study&quot;&gt;SAT scores and gender study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One loud example of this is a study about 13 year old pupils’ SAT scores in math.
In particular, how they depend on sex. The results were that more boys had higher scores.
The paper was published in Nature and concluded that since they had the same lessons
(there was no school curriculum differentiation yet at that age), this must be a biological difference.
Press quickly called this “the math gene” and it was claimed that boys tended to have it more often.
However, there were differences in their environment. Other studies has shown that even in the first grade
a boy is more likely to be called when raising his hand for a math problem. Boys are also more likely
to be praised for correct answers in elementary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adoption-studies&quot;&gt;Adoption studies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at individuals raised in the same environment, but with different genes (adoption studies).
Consider someone who was adopted as a child. Who are they more likely to share a trait with -
biological parents or adoptive? In animals this can be done by cross-fostering,
i.e. switching newborns (or only 50% of them) across mothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biological-component-of-schizophrenia&quot;&gt;Biological component of schizophrenia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seymour Kety tried to test whether schizophrenia has biologic component
(The significance of genetic factors in the etiology of schizophrenia: Results from the national study of adoptees in Denmark, 1987). 
The study considered adopted individuals who had schizophrenia. Are they more likely to share this trait with their
biological or adoptive parents? Entire database of adoptees in Denmark was researched (Scandinavian countries
record a lot of data). In general population probability to develop schizophrenia is 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Probability to develop schizophrenia based on whether biological/adoptive parents have schizophrenia.
Numbers are from the course. The original source: Seymour Kety,
“The significance of genetic factors in the etiology of schizophrenia: Results from the national study of adoptees in Denmark”, 1987&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Biological parents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;!-- schizophrenia --&gt;
&lt;!-- no schizophrenia --&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;no schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;adoptive&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;no schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, having biological parent with schizophrenia increases probability, having both (biological and adoptive) - increases it even further
(non-additive synergisms). This was the first study to show heritable basis for a psychiatric disorder. This became a gold standard for
behavioral genetics studies. People started applying this approach to depression, alcoholism, criminal behavior. They observed similar
results. Problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the adoption does not happen immediately after the birth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prenatal environment shared with mom (this can be measured by difference of probability to share a trait with mom and dad).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paternity uncertainty - sometimes a person claiming to be a father is not a father.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adoptive family placements are not random (in some countries like US kids are matched across a lot of domains before adoption).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identical-twins-separated-at-birth&quot;&gt;Identical twins separated at birth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best approach so far is to consider identical twins separated at birth (they can be adopted in different households).
This uncovers 50% heritability of IQ, position on introvert-extrovert scale, degree of aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem: non-random placements. To mitigate, compare similarities between monozygotic and dizygotic twins (they both have non-random
placement), but this makes the sample size small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-at-non-learned-traits&quot;&gt;Looking at non-learned traits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we consider traits which happen without learning? 
E.g. smiling (even blind babies smile), beginning to babble at the same age
(even for deaf babies). Random observation - even fetuses smile during third trimester.
Prenatal effects can affect such traits too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;environment-begins-earlier-than-birth&quot;&gt;Environment begins earlier than birth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider some ways which can affect the child before birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharing-blood-with-mom&quot;&gt;Sharing blood with mom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hormones&quot;&gt;Hormones&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats have dozen of fetuses which have more similar blood environment with adjacent sibling fetuses.
As a result, the more male siblings a rat fetus has adjacent to them, the later it will reach puberty 
(local endocrine effects).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children born to younger or older mothers reach puberty later (due to lower estrogen levels in mothers).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress in mother propagates to fetus through stress hormones. In rats this causes smaller brain in adulthood,
thinner cortex, less learning abilities, more prone towards anxiety, stronger cognitive decline in old age.
This also decreases brain region responsible for dealing with stress hormones. As a result such offsprings 
have more stress hormones themselves. Their offsprings will be affected even more by this. This environmental effect
can be observed even in grand children (“the grandmother effect”). I.e. this is inheriting of a non-genetic trait
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;non-Mendelian inheritance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nutrients&quot;&gt;Nutrients.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_famine_of_1944%E2%80%9345&quot;&gt;Dutch Hunger Winter&lt;/a&gt; - almost immediate decline in available
food due to war in winter 1944.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Third trimester fetuses learn how many calories are available in the world during a specific time period.
They “study” nutritional profile. Then based on the results they can “choose” how their body should function through metabolic programming.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Individuals who were third trimester fetuses during Dutch Hunger Winter (i.e. built their nutritional profile during the famine) were
trying to store as much nutrients as possible and their kidneys tried to store more salt as well.
When normal diet returned (also almost immediate change) - affected individuals showed 19x increase in incidents of obesity,
diabetes, hypertension, metabolic syndrome. This is a very dramatic difference.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This did not happen to newborns or first trimester fetuses. This is now studied as part of “fetal origins of adult diseases”.
E.g. stress hormones during fetal life cause higher anxiety in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;People in Stalingrad didn’t get this effect, because there the food decrease was steady.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What happens when people affected get pregnant themselves? Their bodies take too much calories from blood,
and as a result fetus is born with mild version of “Dutch Hunger Winter” phenomenon (again non-Mendelian inheritance).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Females (including in humans) can consume different amounts of estrogen (E.g. vitoestrogen from plants).
When consumed more - fetus has consistent increase in estrogen dependent breast cancer in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In rats one can inject sucrose water with particular taste (fetuses drink amniotic fluid).
 After birth this taste will be preferred when given a choice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mom’s voice in humans. Fetuses hear a lot, but especially moms voice. 
When reading “Cat in hat” a lot out loud vs random collection of sentences (controlled for length and rhytmicity),
newborns prefer “Cat in hat” (they make sucking motion when they like something). When fathers read, this does not work
anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;. Environment does not being at birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember strains of rats with different levels of anxiety mentioned in previous lectures? There was “an adoption” study,
where fetuses were transfered during pregnancy. As a result, it was not a genetic trait, but a prenatal effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genetic-influence-from-mother&quot;&gt;Genetic influence from mother&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see more shared traits with mother than with father, these can be attributed to prenatal effects.
However, one gets more genetic influence from mother, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when father is not real father&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mitochondria has its own DNA. Sperm does not carry mitochondria, but only DNA. As a result, one inherits all their
mitochondria DNA from mother.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imprinted genes - work differently based on whom they come from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sperm does not have transcription factors. All transcription factors in a fertilized egg are from mother.
Imagine there is a transcription factor A and it is needed to produce more of A and to activate gene X.
If due to an environmental change, A stops being produced, there will be no A in the egg and
this will disable X for offsprings forever (i.e. genes are inherited, but won’t be expressed due to acquired trait in mother - lamarckian traits).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indirect-genetic-effects&quot;&gt;Indirect genetic effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There can also be indirect genetic effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider 50% heritability of your position on introvert-extrovert scale.
This conclusion held through all the concerns above.
However, height and appearance are highly inheritable.
Taller people are treated better and considered more attractive.
People treated more positively during childhood become more extroverted. Most of introvert-extrovert heritability
is mediated by heritability of physical traits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heritability of rank in turkeys - actually it is due to the color of their feathers, which is inherited.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicks are able to peck for grabs very early. However, newborn chicks have heritable tendency to find their toes very
interesting, as a result they peck at their toes and learn to do proper pecking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;70% heritability of political party affiliation in US. Mediating variable - how people feel about ambiguity. Conservatives
are more ambiguity averse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats and mouse strains with various levels of aggression. Mediation: aggressive strains have lower threshold for pain sensitivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;epigenetic-effects&quot;&gt;Epigenetic effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DNA cover can block transcription factors from reaching DNA permanently.
This happened in Dutch Hunger Winter people. 
Another example: pet newborn rat for 3 min/day for 2 weeks after it is born -&amp;gt; larger brain, better learning.
Pet it for 1.5 hours/day instead -&amp;gt; smaller brain, shorter life expectancy.
It is interesting what counts as stimulation (3 min) vs stress (1.5 hours). However, this actually changes mother behavior.
3 min petting causes mom to get excited and to lick and groom the kid more. 1.5 hours causes ignorance for long period of time.
Petting itself does not matter, but only mother reaction.
Licking and grooming by mother causes larger brain and all other possible outcomes mentioned above. 
This can have multi-generational effect - licked and groomed daughters will lick and groom their kids more (
again non-Mendelian inheritance). This changes access of transcription factors, which are related to activating genes for making receptors for
stress hormones. It is also reversible. Cross-fostering after non-grooming mom improves kids state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Continuing watching and writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”. Lecture 6.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“So Good They Can’t Ignore You” - impression and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-so-good-they-cannot-ignore-you" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;So Good They Can't Ignore You&quot; - impression and summary" /><published>2019-04-02T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-02T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/book_summary_so_good_they_cannot_ignore_you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-so-good-they-cannot-ignore-you">&lt;p&gt;I’ve read “So Good They Can’t Ignore You” by Cal Newport.
Here is my impression (pretty mixed and rather on the negative side) and summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book felt weird and very wordy. Basically the author developed their own theory about what makes one to like their job
and how to reach this state. These ideas seemed reasonable and somewhat obvious. However, there was no attempt to prove anything
any only ~10 anecdotes instead, which do illustrate the point, but does not prove it. One could easily ignore all the anecdotes.
Also closer to the end the book started listing somewhat random advice from other books. Overall, the content could have been compressed 10-20x without losing much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 2/5 (this wasn’t a complete waste of time, but quite wasteful, I can’t recommend this book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;follow-your-passion-is-harmful&quot;&gt;“Follow your passion” is harmful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are used to hear “follow your passion” advice from everywhere as a way to choose your career.
However, this is wrong. Even Steve Jobs said the same advice, but his own story was different.
If he had followed his passion, there would have been no Apple. Do what Steve Jobs did, not what he 
said to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Follow your passion” has been started with a book “What Color is Your Parachute?” by Bolles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion advice is dangerous, because it makes you feel that there is a perfect job and that
you will immediately recognize it. This leads to excessive career hoping and unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-job&quot;&gt;Great job&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self Determination Theory explains intrinsic work motivation needs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomy - control over your day and feeling that your actions are important&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Competence - feeling that you are good at what you are doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relatedness - feeling connection to other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a great work requires creativity, impact and control. 
Jobs with these features are rare and valuable. As a result, due to supply &amp;amp; demand
you have to provide something rare and valuable in return (e.g. good skills).
The author calls such skills “career capital”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mindsets-passion-vs-craftsmanship&quot;&gt;Mindsets: passion vs craftsmanship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to passion mindset (focusing on what a job offers you), there is craftsmanship mindset
(focusing on what you produce).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passion mindset - answering “do I really love this?” and “what do I like?” is nearly impossible and leads to unhappiness.
Also this forces you to focus on what you don’t like, but all entry level jobs are not perfect (low autonomy and few challenges).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion mindset claims that you need only courage to start your dream job, which will have creativity, impact and autonomy.
Craftsmanship mindset requires you to build your skills first (“to be come so good they can’t ignore you”) to earn
creativity, impact and autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some jobs are just not good for craftsmanship mindset. The job is like that if it has any of these criteria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one cannot build skill in it to distinguish themselves from others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one finds the results they produce useless or even harmful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one is forced to work with people they don’t like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deliberate-practice&quot;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are some guitar players not that good, while others are much better even after the same amount of practice?
They’ve practiced differently. If you don’t get out of your comfort level during practice, you won’t develop your
skill that well. Instead you should do deliberate practice - focus on what you do badly and use immediate feedback
to correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps to do deliberate practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the career capital market you are in - winner-takes-all or an auction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Winner-takes-all - only one skill matters and everyone competes for it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Auction - many skills are important, everyone can propose a combination of skills.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify which career capital you need to pursue (i.e. which skill or skills).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define “good”, i.e. your feedback criteria and clear goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Stretch”. Practice outside of your comfort zone and accept feedback even if it
disagrees with your feelings. You may think that what you did is perfect, but you may
be not the one deciding in the end and then your opinion won’t matter at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be patient - improving takes time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use open gates - some opportunities which you happened to have e.g. by chance - to gain
career capital much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaining-control-at-work&quot;&gt;Gaining control at work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving people control over what and how they do increases their happiness, satisfactions and
fulfillment. Once you have career capital you can use it to gain control in your work.
Gaining control before you have enough career capital is dangerous. I.e. you can start doing
what you really want, but no one will find it valuable (e.g. a startup, which no one finds
interesting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have enough career capital to pursue more control (i.e. become valuable enough),
your current employer will try to prevent you from gaining this control, because
this has negative impact for them (less control of you, possibility to lose you). They would
rather use your career capital further and on the old terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, courage is important to face this resistance. However, you should be valuable enough as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-law-of-financial-viability&quot;&gt;The Law of Financial Viability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to identify whether you have enough career capital to go for more control?
If you have an idea how to gain more control, seek evidence whether people are willing to pay you
for it. If yes, proceed. Otherwise move on.
“Willing to pay” may have different meaning, e.g. they actually pay you or you get a loan or you get hired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Do what people are willing to pay for” Derek Sivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless people are ready to pay you for an idea, it is not an idea you should go after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building career on some mission can make it more fulfilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Adjacent possible” - a set of discoveries that are possible to make from the current state of science.
E.g. discovering oxygen required precise weight scales and thinking about air as something not void.
These 2 inventions moved “oxygen discovery” into “adjacent possible”. This concept is considered 
in greater detail in “Where Good Ideas Come From” by Steven Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore “adjacent possible” one has to reach the cutting edge. Finding a career mission is like
a scientific breakthrough. Reaching the cutting edge is equivalent to building career capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of going for one large bold idea, one should do small incremental “little bets”, which will
mostly fail and only sometimes succeed. This way one can gather feedback. Each bet should take 
approximately 2 months and be either successful or fail. Each bet should follow your mission idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Career capital helps to identify a good mission, little bets help to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;law-of-remarkability&quot;&gt;Law of remarkability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mission driven projects need to be remarkable. People who encounter them should want to
“remark” about it, i.e. share. Projects should also be launched in a venue which 
supports such remarks (i.e. allows and promotes sharing). “Purple Cow” by Seth Godin
talks about this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book" /><category term="summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I’ve read “So Good They Can’t Ignore You” by Cal Newport. Here is my impression (pretty mixed and rather on the negative side) and summary.</summary></entry></feed>