<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-11-23T12:09:28+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology" /><published>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_9_ethology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 9, ethology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethology is a field, which studies behavior under the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will need to study the behavior in as many environments as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these environments must be as natural as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will have to translate a language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, ethology is a process of interviewing animal in its own language,
i.e. an expansion of “if you want to understand behavior, get your animal out of the lab”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the historical context, let’s have a look at the history of psychology.
At first it was a branch of philosophy and wasn’t about numbers (i.e. not a science in the modern terms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then behavioralism appeared, which treated an organism as a black box and the goal was to measure as much as possible.
The field had number of strong beliefs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extreme environmentalism - impact of environment is very high.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement theory - when I can control positive/negative reinforcement, I can form any behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Universality across species. Everything is black box, thus, it does not matter whether it is a human child,
a puppy or an elephant. As a result, the studies used mostly rats and pigeons for practical reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then meanwhile in Britain people started to collect butterflies as a hobby. The goal was to just observe
variability. Then ethology emerged, which was like butterfly collection, but for behaviors. 
There were 3 main figures in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nikolaas Tinbergen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Konrad Lorenz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karl von Frisch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field was about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gene-environment interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;examples of animals acquiring new (often unexpected) behaviors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;every species solving its own evolutionary challenges in its own way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: in 1960s it was discovered that, if a lab rat was placed in a richer environment (cage with toys), 
its cortex got thicker. As a result, people started to assume reversibility of early brain damage using
richer environments. However, then it was observed that a simple wild rat had very thick cortex, which was
unreachable using any artificially rich environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;Approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethologists look for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the behavior was - fixed action pattern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what triggered it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what happens in the head of the animal, when it is triggered by the stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the adaptive value of this behavior is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fixed-action-pattern&quot;&gt;Fixed action pattern&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed action pattern - a sequence of actions, which animals don’t have to learn, but they have to improve it.
Experience can also change context of fixed action patterns.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a squirrel raised in a cage on a liquid diet still can crack a nut without any preparation. It will get even better at it practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“visual cliff” = baby animals scared to sit on glass over a height (floating = falling). Baby sloths are not scared of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a male monkey, which was raised in isolation and have never seen another monkey. Show him a video of a face of huge scary
monkey of the same species with threating display. He will freak out and do subordinate gesture. Experience: who to do the subordinate
gesture to, i.e. not kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vervet monkeys have different alarm calls for eagle, snake and leopard. As kids they know how to do the call, but may not know when to do it
(i.e. mix up them). Adults don’t trust young monkey calls, but double check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In humans:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Infants smiling as well as fetuses and blind babies. Learning: who to smile to.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nursing. Learning: increase efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Detecting anger, fear, disgust in others; Learning: social context (i.e. when the meaning is not obvious).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adaptive-value&quot;&gt;Adaptive value&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand adaptive value, they did experiments. E.g. Tinbergen experimented with a bird turning egg shells non-white side up
after its chick hatching. Tinbergen turned them back. As a result, predators could detect the nest better. Frisch looked into bee
dancing. Bees communicate info about food sources (direction, how far, how much). They do this by dancing on the floor in patterns
shaped as “8”. Axes of “8” define the direction. The duration of the dance - distance. The more frantic the dance is (more back
wiggling), the more exciting the food source is. E.g. Frisch rotated a bee hive after the dance and all bees went in wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stimulus&quot;&gt;Stimulus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are number of techniques to study stimulus (so-called releasing stimulus in the field). One can assume what the stimulus is and then
subtract it, then put it back (replacement), then substitute (replace with something else), then superstimulate (exaggerate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently people started to use robotic animals (e.g. bees or cockroaches) for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female deer ovulate when they hear male mating calls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats can be tickled on their ribcage and they giggle in ultrasonic
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=78PfGQbL-g0&quot;&gt;youtube&lt;/a&gt;). Other rats come over to check “the party”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female ovulation in human leads to higher voices. Males can subliminally detect this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was research (&lt;em&gt;Stimuli eliciting sexual behavior&lt;/em&gt; by Schein, M.W., &amp;amp; E.B. Hale, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/how-to-seduce-a-turkey-the-bizarre-poultry-sex-experiments-of-the-1960s&quot;&gt;atlasobscura&lt;/a&gt;) on what makes a female turkey attractive to a male turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olfactory information in people. People can subliminally
(amygdala activation) distinguish scared people sweat from normal exercise sweat.
After “scary” sweat, they tended to interpret ambiguous faces as more frightened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electric fish - males jam each other frequency when courting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vibration in insects - animals have vibration detectors in their feet. They can communicate this way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrogate mom monkeys - a monkey is given a choice of two fake moms - one made with cloth (warm) and one
made out of wire, but with milk. Behaviorists claimed that mom attraction is due to milk. However, animals choose cloth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baby animals look cute (large eyes, ears) even across species. Early illustrators of Disney studied this
(e.g. evolution of Micky Mouse, youtube: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vDiykIUwSo&quot;&gt;with commentary&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3hWXfrANSd8&quot;&gt;without&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.wwu.edu/rcm/mickey.pdf&quot;&gt;“A biological homage to Mickey Mouse” by S. Gould&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neuroethology&quot;&gt;Neuroethology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it was hard to study how stimulus is processed in the brain. Currently there is neuroethology. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neurobiology of bird songs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Lordosis” reflex in female hamsters. When having a pressure on their back, they arch their back to make mating easier.
Only works when the hamster is ovulating. Specific neurons responsible for this are known, even which ones of them 
are affected by estrogen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding electrodes to the brain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sapolsky studied baboons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of learning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female childcare competence in female monkeys is not a strong instinct. Evidence: later offsprings have higher likelihood to 
survive. If she has a sister with a baby, her first child is more likely to survive (observed sister doing the care). The same
when having a niece or a nephew.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meerkats eat scorpions. Mom has to teach her kids. First, she brings a dead one, baby learns how to eat it.
Then mom brings alive scorpion, but she bites off the stinger. Kid has to tackle this one. Finally, she brings 
a normal scorpion. Thus, incremental learning steps (with progressing difficulty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animals make tools (e.g. apes). Chimps use sticks to get termites. One learns by observing others.
Daughters learn better (much more attentive). The larger the social group is, the earlier in life kids learn to use tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One trial learning (imprint after one exposure) - after hatching bird chicks imprint on something big around to bond for mom.
In this case, there is no place for trial and error.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared learning, e.g. Sauce-Bearnaise Syndrome. One ate the sauce and then went to opera. They had stomach pain.
The next time they were to taste the sauce, they had repulsion (unpleasant smell). The pain was not attributed to opera
(even though it occurred during opera), but to the sauce, since there is a prepared learning of food -&amp;gt; stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bees learn smell better than color or shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humans are not inherently scared of spiders and snakes, but have prepared learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cognitive-ethology&quot;&gt;Cognitive ethology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Griffin (random fact: discovered echolocation in bats) wrote “On awareness in animals”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;self-awareness&quot;&gt;Self awareness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can test for self awareness. E.g. dogs are not self aware.
Take a chimp, anesthetize, put a black dot on its forehead with a marker. When looking into the mirror,
chimps are much more likely to start scratching their head where the dot is. Elephants pass this test too.
Marmoset monkeys don’t. They don’t look into eyes normally. Thus, when the dot is on their neck, they
start noticing it too. An example of “interviewing” an animal in its own language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theory-of-mind&quot;&gt;Theory of mind&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing that other individuals can have different information than you. Humans start understanding this at the age of
4-5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test, one can tell a child a story about another child X, who has a doll called Sally. X goes to school.
Mom washes Sally and puts it into a different place. When X comes back, where would it look for Sally?
With the theory of mind the child will say “the old place” (since X does not know that they doll has been moved).
Without the theory of mind - “the new place” (since the child knows where the doll is and can’t imagine X having
different info).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chimps have this too. E.g. you can have two chimps (one high ranking, one low ranking) and a banana (all divided by dividers). 
If there is a glass divider between high ranking and banana, low ranking won’t try to get the banana (he knows that high
ranking knows). When you swap high ranking chimp with a different high ranking one, low ranking will go for the banana, 
because he understand that the new high ranking chimp does not know about banana. However, they can do this only in
competitive setting (no cooperation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corvus have this too. If they see someone observing them when they hide food, they won’t proceed with hiding the food.
I.e. they understand that other birds will know about the food hidden here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can distinguish intentional action from unintentional. In chimps - they react more dramatically to a person throwing
away their food vs. tripping over it. Dogs know the difference between an intentional kick and someone tripped over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can plan for the future. E.g. take corvus living in a cage with 2 areas. In each of the areas, there is a place
where researchers put food every other day. In one of them, they put more. Corvus starts bringing food from this place to another one for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flexible-cognitive-strategies&quot;&gt;Flexible cognitive strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bees will distrust implausible dances. E.g. researchers put food in the middle of the lake. A bee tells others about this. Others
don’t do anything, because there can’t be food in the middle of the lake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerosity.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teach chimp to detect series of 3 objects, e.g. “ABC” and “HIJ”. When they see them, they should pull the lever and
  they will get food. When shown “HI&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;”, they make less mistakes than when shown “H&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;J”. In the former case, the third object
  was replaced with the first. In the latter - second with second. I.e. chimp detects that this object is “second”, but forgets
  which triplet it belongs too.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take a chimp troop. Record foreign male chimp vocalizations. Play one foreign male chimp vocalization in the bush. The troop will
  investigate. Play vocalizations of the same number or more other chimps than in the troop, the troop will know that they are outnumbered and
  silently run away. They understand that 4 is more than 3.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In fish. Fish C sees A defeating B and then B defeats C. C gives subordinate gesture to A (transitivity).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 9, ethology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">All (my) advice is awful!</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/all-advice-is-awful" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All (my) advice is awful!" /><published>2019-11-19T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/all_advice_is_awful</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/all-advice-is-awful">&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to advice others to do something, but it is very hard to be sure that this will actually help them.
However, not all understand this or choose to phrase their advice accordingly. I.e. instead of “here is a way to X”,
it actually should be “this is how I did X”. Thus, very often non-objective advice is just a description of what helped
the author, which is also true for some of my posts.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please treat this as a mega disclaimer to all my future and past posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do try to self-improve a lot and it seems that I am not alone in this desire. There are plenty of blogs,
sites and videos on self-improvement with various advice. This can be about better productivity, self-confidence,
startups, health, exercise. It is a very good way to create value for people and improve people’s lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subjectivity&quot;&gt;Subjectivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, often such advice is very subjective. People just share what they do and how this helps them.
Someone wakes up at 4am every day and starts by making their bed. This helps them to be extremely productive.
As a result, they tell others “hey, do you want to be more productive? Just wake up at 4 am and make your
bed everyday”. Obviously, this does not mean that this will have positive effect (or any) on you. 
The author of the advice has their own life with their own weak and strong areas.
You have your own, which may be completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have vitamin C deficiency (hypothetical example) and this has physical negative consequences, but you
don’t know the reason. You somehow miraculously start taking vitamin C supplements and this fixes the deficiency.
The deficiency is now gone. Then you can advise others - do you want to get rid of such negative consequences? Take
vitamin C supplements. However, let’s imagine that there is some other way to get similar negative consequences. Thus, one
can have perfect level of vitamin C, but still have same negative consequences (hypothetical example). Thus, your advice won’t help them. The situation
above with 4am and making one’s bed is exactly the same. Perhaps the author was missing routine and was too dynamic and
that’s why waking up at 4am helps them. Perhaps you are over attached to your routine and adding more to it will even harm you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eye-opening-examples&quot;&gt;Eye opening examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effect is easy to observe with advice which had an enormous effect on you, but didn’t work for others.
E.g. I do consider “The science of Wellbeing” course on Coursera
(my summaries: 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;full&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary&quot;&gt;brief&lt;/a&gt;)
 to be a life changing as well as “Search Inside Yourself”
book (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/book-summary-search-inside-yourself&quot;&gt;my summary&lt;/a&gt;). However, I met people who
took the course and read the book and were “meh”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, context of the advice matters a lot. There are thousands of dimensions in life and when you do something,
each of these act as an input condition. There are obvious examples of this. Let’s say you’ve been studying positive
psychology for years. Then “The science of Wellbeing” won’t bring you anything new. Even regarding this post right now, you
can think that this is obvious for everyone and it is weird that I am talking so much about this. However, this was
not that obvious for me and I even decided to write about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;asymmetry&quot;&gt;Asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it is very easy to give such subjective advice (in other words describe what you did
and which effect it presumably had on you). However, identifying all input conditions as well as even estimating
whether this could help someone else is extremely hard. For some input conditions, it may be even hard to 
understand that they can vary. E.g. you always wake up energized. It may look like all humans are like that.
Or you can be extremely organized and require structure in your life and you implicitly assume that that how
all people live. It is like fish living in water. If you never experience anything else (meeting a people, who
don’t have this quality), it is hard or impossible to even observe your “water”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estimation of usefulness for others is a nightmare. Unless you are a researcher with a group of test subjects
with double blind testing, you have very little tooling for this. In your own life, you almost always have sample size of
1 (just you yourself). You can’t go back in time and redo the intervention differently (or even not do the intervention
to simulate a control group). Basically, you just have one trial and then you have to derive everything you have from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;incentives&quot;&gt;Incentives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, people are incentivized to increase perceived value of their advice. Very often authors of the advice
also share various positive details about their life, e.g. making a million in couple years, being financially independent,
making a successful startup, feeling very happy for many years. I am not saying that this is done maliciously, however,
there is clearly an incentive to create an appearance that this positive quality was caused by the advice. At the same time
the author is not incentivized to point out weaknesses of their advice. E.g. the sample size of 1. If you want to attract
attention, you will rather say “hey, this always works, 100% credibility and reliability”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is somewhat peculiar that I do point this weakness in my blog right now. Basically, I am saying here that you should treat my advice carefully
and always keep in mind that even if it works for me, it does not mean that it will work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix&quot;&gt;Fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If authors are not the ones to fix this, you will have to take this into account. When you see someone saying “do X and 
you will get Y like I did”, always remind yourself that you may have different context. Even advice which worked for you
before, may not work anymore. I especially observe this with startups. Usually there is someone who made an extraordinary
exit and then they often start advising others. Usually they just tell their story and what they perceive as key factors
to their success. Often they actually don’t know themselves why it worked out. Remember, sample size of 1. Thus, they already
estimate. At the same time, the market is very dynamic. The situation they had is now gone. That demand is fulfilled by them. The world is
different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I don’t have any concrete example of a serial startup founder. Based on my observations a person with an amazing exit just tells
others about the exit, but can’t reliably reproduce their success again. Obviously, their context is now different. E.g. they may not
have financial pressure they had before. However, this somewhat contradicts credibility of their advice. If their advice was that sound,
they would be able to use it themselves to create a new startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can try the advice out. Alternatively you can try to generalize yourself based on multiple sources. E.g. if there are
100 different people telling that waking up at 4am improves their productivity and they are diverse enough (e.g. not all are 
military folks), you may conclude that this is reasonably general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix-as-an-author&quot;&gt;Fix as an author&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an author, I do feel somewhat weird about writing such subjective advice. One way to improve the situation is to always
mention that you didn’t do extensive research, this just worked for you and your own unique conditions. Another way is to avoid
writing about subjective topics. Instead do e.g. objective calculations and simulations. I personally write about subjective
advice if its impact on my life was enormous (like the course and the book above). In some sense, we can estimate expected
effect by multiplying probability of having effect with its magnitude. If magnitude is huge for me, the expected effect on
others is also larger (even if probability is generally low).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy self-improvement &amp;amp; mental adjusting of subjective advice value!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is very easy to advice others to do something, but it is very hard to be sure that this will actually help them. However, not all understand this or choose to phrase their advice accordingly. I.e. instead of “here is a way to X”, it actually should be “this is how I did X”. Thus, very often non-objective advice is just a description of what helped the author, which is also true for some of my posts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How technology affects our lives - a story about a delayed sms</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-technology-affects-our-lives-or-story-about-delayed-sms" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How technology affects our lives - a story about a delayed sms" /><published>2019-11-09T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-09T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_technology_affects_our_lives_or_story_about_delayed_sms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-technology-affects-our-lives-or-story-about-delayed-sms">&lt;p&gt;Today I stumbled upon a tweet about an SMS which was sent before Valentine’s day, but was delivered only recently
(i.e. 9 months later). This made me think about the impact of technology on our lives. Let’s look more into what 
has happened and my thoughts as well as speculations about the reasons for such a delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tweet&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danandelin/status/1192510312634695680&quot;&gt;The tweet&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_technology_affects_our_lives_or_story_about_delayed_sms/tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tweet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-context&quot;&gt;More context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, I noticed in the thread that there are journalists eager to reach the author
and wondering whether the two are going to reconnect. There were also plenty of news articles
(e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/11/7/20953422/text-messages-delayed-received-overnight-valentines-day-delay&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popularmechanics.com/technology/a29726341/texts-delayed-random/&quot;&gt;popularmechanics.com&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were multiple tweets from other people about similarly delayed SMS. Someone complained about their boss receiving an SMS
from them at 4am. Some claimed that they didn’t send these messages at all (it is easy to forget an SMS after 9 months).
For some this was a sad experience, since they received a message from people, who died in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/11/7/20953422/text-messages-delayed-received-overnight-valentines-day-delay&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt; seems
to provide the most technical details:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A company named Syniverse, which provides networking services, later took blame for the messages being delayed.
Syniverse said a single server was at fault: that server failed on February 14th, trapping messages waiting to be
sent out; the server was only brought back online on November 7th. When that happened, all of the messages were finally delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Syniverse initially published a note saying that 168,149 delayed messages were sent. A spokesperson later told The
Verge that the company is “still assessing the scope and volume of messages impacted by this server disruption.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that 168k messages is an underestimation. It is hard for me to believe that 168k would create such a public outcry.
On the other hand, it is super easy to write something on twitter or reddit these days, so perhaps this number was enough…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-has-happened-on-their-side&quot;&gt;What has happened on their side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just my speculations. I don’t work in communications, so I have no clue how their system is setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that there was some server responsible for delivering such messages and around 14th of February it
stopped working for some reason. It likely had some cache (presumably even on-disk), because dropping SMS messages
seems bad. Perhaps it was one machine out of many (e.g. geographically distributed). Then I can see two possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No one noticed and the server just was off all this time;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Someone noticed and restarted the server, but there was a bug in how the cache was processed
(i.e. the cache was just ignored for long time and recently someone fixed this bug).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like option 1 more. It also seems to agree with the quote in The Verge. 
I speculate that other servers in the system just overtook the work this server had to do, that’s why no one noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then around 7th of November someone noticed this server being offline. 
Here I can again see 2 options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They think “oh, wth, this is bad” and investigate;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They think “oh, this one is offline, let’s restart it, not a big deal”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of (1), they might have discovered 168k message undelivered and then had a discussion with their manager
or even the manager of their manager about what to do. However, I prefer option 2 here. I.e. this cache was delivered unintentionally.
Otherwise I don’t think they would go for delivering these messages during the night and without any explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, these are just pure speculations. Bug happens, this one was not the worst.
Dropping the messages completely would probably be less fun (but on the other hand after 9 months their value is of doubt).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-can-be-malicious&quot;&gt;This can be malicious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had a thought that perhaps there is some entity, which intercepts all my communication in all channels
(SMS, email, messengers) and filters it. Perhaps that’s why people, who I write to, sometimes don’t reply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it is very easy to shoo such a thought away by just reminding myself that there is no point in doing
that to me and it is quite hard in terms of resources and tricky to automate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it is entertaining to imagine such a super entity controlling everyone’s communication. 
Basically it would decide who can say what and to whom. Like a god-like AI orchestrating our lives to maximize our happiness
(or just because it can).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again this is more like a conspiracy theory. I am pretty sure that if that was the case, someone would have noticed. 
E.g. they send a message to someone close by and just verify physically that it is not delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more realistic case would be parents doing this to their child. Parents definitely have preferences who their child
should hand out with. Usually with people who parents like more. So it would be convenient for parents to create an
illusion that other less desirable people are not even interested to communicate with their child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again practically pretty hard - one still communicates directly quite a lot, but in a fully digital world (i.e. no physical
communication at all) - easy peasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effect-of-technology-on-our-lives&quot;&gt;Effect of technology on our lives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peculiar to think more about the original tweet I stumbled upon. There was a romantic relationship involved (probably 
at a very early stage) and due to this missing SMS, it didn’t go further. In some sense, this delayed SMS had a substantial impact
on the author’s life. While I doubt that the two are ideal match for each other (just using a probabilistic argument - probability of that is low), the author would still spend time with the other person and might have attempted to build a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think that technology always affects our lives in multiplicative ways. I.e. if I do something, technology may help
me to do this easier, cheaper, more conveniently. Somehow I didn’t think that technology could do something on my behalf (or 
it could another human using technology) or negate effect of my action completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fallacy&quot;&gt;Fallacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is very easy to start falling into a fallacy, which reminds me of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Butterfly_effect&quot;&gt;Butterfly effect&lt;/a&gt;. 
In some sense one could start saying that technology actually changes our life extremely.
Because of computer, I sit more often than I would otherwise, my profession is based on IT.
I spent numerous hours in Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claim that this is a fallacy because you can say this about anything in your life.
Basically, you can consider almost any effect or detail in your life as your own
“flapping of butterfy wings”. Your life might have been very different otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that one can’t just separate an impact of an individual event. The life is too interconnected these days
and it has too many dimensions. This impact of something depends a lot on initial conditions.
E.g. the same startup idea may work for someone who has enough resources or experience 
(or just lives in the more appropriate country).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also consider such deep thinking about alternatives counterproductive. Basically one can
spend plenty of time thinking what could have been different, but this does not bring any value.
It is just a form of entertainment and dreaming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technology-is-still-good&quot;&gt;Technology is still good&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the author of the tweet ended up in this peculiar situation, I still think 
that technology is good and the author would agree with this as well. Funnily enough, for them
this story might have even a net-positive effect due to journalists’ interest. This also has
potential to boost the relationship with that other person (at least it is a funny story
to tell other people about how you met). But even if this was negative, e.g. this message
was completely lost, I would prefer losing this SMS to not having SMS at all (e.g.
using paper mail or not being able to communicate via long distance at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to stop appreciating the positive impact of technology on one’s life,
especially since one is so deeply ingrained in it that they never see any alternative. But it 
is enormous. I think I could be naming examples for a very long time. I am definitely
grateful for medicine (this extends life and its quality a lot), Internet and knowledge 
available there (a way to multiply your impact, partial equalization of opportunities independent
of your initial conditions like wealth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy living in this bizarre world!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Today I stumbled upon a tweet about an SMS which was sent before Valentine’s day, but was delivered only recently (i.e. 9 months later). This made me think about the impact of technology on our lives. Let’s look more into what has happened and my thoughts as well as speculations about the reasons for such a delay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Github Pages refused to refresh my Jekyll blog</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/github-pages-not-refreshing-my-jekyll-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Github Pages refused to refresh my Jekyll blog" /><published>2019-11-05T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-05T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/github_pages_not_refreshing_my_jekyll_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/github-pages-not-refreshing-my-jekyll-blog">&lt;p&gt;Recently I was trying to publish a post (namely
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-8-jobs-in-2030&quot;&gt;thought experiment #8&lt;/a&gt;
) and I was in a hurry. Peculiarly, Github Pages (the hosting I use) didn’t completely refresh the site
after my commit with the post. Let’s see how I fixed this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fix&quot;&gt;Fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to waste your time - here is what fixed the issue for me. I just recompiled the blog locally
(this just changes the timestamp in a couple of places) and committed again. This time everything worked.
I don’t know why. I cross my fingers for it to work for you as well :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use Jekyll on Github pages. Since I want to have more control over the visual theme
and plugins, I do the Jekyll compilation locally and publish the final html to Github pages.
Usually it takes up to couple minutes for Github pages to start showing the new content
after my commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;symptom&quot;&gt;Symptom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that time the link just didn’t work. I kept getting 404. Obviously, I assumed that
I made a typo in the link. I double checked - it was fine. I started the Jekyll server locally
and it also worked. I manually crafted Github Pages URL from a local URL and still got 404.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then tried the same link with “.html” in the end and it worked. I might have given up,
but this was a thought experiment and Savings Ninja &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/the-future-of-work/&quot;&gt;had already published&lt;/a&gt;
my link without “.html”, so this was not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discovering-the-fix&quot;&gt;Discovering the fix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just decided to follow the usual “turn it off and on again” advice and did another commit with
no user visible changes (just some timestamps after Jekyll recompilation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy blogging with timely refreshes of your Github Pages websites!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Recently I was trying to publish a post (namely thought experiment #8 ) and I was in a hurry. Peculiarly, Github Pages (the hosting I use) didn’t completely refresh the site after my commit with the post. Let’s see how I fixed this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to buy ETFs at Flatex</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-to-buy-etfs-at-flatex" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to buy ETFs at Flatex" /><published>2019-11-03T09:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-03T09:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-to-buy-etfs-at-flatex">&lt;p&gt;It can be overwhelming to start buying ETFs, especially for non-German speakers.
Here is a step by step guide to buy ETFs at Flatex in Germany (directly, not savings plan aka Sparplan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally started investing with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/&quot;&gt;Flatex&lt;/a&gt; too (funny fact, this is 
not a referral link, their referral system conditions are weird). They have constant fees (5-8 Euro) to
buy and sell ETFs. To the best of my knowledge all other brokers (except onvista and its derivatives) have
percentage-based fees, which I avoid (here is 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/underestimating-ter&quot;&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt;
 why - basically paying 0.5% of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; my networth is not fun). I already did
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/german-brokers-overview&quot;&gt;an overview of German brokers&lt;/a&gt;
before. I also started using Interactive Brokers in parallel with Flatex to diversify across brokers
and to save more on the transaction fees. However, Interactive Brokers won’t do your investing related taxes,
while Flatex will, so for beginners Flatex is definitely a much better choice.
If you are curious
about Interactive Brokers anyway, I wrote about
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions&quot;&gt;their commissions&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee&quot;&gt;monthly fee&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-buying-etfs&quot;&gt;how to buy ETFs there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am aware of two disadvantages of Flatex. First, they charge 0.4% (Negativzinsen) each year of all the &lt;em&gt;cash&lt;/em&gt; you have with them.
This is actually applied each day (as ~0.4%/365 = 0.00109%) and rounded down. E.g. having 1k EUR with them
for one day will result in 1 cent charge. Solution: just don’t store cash for long. One should be careful, though, and don’t let
the account be negative for long, because the credit rate is 7.9%. One pays Negativzinsen at the end of 
a quarter, so you should transfer the missing money soonish there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second potential issue is that
they charge 5.9 EUR for receiving dividends from individual non-German stocks (this is not ETF, dividends from ETFs are free).
Solution: just buy ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, they have nice customer service, who unofficially speaks English (i.e. this is not advertised,
but they all switched to English easily). They also have non-customer service (i.e. for potential
clients), which is amazing for asking random questions not related to me personally (I don’t have to fill
in all the account details and to verify my identity to ask 5 second question).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume that you have already registered at German Flatex (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/en/&quot;&gt;flatex.de/en&lt;/a&gt;).
Unfortunately I can’t help you with this, because I already have an account with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before buying an ETF you need to have money in your Flatex account. Surprise, surprise.
Fortunately, you get a usual IBAN number where you can transfer money as if it is just a different bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find the IBAN:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&quot;&gt;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to “SERVICE” tab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Bankverbindungen” (which means bank connections or links)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for “Cashkonto” (cash account) and its IBAN. That’s where you need to send your money.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the best to save this IBAN as a template in your bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/iban.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sample screenshot of Bankverbindungen with fake data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please be careful and don’t confuse this with “Externes Konto” (external account),
i.e. the account linked with your Flatex account. For security reasons, you can transfer
money out only to 1 predefined IBAN (in order to change it you actually need to send a paper letter).
This is your “Externes Konto”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to transfer money from your “Externes Konto” though. It can be any account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finding-etf&quot;&gt;Finding ETF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selecting an ETF to buy is an art of itself and this is outside of the scope of this guide.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justetf.com/&quot;&gt;JustETF&lt;/a&gt; is a good start. Once you know the ETF, you need to find
its ISIN number, e.g. for accumulating S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF from iShares it is IE00B5BMR087
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justetf.com/de/etf-profile.html?query=IE00B5BMR087&amp;amp;groupField=index&amp;amp;from=search&amp;amp;isin=IE00B5BMR087&quot;&gt;iShares Core S&amp;amp;P 500 UCITS ETF (Acc)&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/isin.png&quot; alt=&quot;JustETF page for iShares Core S&amp;amp;P 500 UCITS ETF (Acc) with ISIN highlighted&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buy&quot;&gt;Buy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;buying-screen&quot;&gt;Buying screen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you received your money (you see it in your Cashkonto), you can get to ETF buying screen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign in at &lt;a href=&quot;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&quot;&gt;www.flatex.de/kunden-login/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “HANDEL” (trading)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select “Order aufgeben” (give an order)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paste the ISIN number of the ETF you want to buy. I use IE00B5BMR087 as an example&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The suggestion with the ETF should appear, select it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You get to the ETF page, scroll down to see exchanges overview
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/exchanges.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flatex short exchanges view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose one of the exchanges. I recommend XETRA, flatex Preis (TRG) or gettex. 
I personally used gettex in the beginning a lot and, if you are not sure, I suggest to try gettex at first.
Possible criteria for choosing an exchange:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;opening times - exchanges work only at particular times, so some may be closed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fees - each exchange takes its own fee as well, I tried all 3 mentioned above and
the resulting fees were 5-9 EUR&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ETF price - there may be different price at different exchanges&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;availability - there may be more stocks available to buy at one exchange&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If your exchange is not in the list, click “Weitere Handelsplätze anzeigen” (show other trading places)
to show the full list.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click green “K” button (stands for “kaufen”, i.e. to buy) in the row of the selected exchange.
I use flatex Preis (TRG) here as an example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;buying&quot;&gt;Buying&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you get to the actual buying screen. To buy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Double check “Verfügbar” (available), i.e. how much money you have.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/how_to_buy_etfs_at_flatex/available.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flatex buying view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change “Handelsart” (kind of order) to “Limitorder” (order with a limit).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change “Ordertyp” (type of order) to “Limit”. This means that order will be fulfilled 
only when its price is smaller than the limit. This saves you from buying at an extreme price due
to an unexpected market spike.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type the desired price limit into “Limit”. This can be just the current price or 
something 0.1% or 0.5% lower if you don’t mind waiting or risking that your order does not get fulfilled.
Basically, Flatex won’t execute your order unless the price is lower than the limit.
If you set unrealistic limit, your order won’t get executed. At the beginning I suggest to set 
the current price. &lt;em&gt;Important:&lt;/em&gt; use comma (i.e. “,”) as a decimal separator, i.e. 7 EUR 50 cents should become 7&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt;5.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type into “Stück/Nominal” (quantity) number of ETFs to buy.
It can’t be fractional. Please leave 10-15 EUR gap for the fees. Usually they are applied later and not shown at this stage.
If you are curious to know more about the fees, there is “Kostendetails &amp;amp; Auswirkung” link, which shows the breakdown.
This is quite a recent feature, I don’t remember seeing this before.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Nettoschätzung” - should look green, this means that you have enough money. Double check that the number agrees with your
understanding. E.g. if you forgot to use “,” as a decimal separator, the number here will be super large.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Orderzusatz” - “&amp;lt;ohne&amp;gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Gültigkeit (Datum)” - how long the order should be valid. In other words, if the price does not reach your
limit in this timeframe, the order will be canceled. This happened to me couple times and I didn’t pay any fees (anecdotal evidence, I haven’t seen this officially confirmed anywhere).
You can choose “tagesgültig” (i.e. today) or “gültig bis:” (“until”) and some
date of your choice. At the beginning I suggest to set lax limit (i.e. just the current price) and “tagesgültig”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Press “Eingaben übernehmen”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The site will ask you for your TAN code, just fill it in from the card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Done, your order has been created.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually “Verfügbar” (available) cash decreases at this stage, but in some places the money for the order may be shown as if
they are still in your account. Actually, they are, they are just “frozen” for the order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tracking&quot;&gt;Tracking&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check the status of the order in “HANDEL” -&amp;gt; “Orderbuch”. There you can also cancel your order, e.g. if you limit
happened to be too aggressive.
I did this couple times and didn’t pay any fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some time (depends on your limit and market state), the order should get fulfilled and usually after
a delay of at most 1 day, the result gets reflected 
in the interface (i.e. you can actually see the new ETF in your account). 
If this is not the case after a day (assuming this is not a weekend), I suggest to call their customer service.
I personally never had to do this, but better safe than sorry!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-is-still-scary&quot;&gt;This is still scary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that this may look hard and complicated. It definitely took me couple months of research before I started
investing myself. As a workaround, I suggest you to make your first order with 10-50 EUR instead of your original amount.
This way it is much easier to convince yourself to try. In the worst case, the loss is very limited. I did this myself
too. I bought 1 share of some ETF and then sold it the next day to double check that I can get my money back. I know, this sounds
very naive now, but it was scary to move a bunch of my money there otherwise. But soon after, I started to feel pretty confident
with the process, so the learning curve is steep, but manageable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy investing!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It can be overwhelming to start buying ETFs, especially for non-German speakers. Here is a step by step guide to buy ETFs at Flatex in Germany (directly, not savings plan aka Sparplan).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisit what you are bad at</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit-what-you-are-bad-at" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisit what you are bad at" /><published>2019-11-02T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-02T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit_what_you_are_bad_at</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/revisit-what-you-are-bad-at">&lt;p&gt;Often we can get conditioned from outside that we have no talent in some area
and it is just not our thing. Thus, we shouldn’t even try. It is easy to get into 
this trap as a kid due to yet low self-confidence. Consider stopping for a moment and explicitly
catching all ideas like that. Let’s see why you might discover a lot of new about
yourself this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;talent-is-weird&quot;&gt;Talent is weird&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it is indeed the case that a person has very strong innate talent and just
excels in some area. However, in the majority of cases it is not like that. Skills
require time and practice. It is naive to expect immediate results. However, external
observers very often forget about this. Yes, a given kid may not sing too exquisite, but
this does not mean that they can’t sing well in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One does not require that much of talent, but rather just interest and curiosity 
about the area. If one desires to practise and get better, this is already enough
to do so. You don’t have to be good at something, in order to be able to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-your-main-reason&quot;&gt;What is your main reason?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the second point. There may be various reasons to get better
at some skill. For example, it is just fun and one enjoys the process. This is
a perfectly valid reason to just do the thing. The growth is not important.
You don’t have to even show what you are doing to others. If one likes to
sing in the shower, please go ahead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason might be to make money or to impress others. In this case, one
has to care about external opinion. If someone says that you should stop,
this is just a feedback that what you are doing now is not good enough &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;.
Take into account negative feedback, but remember to decrease its
amplitude. Also don’t focus on the negativity, but try to understand what
exactly causes such effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;revisiting-i-never-will-be-able-to&quot;&gt;Revisiting “I never will be able to…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a bunch of areas about which I can
easily say “I never will be able to do it”. For some of them I even spent
quite some time in my childhood and even took lessons. That is I had
quite enough of data to make my conclusion and decide to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with years somehow by chance I went back to some of these areas.
To my surprise, a) it wasn’t that bad
back then b) I can actually improve these skills further and it goes pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then it has become my personal sport to tackle such areas.
If there is something about which I could say “I will never be able to do this well”,
I am definitely lured to disprove that. This was definitely hard at first,
when I didn’t have any positive examples. E.g. I remember
I tried ice skating as a kid. I sucked at it really terribly. But as far as I remember
I tried only once or twice. Then I concluded that this was not mine and I should have focuses
into something else. After some years, I tried again and it just went fine.
I was able to learn to ice skate reasonably well and it is a lot of fun.
With each new such example of breaking “I will never…”, I get
more self confidence to tackle even harder areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, you are now quite a different person. You know so much
more, you have experienced so much more in your life and the world is different now.
There are new challenges, new opportunities. Perhaps something that blocked you back
then is now gone. Perhaps the technology has improved. Perhaps the learning materials
are now so much better. Thus, it makes sense once in a while to revisit your self
beliefs about what you can do and what you can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can imagine some really serious obstacles on one’s way to some skill
(e.g. physical body irregularities). Yes, this may affect the traditional
way of tackling the skill, but nothing prevents one from trying something else.
There are people, who play guitar with their legs (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/CK2TkN0m1SM?t=93&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;irrationality-of-i-will-never-be-able-to&quot;&gt;Irrationality of “I will never be able to…”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense, “I will never be able to…” is almost always false.
Obviously, there are examples where such statement is hard to disprove.
E.g. breathing under water. But if it is about some human developed area
(like art, sport) and the bar is not too challenging (e.g. not world class or Olympic level),
the question is only about how much time one needs to achieve this level. 
It is also about how much time one is ready to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that some skills go better due to some innate ability and just
general life situation. Perhaps one already has skills which work well in that field.
E.g. from math into programming. However, the absence of some skill should never be
a blocker. It just means that one will have to spend more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I suggest to rephrase “I will never be able to…” into 
“I consider it is not reasonable to invest so much time into area X
to reach level Y”. This moves the question from your ability into
your priorities and decisions. Sounds much better, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sometimes-it-goes-better-once-you-start&quot;&gt;Sometimes it goes better once you start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of ignoring such self doubts is that
one can discover their innate ability once they start working
on their skill. Perhaps at first it goes badly, but after
some time they can discover that they are actually quite good at it.
Thus, one should avoid premature conclusions and dropping stuff
too early. Unfortunately, I have no clue when it is the best time to stop trying.
Perhaps when it is not fun anymore.
But to avoid false positives, it should rather be “when it is constantly not fun anymore
for a specific predefined period of time (e.g. a month)”. Otherwise one could
drop out by accident e.g. on a bad day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-others-do-this&quot;&gt;Why do others do this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do other people seed such self doubts?
Obviously this can be malicious (either explicitly
or implicitly). If a competition is possible, it is
easier for them to just convince you to drop than
to actually compete properly. This may happen implicitly as well
(i.e. person does not realize what they are doing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, they may believe into innate fixed talent 
(i.e. fixed mindset instead of growth mindset) and even consider
their advice very beneficial for you. They may not want you to
waste your time. From their perspective, since you does not perform
well at this, you never will and should search for something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed quite a few examples of parents saying this to their kids.
Often this is supported by an argument that parents themselves are really bad at
this skill and, thus, the kids are genetically predisposed to be bad as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dangers-of-such-self-doubts&quot;&gt;Dangers of such self doubts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main problem with such self doubts
is that they become deeply ingrained self-fulfilling prophecies. 
One just stops questioning this statement. It just becomes part of 
them and as a result - becomes completely true. Each time one claims
that they are not good at something and refuses even to try,
they push this self doubt even further into themselves. They self
reinforce it. With time they may even fully forget where it actually came
from and just live with it as a fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, next time you catch yourself thinking that you are not good at something
and as a result shouldn’t even try, try to understand where this is coming from
and whether this is still actually the case. Perhaps it is not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy self improvement, while crashing your irrational self doubts!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Often we can get conditioned from outside that we have no talent in some area and it is just not our thing. Thus, we shouldn’t even try. It is easy to get into this trap as a kid due to yet low self-confidence. Consider stopping for a moment and explicitly catching all ideas like that. Let’s see why you might discover a lot of new about yourself this way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #8: jobs in 2030</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-8-jobs-in-2030" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #8: jobs in 2030" /><published>2019-10-15T09:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-15T09:01:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_8_jobs_in_2030</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-8-jobs-in-2030">&lt;p&gt;Thought experiment #8 about jobs in 2030. Jump in!
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I noticed the new thought experiment by chance and didn’t plan to write it yet,
but I have some time, so why not. Excited to know that it was proposed by 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MoneyModernGirl&quot;&gt;@MoneyModernGirl&lt;/a&gt;. Also funny that 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavingNinja&quot;&gt;@SavingNinja&lt;/a&gt; started to have so many external thought
experiment ideas. This is likely just a recency bias. I remember that last 2 experiments
were proposed by other people. Perhaps, participants just started to propose their ideas.
Ok, feels like I am already in “dump everything verbatim” mood.
Thus, it is the time to read the new experiment! I actually feel much more excited than I was
when I started writing this paragraph. Wow, the magic of writing and just starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-statement&quot;&gt;The statement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I recently read a statistic that 85% of the jobs there will be in 2030 have not yet been created. What do you think these jobs are, and which ones will no longer exist? What does this mean for education? What will offices look like in 11 years? Will people continue to commute to a physical office or will remote work and digital nomadism take over? Finally, how do you think this will affect the overall global economic balance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment page is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/the-future-of-work&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and it has links to other answers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, at least I understand all the words in the description and don’t need a dictionary.
Thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this time there are 2 major ways to answer this question for me.
The first one “I read that” and the second one “My own opinion”.
The issue is that the second one is very tricky to produce aka I don’t have much opinion yet.
But I will just write and I am pretty sure that by the end of this post I will have a pretty strong 
opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What do you think these jobs are, and which ones will no longer exist?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read in multiple places that these will be mostly creative jobs. I tend to agree.
People are doing great at improving efficiency in areas which are necessary for life.
E.g. fewer and fewer people are involved in agriculture (I read this somewhere and feel
lazy to find a proof, sorry). Thus, I assume that this trend will to some degree continue.
2030 is actually pretty soon, so I don’t think there will be full automation by 2030. 
At least I would be very surprised. I suspect that current technology is not sufficient yet
for that (or I just don’t know enough).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, more and more people will be forced to move away from these “strictly-needed-for-life” fields
into “technically-not-needed-but-makes-fun” fields. Some part of this outflow of people should definitely
go to existing creative professions. E.g. writing, making music, videos, painting. This also gets
easier and easier nowadays. One can make a video and publish it on Youtube or even self publish
a book on Amazon. This does not mean that someone will buy it, but at least it is much easier
than publishing a paper book (and so muuuuuuuuuuuuch cheaper).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tendency to automation will create demand for make-automation-happen jobs. Some people need
to maintain the automation. Hm, could this be automated? Not sure, perhaps not at first. Some
people will need to develop automation (thus, research). Some people will need to produce tools
for automation (thus, hardware, software). These areas won’t be that relatively large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also presume that it will be cheaper to buy all the necessities in life. I.e. something like on
the way to Universal Basic Income, but not that dramatic. Since producing stuff needed for life 
gets more efficient and, thus, cheaper, one will need to work less to be able to afford all of that.
One will also have less pressure to work due to that. That’s another argument for creative fields.
People will get more fun from work, because they are not forced to work that much as now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I also read is that customized stuff will be super expensive (this time I remember the source:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/levelsio/&quot;&gt;levelsio&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/levelsio/status/1170997682728361985&quot;&gt;specific tweet&lt;/a&gt;). These cheap ways to satisfy one’s needs will be produced by automation
and will be quite generic. In some sense it is like mass produced clothing now. You do have some choice
(e.g. which color or size), but you don’t get to choose everything about the item (e.g. how it should
be made, precise template). I assume that something like that will happen in the future as well.
Probably, not in 2030, but I think it will already be much cheaper to satisfy basic needs in 2030.
Here I definitely remember that making future predictions is risky, but I am also not betting any
money, so I am fine to do some here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, highly customized stuff will become more expensive and there will be people who produce it.
In some sense this still fulfills the old description - these jobs can be creative. One can buy
a cheap mass produced t-shirt and know that there are thousands (or millions) of them in the world. Or they can pay
much more to a tailor to make a unique one specifically for them. For a tailor this can definitely
be like a creative endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, now I see that the two ways above (what I read vs what I think) do intersect a lot.
So please excuse the mess, but we are going further!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What does this mean for education?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. That’s tricky one. It definitely means that the education will have to change.
Currently the education is meant as a way to produce humans who can create some value in the
world to be able to satisfy their basic life needs. If it becomes much easier to satisfy these needs 
(the extreme case is Universal Basic Income), then the pressure to study should become much smaller.
Obviously, there will be people who will study, but their intention will be very different.
It will be just for their intrinsic fun. If they decide to drop out for some reason, they can definitely
do that. I also think that the studies will have to become more practical. The demand for 
some highly theoretic stuff should go down, but for practical “how to do XYZ” - up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is mostly about higher education, e.g. uni. It is actually hard to imagine what kind of
knowledge will be necessary to be learned in the school. Obviously, in 2030 few will worry about this
and just continue having the old material they used to have, but at some point people will notice
that a lot of it does not make much sense anymore and stop teaching it. Perhaps the mandatory school part
will be compressed in couple years with some really basic stuff like reading, writing, counting,
using Internet, writing blog posts, paying with a credit card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing the paragraph above, I noticed that this absence of pressure to study should create a field
producing these pressure artificially. If you don’t have to do anything, it is very easy to overreact and quit
stuff. For example, “oh, I am having a headache today, let’s drop this university course, perhaps this will help”.
Also I suspect that psychology should become more popular too (not studying it, but using).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What will offices look like in 11 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think they will mostly look like they do nowadays.
There are already examples of companies with no office. surveymonkey.com came to mind
and I can’t remember the second example I heard recently. I assume that the trend will continue.
In some sense the number of jobs which require physical presence are decreasing.
Being in one office is good for communication, but there are workarounds for that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also suspect that coworking spaces will continue to become more popular. If everyone is into
something creative and completely on their own, they will get lonely fast. Thus, being able to
communicate/collaborate with others even when you are not from one company will be valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I suspect that 11 years is just not that much. Or perhaps am I being to conservative?
I think a good way to sanity check this claim is to think about what changed since 2008 
(i.e. 11 years before today). To be honest, nothing too major gets in my mind.
There are many more smart-phones for sure. The offices seem to be pretty much the same.
Yes, the nomad movement is much more popular (I don’t think I ever heard about it back
then at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Will people continue to commute to a physical office or will remote work and digital nomadism take over?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See above.
Some will do, because their job requires that, e.g. hardware development or maintenance. 
Majority won’t have too. Some will do this voluntarily when they feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny that so many office people find the other extreme of having no office 
so nice and attractive. I am pretty sure that once they try it, they will find
plenty of aspects in which their office job wasn’t that bad. E.g. I read that nomads
have very few deep friendships, because it is trickier to build a friendship without
being able to meet and spend time together. I didn’t say impossible. E.g. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sivers.org/&quot;&gt;Derek Sivers&lt;/a&gt; claims to have phone calls with his friends
and this seems to work well for him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Finally, how do you think this will affect the overall global economic balance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another hard question. I suspect that everyone will become a bit more frugal when compared to now.
Now one has to work quite a lot, because otherwise they won’t be able to live sustainably.
At the same time, the job offerings are often such that one has to work a lot more than
they would need to just satisfy their needs. As a result, they have plenty of spare money
and this ends up in consumerism. I feel like being able to work creatively with little financial
pressure should change this. I.e. people will refuse to work that much for stuff they don’t need.
To be honest, once I wrote this it is hard to believe. At least that’s my hope in some sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think that this will stop the economic growth though. These creative endeavors can still
produce value and one could invest into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I got a feeling that my hand-wavy descriptions are missing something, so let’s try
consider a concrete example. This is probably not from 2030, somewhat later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take Jane. She is 12 now. She has already finished her mandatory part of education.
She is free to choose what to do next. She needs 100$ per month to have basic food, some
reasonable-but-modest shelter, minimal fun. She can study a lot for the next years and become
an automation robot developer and earn like 10k$ per month. This produces a lot of value
(scales well) and not many people want to do this - learning all the tricky stuff is boring and hard.
Or she can take some shorter more practical classes. E.g. music, drawing, writing.
She can produce some content on her own and be payed for (or by donations).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to uncover what makes me feel uneasy about my arguments. If everyone is lazy and frugal,
why would someone pay Jane for her music? E.g. nowadays it is extremely hard to get payed by
one’s creative endeavors. In some sense, you must be pretty good to get there. It cannot be the
case that everyone will be equally good. Thus, there will be some competition anyway.
So I am not sure how to resolve this. If Jane gets 100$ per month from her country, then
my model seems to work. If she needs to earn them - than it is tricky. It some sense
Jane is not needed anywhere. This sounds a bit scary. Perhaps she could start her own 
“industry” the same way “let’s-play” videos and streams have started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I suspect that not much will change by 2030. The descriptions above are in my view
more likely for 2050-2100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is funny to experience this conflict, which automation brings. In some sense it tells
you - hey, your work is not needed anymore, but providing for your basic needs is so cheap
that we are happy to do so (perhaps even completely for free). Thus, just enjoy your life.
So will we become a bunch of low educated pleasure seeking constantly depressed weirdos?
It is also funny to think of the impact of this survival pressure on my life. I think I would
have achieved much less if there was no pressure to work and earn money. I also wouldn’t end
up discovering the areas which I enjoy a lot now. I would consider them too difficult and not
worth it. However, I like them a lot now. Perhaps, I would discover something else then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time for people who are adults right now this switch should be okeyish. They already have
developed their sense of “I must stick to this and get through”. Thus, they will be able to figure
out some way to live reasonably happy life even when their job is not needed anymore.
I have no clue how new generations will handle this. Will they be able to self challenge
themselves the same way the world challenges us nowadays?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny that I produced more questions than original post even had.
Overall, despite my descriptions above I do like optimism and I do believe
that everything will be fine. People have got through a lot of bad stuff
and such jobs turmoil does not seem that major from this perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy future!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;About me&quot;, &quot;Thought experiments&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Thought experiment #8 about jobs in 2030. Jump in!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should you tell others about FIRE?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/should-you-tell-about-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should you tell others about FIRE?" /><published>2019-09-24T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-24T23:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/should_you_tell_about_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/should-you-tell-about-fire">&lt;p&gt;Participating in Financial Independence / Early Retirement (aka FIRE) movement can become
a substantial part of one’s life or even identity. At the same time the number of 
people in the movement is still small and, thus, most of the time we talk to
people who have no clue whatsoever about FIRE. As a result, one wonders quite often
whether they should share their FIRE story and explain the concept.
Let’s see arguments for and against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start - a little disclaimer. The life is very complex and multidimensional
and obviously the precise answer whether to share FIRE concept depends on a lot of factors
especially on the person who you consider sharing to. Thus, treat this as food for
thought and consider each situation on case-by-case basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-have-a-lot-of-money&quot;&gt;“I have a lot of money”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching FIRE requires a substantial amount of money, which people outside of FIRE usually don’t
have. Even if you don’t tell this explicitly, a person can easily
deduce this fact from the concept itself. Basically, FIRE = “save a lot” and when
you say “I am into FIRE”, the other person can easily conclude that you want
to have a lot of money and you are on your way there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publicly announcing having a lot of money can backfire. In the worst case the question
can be even about physical safety (highly depends on a country and the setup). In mild cases
this may give a wrong incentive to the other person. E.g. “oh, this person has a lot of
money, I should hang out with them, perhaps they are generous”. I.e. they could start liking
your money more than you and it may be tricky to distinguish the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially tricky in relationships. In many countries there are implicit 
assumptions that one party has to contribute more financially. If this person happens
to be into FIRE and their partner - not, this may sound like a jackpot for the non-FIRE partner.
Basically, from their perspective it is like “hey, I don’t plan to work and since I am considering spending my life with
you, you probably won’t need to work either”. Even when one does not have such dramatic
malicious incentives, they can still be appealed by your financial security and stability.
Again this does not sound right - one should like the person, not their financial state.
At the same time it is perfectly rational for them. If they want a good life for themselves
and their kids, having a very financially stable partner is the best. Thus, I do 
definitely understand their perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can conclude that you should not tell that you are into FIRE to
people who you know poorly to avoid becoming a fruitful target for scams.
If you are in a relationship, consider delaying telling this too.
The idea is to be sure that your partner would be with you even
if you were not into FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trust&quot;&gt;Trust&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I think that you have to eventually tell your partner
everything. First, otherwise it will be extremely hard to explain your 
lifestyle (I can’t even imagine any plausible attempt at this). Second,
if you can’t tell this, then you just don’t have enough trust and 
this suggests that the relationship has intrinsic problems. Obviously,
your case can differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to remember that trust begets trust (which I read
from “Search Inside Yourself” book, &lt;a href=&quot;/post/book-summary-search-inside-yourself&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
is my summary). Thus, by sharing
such an intricate and important detail of your life, you can improve
the state of the relationship and create a positive feedback loop of trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this perspective you should eventually tell about FIRE
people close to you and who you reasonably now and trust. Especially
in a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unhealthy-reference-point&quot;&gt;Unhealthy reference point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I started to use this concept of reference points for happiness quite
a lot recently. I discovered it in “The Science of Wellbeing” course
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;my summary&lt;/a&gt;),
I also recommend to take the course, it is life changing). The idea is that
people are bad at absolute evaluations, so they compare relatively,
e.g. when they decide how good their life is. As a result, when they happen
to have unfortunately high basis for comparison (e.g. rich friend or
neighbor or even some movie actor), they become unnecessarily unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the same impression about FIRE. On the one hand, it can be
like a blessing in life. The move from blind
consumerism and working until state pension to having a concrete goal
and plan can improve one’s life greatly. On the other hand, it can
be a curse. For some people it can be very hard to rich FIRE
for various reasons. They could be okeyish with their current state.
E.g. they just have accepted it and got used to it. And then you
tell them that there is this way to not work and live happily and so on.
This can revive their inner struggle about their state. This can also
set unhealthy reference point for them: “Hey, my friend can reach that,
so I should be able too”. As a result, just knowing about FIRE existence
can make them unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also peculiar that reaching FIRE can actually be demanding in many ways.
One has actually to learn a lot, to control themselves, to manage their
finances, to plan everything for many years in the future. All of these
can be tricky. One can also easily become an outlier and lose their friends
and even their partner if they happen to disagree with the FIRE lifestyle.
Thus, by sharing the idea of FIRE, you may in some way force the other person
into all these difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time we are all grownups and theoretically should be able to make
our own decisions. Having one more option in life, one more theoretical way to move forward,
shouldn’t hurt that much. In the worst case, we can just drop the idea.
I think our brains are good at coming up with not always rational reasons to explain
whatever we want (this was mentioned during the “Science of Wellbeing” course too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally learned about FIRE by chance and extremely happy about it.
Not sure how I would feel about someone else convincing me. I would probably
assume that it is some Ponzi scheme or other scam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, from this perspective, you may try to see how useful the idea of FIRE
will be for someone. If they will likely pursue it and be able to achieve
it, it should be ok to share. If they will just drop it as nonsense, this is 
fine too. If they are likely to get stuck in the middle - the idea is reasonable,
but not achievable - consider not sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally would rather not share and not “convert” people.
It is also partly due to reasons above - by sharing the concept
I will also tell others that I am into FIRE, which I prefer not to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meetups&quot;&gt;Meetups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately there are FIRE oriented meetups, where everyone already knows the concept
and is in approximately similar situation. Thus, if you want to discuss FIRE
(e.g. roast your plan), you should consider attending something like this.
I did this couple times and it was very refreshing experience after years of
silence regarding FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy FIRE discussions (or silence)!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Participating in Financial Independence / Early Retirement (aka FIRE) movement can become a substantial part of one’s life or even identity. At the same time the number of people in the movement is still small and, thus, most of the time we talk to people who have no clue whatsoever about FIRE. As a result, one wonders quite often whether they should share their FIRE story and explain the concept. Let’s see arguments for and against.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No one promised you anything in life</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/no-one-promised-you-anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No one promised you anything in life" /><published>2019-09-22T13:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T13:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/no_one_promised_you_anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/no-one-promised-you-anything">&lt;p&gt;Quite often I observe people being unhappy about their life as if someone has promised them
something. Somehow they focus on what could/should have been better in their life and this
makes them extremely unhappy. At the same time, from my perspective they are not doing that bad.
They are just too much into their fantasies instead of appreciating what they have.
Let’s look into into “no one has promised anything” and see some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observe surprisingly many people with a very specific attitude to life.
Usually they are quite unhappy with what they have and there is always plenty
of stuff they should have had instead. This can be being more beautiful,
smarter, healthier, wealthier (e.g. coming from a wealthier country),
having cooler car. Usually they use other people as a basis of their comparison.
E.g. “Alice is so beautiful and I am not so beautiful, why? This is unfair, 
what did she do for this? Am I worse than her?” or “Harold earns so much at his
startup and it is going so well for him, am I not as smart as him? Why don’t I
have a startup?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outside-our-control&quot;&gt;Outside our control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this wishes are directed to stuff fully outside of our control.
E.g. being more beautiful, coming from a wealthier family, being born
in a different country. Obviously being unhappy about this stuff is 
not rational at all. However, as I read in “Too soon old, too late smart”
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/book-summary-too-soon-old&quot;&gt;my review&lt;/a&gt;) - 
it is very hard to change an opinion formed non-rationally (without logic)
with a rational (formal logical) arguments. This is definitely the case here.
I can occasionally feel something similar too, but I catch this pretty soon.
It is very healthy to try to change your reference points (as it was
suggested in the “Science of well being course”
(&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;my summary&lt;/a&gt;)).
E.g. there are many other things outside of your control which probably have
worked well, but could have been much worse. E.g. you are alive, this is
already pretty good. There are people, who have died already. Some even had completely
no control. Usually there are countries/people which are doing
much worse than you. So in some sense you were lucky to be born where you are
instead of there. There may be many features of your life, which
you don’t appreciate at all, but could. E.g. your have good relationship with
your parents. There are many people who don’t. Or your parents are not divorced.
Or they are even still alive. Or you like your job. Or you have a very nice hobby
and feel happy doing it. Basically by searching a bit and reflecting over your life
you can find plenty of examples where something could have been much worse, 
but it is pretty good. This definitely helps you to appreciate these things more.
This approach is also much healthier than trying to look at what could have
been better. There is no perfection. One can always be a bit
wealthier, healthier, smarter, more beautiful. Even after improving the desired
parameter a lot, one will just start desiring something else. Thus, in some sense
you could fight your desires now instead of being driven by them all your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inside-control&quot;&gt;Inside control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there are some statements, which are somewhat inside our control.
E.g. why Harold has a great startup and I don’t. Perhaps he started the
startup and spent plenty of hours working on it. Perhaps he even failed
multiple times with his earlier ideas. Perhaps he was risking
bankruptcy or losing all his savings, but somehow he sticked to it.
Obviously, it does not mean that one is worse than Harold or that there 
is something intrinsic in one, which prevents them from having a startup.
However, if you don’t have a startup, then you probably didn’t do enough
to have a startup. Obviously, the state you desire is much better than what
you have now. E.g. current state + 1kk$ is better than current state.
However, 1kk$ can’t magically appear from nowhere. One has to do
something to earn them. Or e.g. you would be so happy to be able to speak
Italian. But you can’t magically start speaking Italian, you need to
exert effort for quite some time. Are you ready to invest this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-one-promised-you-anything-in-life&quot;&gt;No one promised you anything in life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often when I hear people complaining in this fashion, I remind myself that
no one has promised them or me anything. They make this weird assumption that they
deserve something by just being alive and themselves. No, they don’t.
They are actually unbelievably happy to live in these times in their conditions.
There is no war around them. They are still alive. Reasonably healthy, both
physically and financially. The nature is actually extremely harsh and scary.
For some people the feeling of physical safety is so innate and obvious, that
they don’t even notice it anymore. While from the nature perspective, it is
a huge privilege. Imagine being a rabbit. You can be dead literally at any moment.
Did you injure a part of you body? Adieu, you are dead - there are no hospitals. Did you got unlucky
and happened to be at a wrong time at a wrong place - you are dead, there is no one
to protect you. You don’t have enough to eat? There is no social security and you
will likely starve to death. Did you happen to be around hunters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;yeap, you are dead and this is completely outside of your control. Humans have already
improved all of this greatly for themselves. The user experience of the modern human life
is just mind-blowing if you compare it to a rabbit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can see how much better your state is when compared to the raw nature.
But even in the human society there are situations where everything is much worse.
E.g. people starved a lot, fought wars, lost their everything due to natural disasters.
You are very likely not affected by any of this. And while it may look like you
are playing your life at hard difficulty (oh, going to work, having to do so
much, so many problems), when considered from this other perspective - it is actually easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even when you find yourself in one of this unlucky situations, this is perfectly normal too.
No one has promised you anything. I do like asking people, who complain in this fashion:
“Did anyone promise you anything in life? I don’t remember something like that in my life”.
Theoretically I can be dead tomorrow and from general life perspective that is perfectly fine.
It is already a miracle that my body functions. Just imagine - it is a weird complex mechanism,
which we don’t even fully understand. And somehow it just works. I get a cut in my skin and it heals.
Completely on its own. Somehow magically. I get tired, then I sleep and feel refreshed again.
I eat and it is digested completely on its own. My brain does something and I get ideas
and can actually be productive. Also somehow magically. Like any of these details could
theoretically go wrong. There could be some weird disease or the brain would just decide to
not function well anymore. Or food could stop being digested. Or I could be dead tomorrow.
Or right now. And again this is perfectly fine from general life or nature perspective.
No one has promised me a specific lifespan or specific conditions in life. 
I am already extremely happy to have what I have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-this-matter&quot;&gt;Why does this matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that it is their right of these people to be unhappy about their situation.
Some sense of unhappiness may be even good, because this is the first step to
improving. However, very often their complaints don’t result in anything productive.
Again - they are free to choose how to spend their time and energy. I just personally
try to avoid such complaints and find it useful to be able to detect such situations
and to get my brain out of them. When they are unhappy about things outside of their control,
they just can’t fix them anyway and, thus, this doesn’t make any sense.
E.g. being more beautiful. You have to work with what you have and I personally
like to accept that. I do have something, I could have had something better, but also
something worse. Thus, I will just do my best at getting the most from what I have.
When complaining about something inside their control, they usually reach a wrong conclusion.
Usually it is just “oh, life is so unfair, poor me”. In reality it should be “oh,
it seems like I like this thing a lot and want to reach this state, thus, I need to do something
and I will start right now”. Do you want to be able to speak Italian? The best way to achieve
this is to actually learn the language. Yes, one can dream about magically being able to speak
it, but this won’t help them at all to reach the goal. Thus, ignore stuff outside of your control.
For stuff inside your control - try to convert it into impulse to do something:
“hey, these people are dancing so nice, I would love to dance that well as well,
oh, I will go to a dancing school right now and start my classes”. Instead of
“oh, life is so unfair, I should have been able to dance easily, I should have had a talent,
I should have taken enough classes already” - you should have, but you didn’t, so just accept that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy remembering that no one has promised you anything!
And setting healthy reference points (remember the poor bunny)!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Quite often I observe people being unhappy about their life as if someone has promised them something. Somehow they focus on what could/should have been better in their life and this makes them extremely unhappy. At the same time, from my perspective they are not doing that bad. They are just too much into their fantasies instead of appreciating what they have. Let’s look into into “no one has promised anything” and see some examples.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Refuse to leave the zone</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/refuse-to-leave-the-zone" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Refuse to leave the zone" /><published>2019-09-17T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-17T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/refuse_to_leave_the_zone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/refuse-to-leave-the-zone">&lt;p&gt;Quite some time ago I stumbled upon &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/akirathedon/status/1152459994849091584&quot;&gt;a tweet&lt;/a&gt;
just saying “get in the zone, then refuse to leave”.
Despite the simplicity of the advice and complete absence of any proof, this has
a profound positive effect on my productivity. Let’s see what this means for me
and why I think this works so well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I completely by accident stumbled upon the following tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/refuse_to_leave_the_zone/tweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;The initial tweet I saw&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fig: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/akirathedon/status/1152459994849091584&quot;&gt;the tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously I don’t do everything people say to do in their tweets, but in this case
the advice just struck me and I did try it almost immediately. And it worked like a charm.
The tweet itself has a longer thread with more explanations. Basically the author
has been doing this for 200 days already. They get into the flow and then just try to stay there
as long as they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-this-works-for-me&quot;&gt;How this works for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I preplan a list of tasks, like creating a playlist, but with work.
Then I start doing the first task in the list. Sometimes this can be hard (I can feel tired, not interested).
Often this can be a very small task (10-20 minutes). I also turn on my time tracking.
Very soon I finish the task and completely forget that I was tired or not interested.
The time has just likely passed like a lightning. And when finishing a task I use the advice from that tweet.
Instead of just turning off the time tracking and marking the task as done, I start to track time for
the next task. Then I quickly mark the previous task as done (the new task is being tracked already,
so I need to hurry up). Then I literally jump into the new task with no hesitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is peculiar that sometimes I have literally no clue how to solve the new task before I actually get to it.
E.g. writing a blog post without having a particular inspiration. If I didn’t try to stay in the zone,
it would be very easy to get scared. I would stop, think that I have no clue what to write and just
get distracted with something unproductive. Instead I just jump into it ASAP. My brain seems to be doing
something like “oh, we are in trouble, I need to quickly come up with some idea, ok, to mitigate
this unpleasant situation of being time tracked and having no clue what to do, I could &amp;lt;some surprising idea&amp;gt;”.
E.g. for blog posts I just quickly go through my list of topics I could write about and take the first
one which resonates with me. It is also peculiar that without staying in the zone I would hesitate which one
to take and would go through the list for much longer with plenty of doubt and multiple equally good options
to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I am able to do this for multiple hours, which was very surprising. Before 
I would struggle very badly and make a lot of breaks. I would also feel quite tired, but
once in the zone, I definitely don’t feel this anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-works&quot;&gt;Why this works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to warn you - there will be a bunch of speculation ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main hypothesis is that starting doing something is hard.
E.g. it is evening and I know that I would love to do a couple of tasks,
but I still have some free time. So I could probably read something pointless somewhere
in the Internet for couple minutes before I start working and be just fine.
Or I am tired. I could go directly to bed. You see, a stuff like this could prevent me
from happily jumping into executing the tasks I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My old approach didn’t take this into account at all, thus, didn’t work that well either.
Basically after completing a task I would make a couple minute break. Yeah, that’s what
people usually do - they do something and then they rest / have fun. The problem is that
I would get distracted and these 2 minutes easily become 10 or even hours. In the end I get to the square 1 - I
need to start again from this unproductive state with all the questions arising again 
(I am tired, should I go to sleep, I already did this one task, I should be fine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I stay in the flow, I just avoid all of this. The flow functions as a momentum to
get me through task switch. Instead of thinking much how I feel and whether I am tired,
I just start another task. By the way, flow feels amazing and once I am in the flow
it is much easier to achieve it in the next task (even if it would be impossible to do
with that task on its own).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach also encourages one to batch their work better,
i.e. to gather similar tasks into series and do them in one go.
E.g. if I write a blog post, I can then write a second one just
because I felt in the mood and was already warmed up for writing.
This saves me from ramping up for writing some other day and,
thus, improves my productivity. The author of the tweet also mentions
batching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just jumping to a task helps to fight perfectionism and analysis-paralysis.
It is easy to start reflecting before doing a task that e.g. I don’t know
what to do or there are multiple options, which are extremely hard to evaluate.
When staying in the flow and starting a task I have no time whatsoever for this.
The time tracking is already on, I already need to start doing something.
Obviously this may lower my quality bar (“let’s just do something”), but
I haven’t seen this being a problem. Instead I get reasonable results
while avoiding perfectionism and over-analysing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest you to try this approach. I understand that we are all different
and the advice above may be life-changing for me, but completely useless for someone
else. Only you know how it is for you. Naturally I still occasionally feel not that well
and don’t even start with any tasks at all. Or I do get distracted before starting. The advice is not
a silver bullet, but still it has improved my productivity a lot and I do feel happier,
because I stay in the flow much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy staying in the zone &amp;amp; being hyperproductive! 
Thank you, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/akirathedon/status/1152459994849091584&quot;&gt;@akirathedon&lt;/a&gt;,
for your tweet with such amazing advice!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Quite some time ago I stumbled upon a tweet just saying “get in the zone, then refuse to leave”. Despite the simplicity of the advice and complete absence of any proof, this has a profound positive effect on my productivity. Let’s see what this means for me and why I think this works so well.</summary></entry></feed>