<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-08-24T14:43:14+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stagnation in impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation-in-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stagnation in impro" /><published>2019-08-24T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-24T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation_in_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/stagnation-in-impro">&lt;p&gt;I started to feel a stagnation in impro. 
I have a hypothesis that this is natural and expected.
Let’s see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impro-for-fun&quot;&gt;Impro for fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally haven’t met that many groups doing deliberate practice in impro.
It looks like accepting random participants into the workshops makes this impossible.
In order to deliberately practice people must be heavily motivated and focused.
In the end newcomers may not even like impro at all, thus, it makes no sense for them to exert
that much effort. I speculate that one needs closed meetings (e.g. invite only,
where all members have to accept a new member) to do deliberate practice.
As a result, 99% of workshops I have been to are meant for fun and laughing.
It is mostly about using the skills you already have and not that much about improving them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progress-in-impro&quot;&gt;Progress in impro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t started that long ago, so I don’t know how this works in the long term.
However, I clearly observed that initially one just removes their own inner blocks
and starts risking to experiment and make mistakes. This is the first stage in impro growth.
In the beginning one is scared to look weird, to be misunderstood, to accidentally insult someone. 
Step by step these blocks get removed and finally one builds almost a direct channel of their
inner creativity to execution. This feels like an enormous growth. I think initially at
my first impro workshops I only observed others and minimized my interactions
(i.e. I did anything only when necessary). I never volunteered and didn’t express myself 
without an external demand. However, already in couple weeks I started to understand
that everyone accepts whatever I do and no one uses that against others. 
People don’t use what you do (especially if you fail) to evaluate you as a person.
That’s very popular outside of impro and I get this reaction often when I tell people
about impro. E.g. I say that one needs a special very understanding group, because some 
stuff may look crazy. Others often reply something like “oh, yeah, people have weird
stuff inside them which just comes out”. That’s a wrong way to look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expectation of no judging helps enormously to progress at first. Basically you just unlock
your skills which you already have - acting, singing, story telling, dancing. Everyone has them
developed to some degree, people are just too shy to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stagnation&quot;&gt;Stagnation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to this level (at a very high speed), you reach a plateau.
Removing inner blocks is not easy, but it is reasonably fast.
And you see very rapid results. Developing the base skills (e.g. acting)
is quite slow. Much slower than removing the blocks. Moreover, the fun workshops
work even better for removing the blocks (people care less about the process or results,
it is less painful when you screw up), they don’t help much with developing the underlying skills.
I can clearly see that some other people seem to perform much better (the result is more interesting),
but I can’t reverse engineer why. There is too much indirection - they just perform a random
scene involving a lot of elements - the problem gets too hard to reverse engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I speculate that I am at this level right now. It feels like standing at one spot.
My impressions is that I perform consistently better than when I started, but 
I don’t see that much growth anymore. Occasionally people mention little details 
which could be improved, but this happens somewhat rarely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I have no clue where this will bring me or whether I will be able to overcome this plateau.
I didn’t plan to take acting classes (and still don’t). I also didn’t expect that this would
be needed for getting better at impro (pardon so naive me). Thus, let’s just see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-better&quot;&gt;What is “better”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, what does it even mean to become better at impro?
I think everyone has their own goals. E.g. if people play impro games
without an audience and never intend to perform, then it could be just
“having more fun”. If they plan to perform with audience, then the
criterion must be “more interesting to observe”. Since each workshop
usually has “temporary audience” (other participants who don’t take part in the scene),
the second criterion feels much more common. For “having more fun” case, you
probably need a very small group of e.g. 2-4 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, “more interesting to observe” does not help much to grow.
It is not obvious that better acting will be that much more interesting
to observe. One definitely needs more peculiar and interesting ideas
in order for the resulting scene to be interesting. I am not aware of any skill
outside of impro directly targeting this area. Perhaps this is the
gist of impro and one can improve it only be doing and observing more impro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-plan&quot;&gt;My plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall impro is a lot of fun for me, so I do plan to continue.
I can’t say that my main goal is to grow. Just having fun is already 
good enough. Thus, I will just proceed as it is and see whether I
keep having no progress. If this persists for long time and becomes
not fun anymore, I will re-evaluate the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy growth in impro!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="impro" /><summary type="html">I started to feel a stagnation in impro. I have a hypothesis that this is natural and expected. Let’s see why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Consumerism would be rational if FIRE did not exist</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-non-existence-and-consumerism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consumerism would be rational if FIRE did not exist" /><published>2019-08-20T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-20T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-non-existence-and-consumerism">&lt;p&gt;I’ve noticed that consumerism makes sense if one assumes that Financial Independence is not achievable. 
Let’s look more into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-fire-perspective&quot;&gt;“No FIRE” perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example of Alice. She works at some job and makes some money.
Let’s consider a case when she does not know about FIRE or for some reason assumes that it is not achievable
(e.g. expects the stock market to stop growing). She spends some part of her salary
each month and with the remaining part she is free to do whatever she wishes. 
It was surprising to me that in such a situation spending a large portion of the remaining money just for fun
makes sense and it is even rational.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Alice’s perspective, there are not that many options to go with her work. At some age, she will
start getting a pension and stop working. Before that she needs money, so she cannot leave the job.
Basically, her no-FIRE assumption leads to “I will likely work until governmental pension age”.
That’s optimistic case. In the worst case she could lose her job. That’s why I said spending “large” portion
of her money and not &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them. From a rational perspective, she needs some emergency savings, but
they don’t have to be as aggressive as for FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under such conditions, it makes sense to try to get the most out of free time she has left (evenings,
weekends and vacation). That’s all what she has left (based on her assumptions) and she needs to maximize
utility of this time, i.e. to maximize happiness. Here we unfortunately leave our so far very formal framework,
because defining happiness is tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider a more concrete example.
Let’s say she has X EUR left after covering all necessary expenses for this month.
One option would be to invest this money and just leave them there. 
Another option would be to boost her happiness by somehow spending them. 
Here we assume that she already has a reasonable emergency fund and various insurances
(disability, medical). If FIRE is not possible, investing does not make sense.
The money will be just laying somewhere without positively affecting her life at all.
I agree that this can be perceived as an additional buffer, but we assume that she already
has a sufficient emergency fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically by investing she could spend the money later. E.g. if she exhausted all ways to
boost her happiness, shew could wait to discover new ones. However, the timeline in this case is still
very different from FIRE. Here it is much shorter - like the next vacation or saving for something expensive.
For FIRE - it is years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that I am not saying how she should spend them. Obviously she could go 100% consumerism
route and start buying a lot of expensive unneeded stuff. As “The science of wellbeing” course has
pointed out (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/a&gt;), this won’t
help her to become happier and even can make her unhappier. She could probably pay for experiences
(e.g. travel) or try to help others. However, here I just assume that there are some meaningful ways
to boost her happiness with spending money and Alice has a magical box telling her these ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this framework, as long as spending money boosts her happiness even a little, it is rational for her to use this opportunity
and spend the money. If there are no meaningful options left, she may save the money for some short time until
an opportunity arises. Anyway, she we will work until pension age and nothing can be done about this (from her perspective).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall visually we can represent this as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism/without_fire.png&quot; alt=&quot;a sample scale with happiness boost of various opportunities, showing number of opportunities ranked by their boost value.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise values are arbitrary.
How to evaluate each option is an art in itself, which we don’t even touch here.
Alice just goes through the opportunity list from top to the bottom and executes them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-exists-perspective&quot;&gt;“FIRE exists” perspective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s imagine that Alice discovers Mr. Money Mustache blog or somehow changes her mind about FIRE.
Now FIRE becomes viable for her and she may pursue it. 
How does this affect the framework outlined above?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much, FIRE is just another opportunity on her list with its own “happiness boost score”.
Again it is close to impossible to estimate it well (you probably have to trust your feelings and priorities),
but for simplicity we assume that Alice somehow magically can make this estimate.
Thus, the framework still works the same as before, there is just one more option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the picture becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_non_existence_and_consumerism/with_fire.png&quot; alt=&quot;a sample scale with happiness boost of various opportunities, showing number of opportunities ranked by their boost value, including saving for FIRE.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically there are still opportunities, in which it makes sense to spend money to boost happiness.
However, at the same time there is now a new mega opportunity - saving for FIRE.
It functions as a lower bound for all other opportunities - with FIRE I expect to be
happy to a certain degree, thus, if I have some spare money and no better way to spend them (i.e. bringing more happiness),
I should invest them for FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like you are going to ask “hey, that’s all very cool, but what is the point?”.
So I am going to reply in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, this is a useful exercise to understand others better. I am reading “Search Inside Yourself” these days
and they talk a lot about taking other people perspective to understand them. Previously I personally was 
confused by people, who explicitly refused FIRE and continued their regular “shopping therapy” routines.
It may the case that they just don’t find FIRE realistic - likely they have never seen anyone who reached this state,
this also means going against the crowd and one becomes an outlier and in some sense a pioneer.
It is also funny that I can remember the times before I discovered FIRE. I definitely felt unhappy about
working for decades, but this unhappiness didn’t go anywhere. I just couldn’t find a solution, so I was 
slowly going into “ok, let’s at least have as much fun as I can” mode. Fortunately, I discovered FIRE
and this gave me proper perspective and I abandoned that route immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the happiness maximization framework with a list of opportunities also works for FIRE.
Are you not sure whether you should invest the money or spend them in some fancy way?
Then try to answer whether it will make you that much happier. I understand
that this is still a hard question, but it is a good first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy rational happiness maximization!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><summary type="html">I’ve noticed that consumerism makes sense if one assumes that Financial Independence is not achievable. Let’s look more into this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #7: true happiness</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-7-true-happiness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #7: true happiness" /><published>2019-08-08T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-08T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_7_true_happiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-7-true-happiness">&lt;p&gt;The new thought experiment! About happiness this time! Woohoo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;concept&quot;&gt;Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;my last thought experiment post&lt;/a&gt; for
the description of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;before-we-start&quot;&gt;Before we start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, this time I feel quite excited and I was looking forward to the new experiment.
I am extremely curious what it is about. Somehow I started to really enjoy participating 
in them. I am reading “Search Inside Yourself” by Chade-Meng Tan these days and there they
write about “Journaling”. Basically writing down your thoughts as they are, without blocking them.
They claim that this allows you to understand yourself better and overall become happier.
Today I understood that SavingNinja experiments are like that!
So, the therapeutic effect is included! And it is completely for free! Ok, looks like I jumped to dumping my thoughts too
early, let’s actually have a look at the new experiment. I hope it is not scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-statement&quot;&gt;The statement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most people’s lives are filled with so much commotion. We’re constantly moving and thinking like an electrode jumping from atom to atom. There are very few moments when we experience true clarity, when we have a chance to really think clearly. These moments may come when reaching a mountain peak in the early hours of the morning or when you’re sitting up late one night and silently staring at the stars. Lots of life-changing decisions can be made in these moments; when you have the time to think about true happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;So, for this Thought Experiment, I’d like you to create one of these moments for yourself. I’d like you to think, and I mean really think about what you want and need to make yourself and your family happy.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;What do you need to achieve real, true happiness? What are you aspiring to? Paint that perfect picture, you will need it as a guide whilst you make your way through life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment page is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-is-happiness-to-you&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (it includes links to answers of others, I definitely recommend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know the word “commotion”. Let’s see the definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;commotion - a state of confused and noisy disturbance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, ok, that’s approximately what I guessed. Ok, reading further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;finished reading&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, this sounds really tricky. True happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have no clue, but I start to get vague ideas, so let’s go with something
and then see where this brings us (oh, this is so meta-meta level now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely would like more control in my life and a better guarantees for the
worst case scenario. It is hard to define control well, but I can give a couple of examples.
E.g. when I wake up one morning and I &lt;em&gt;have to&lt;/em&gt; go to work, but don’t feel like it at all.
I am not physically sick. I just don’t feel like working today. I would love to be able to
just say - “ok, a good day not to work” and just not to work. Currently, I can’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst-worst case is death. This I don’t consider much,
because I probably can’t affect it much either. So by the worst case scenario I mean something
like I lose my ability to earn money and then I don’t have enough to live.
I would like to know that
if something like this happens, I have enough to just be. I.e. I won’t need to be needed.
In some sense this is like an insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But both of these examples follow from my desire to reach FIRE. If I had to explain why
I want to reach FIRE, these would be the first two examples. This somewhat discredits
them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, did I mention journaling in the book above? They claimed that one can understand themselves
and what they want better. So I should probably try that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that I definitely would like to be healthy. This is probably a precondition for
everything else. It is funny that this did not come as the first idea, but whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I started to derail, I will reread the statement again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would like enough time and financial resources to satisfy my insatiable curiosity.
&amp;lt; I had to check the definition of “insatiable”, because I was not sure&amp;gt;. To be honest,
calling it financial resources is probably an overkill. I can definitely find plenty
of interesting stuff costing 0 or close to 0. But when considering the time, the situation is completely
different. I definitely would like more free time and just to do stuff for the sake of doing it
without any other (e.g. financial) incentives. I think this is called time affluence.
I suppose when I gradually lose it in my life, I start feeling bad and then notice
absence of time affluence, slowly regain it back and start feeling better again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is again just equivalent to “become FIRE”.
Oh, SavingNinja, you are putting me into a tricky situation here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then more communication with people would be nice. I feel like it is overall fun
(depends on people, but with some it is amazing), but I kind of lazy enough not to
try that hard to establish something with others. As a result, I don’t communicate often.
Occasionally it works out well and I feel very nice. I also have strong views (aka 
stubborn), so with some people it is just hard (not for me, I suppose, mostly
for them). This desire is probably coming from outside. I just heard from multiple
sources that this makes people happier (including the happiness course on Coursera,
I did 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;a proper review for it&lt;/a&gt;
 as well as 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary&quot;&gt;a brief summary&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I am really scared to reread this. It probably makes little sense.
It would be funny just to post this without rereading at all, but I need to 
at least fix my typos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also be very surprised if this experiment would really change my life dramatically.
It takes me ages to make a decision, but once I do that, it is very unlikely
that I will change it (see “strong views” above and also I need quite a few
arguments to make a decision, so it is unlikely that all of them become
void at the same time). Thus, changing my views is very
gradual process. This could be a trigger or the beginning of the shift, but
not an actual change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also scared that FIRE will lose its charm once I reach it.
Basically, now having free time could look so nice, because the time is scarce.
Once I have free time, what if this charm and magic just goes away due to absence of 
scarcity? Scary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeap, finding a perfect life partner would be great. Oh, perhaps even understanding what
“perfect” means would already be amazing. Oh, a funny observation, “understanding what
would make me happy would make me happy”. Technically I should be happy already :)
that’s like a recursive criterion of happiness, because I know that “understanding what
would make me happy” would make me happy. And since I know this I should be happy now.
Ok, at least this made me smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would say - health, FIRE with freedom and control coming out of it, 
a bunch of interesting people to talk to (who would inspire me),
an obviously great life partner (without whom I would not be able to imagine my life).
It is actually funny that it is quite a strong criterion: “without whom I would not be able
to imagine my life”. My worry is that I may be overshooting. Like the maximal level could be like
“having great time together”, but I ask for “not being able to imagine my life without”
and as a result refuse good relationships. Oh, how did it go into relationships?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt; rereading the statement again &amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also love to make people, who I care about, happy.
Try to improve their life and help them to make the best out of it.
This can mean challenging them or traveling together.
This does not mean making it as easy as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also probably need acknowledgment from other people.
I.e. some positive feedback for what I am doing.
It might be interesting to do something for the sake of it and my own
joy, but so far I cannot imagine this. E.g. painting something which
no one else in the world would ever enjoy or find interesting. This is 
a valid activity and I can see how it could be pleasant, but somehow
I can’t imagine doing this at this stage. I would rather try to impress others.
In some sense this adds challenge or in the math terms - regularization. 
When doing it for myself, there are no limits or boundaries. Whatever I do is
the right thing. It can be tempting to choose the easy path.
For others, there is always some external limit, which I can’t cross,
otherwise they will refuse the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, also being able to use computer sustainably would be amazing as well.
So far I feel like no matter which approach I choose with my setup,
it works for some time and then I discover that actually some part of my body
does not like that approach. It is not that acute, but slowly it accumulates
and after some time I notice that something is fishy and “let’s start this game again”.
So somehow being sure that what I am doing with my computer setup is reasonably 
sustainable would be amazing! It is hard to imagine my life without a computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I would like to spend more time in nature as well.
Perhaps more days without Internet. I occasionally spend a day without Internet at all.
I just turn off my router and that’s it. Somehow it feels very differently.
Easy and calm. Amazing. I definitely can’t explain that. So I would like to try
to have more of such days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also doing projects with others would be interesting (like a combination of my curiosity
and communication). Now I don’t have enough time for this (blink, blink at SavingNinja and
our plans for a game-project, I feel sorry for not having much progress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, I just looked back and I wrote really a lot. I even feel a bit lazy to reread it.
Ok, I did reread it anyway. I did write a lot. Somehow it went mostly from “what I am scared of”,
but I think this is fine. I did say that I don’t have much clue what would make me really
happy. That’s also why I am trying to reach FIRE. This sounds like a good tool
for whatever I decide later. Also working in the office until 67 or so does not
go into that list for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I would like to point out that happiness course (which I already mentioned
above and even gave links to my reviews, it would be weird to give them again) thinks about happiness
somewhat differently. Basically, it is about (I am not looking into the reviews,
just doing this from memory) having enough money, having enough free time (time affluence),
deep social connections and doing kindness, being in the flow, good reference points
(not comparing yourself with others or at least not with wrong others), good sleep,
enough sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I hope you enjoyed it. This was challenging and I was in the flow for sure.
Thank you, SavingNinja for challenging me and bringing plenty of food for thought!
I am looking forward to what others will write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy discovering what makes you happy (without my recursive tricks above)!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;About me&quot;, &quot;Thought experiments&quot;]" /><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">The new thought experiment! About happiness this time! Woohoo!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I write this blog</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-i-write-this-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I write this blog" /><published>2019-08-06T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-06T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/how_i_write_this_blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/how-i-write-this-blog">&lt;p&gt;I would like to go a bit meta and tell you how I write this blog. 
This includes somewhat technical details and just general process.
You can treat this is an overview of a life of a post in this blog - from an idea to being published.
Thus, please let me welcome you to the backstage, but take your shoes off first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ideas&quot;&gt;Ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every post in this blog starts with an idea. As you might have noticed, I don’t limit myself to any
particular topic and this is also true for my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I collect ideas for posts non-stop. Whenever I get something vaguely resembling an idea for a post,
I just take a note of it and add it to my list. The bar at this stage is extremely low.
Basically, I just write it down (with enough info to be able to understand what I meant and occasionally
possible ways to develop it) and forget. I use my “the worst that can happen” principle here (which I already
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-worst-that-can-happen&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; before). In the worst case, I just change my
mind later and delete the idea. Thus, my goal here is to just collect something, evaluation will happen later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my idea-collection phase (I call it “catching”). Overall, I like this process a lot,
because it is hard to get an idea on purpose, but they do come often by themselves especially when walking
or doing something unrelated. As a result, when I feel like writing a post, but don’t have any idea in mind,
I can just look at my list and something immediately resonates with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea list has a lot of items at this stage. As I said, the bar is extremely low. 
I would say I have ~100 items there. Some are probably not actionable (the bar is unbelievably low here, did I say this already?).
But there are 10-20 ones which I could just start writing about right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this has some disadvantages. The list works like a stack. Thus, the oldest items
just stay there and normally I don’t reach them at all. Normally I find something interesting already in the beginning of the list.
With time I add more items and it gets even less likely to reach the oldest items.
I could probably randomize the order, but this is not a problem for now. Just an observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also publish some ideas as ideas in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/queue&quot;&gt;“Future post ideas” list&lt;/a&gt;. As you might have
noticed I don’t do this that often. Theoretically you could check out my ideas there and I would notice
in my statistics that some of them are more popular than others and then write about the more popular ones sooner.
In practice I haven’t got that much signal this way so far. Also publishing ideas feels cumbersome, because there are 
too many of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-minutes-of-post&quot;&gt;First minutes of post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then at some point I feel like writing a post. If I don’t have anything in mind, I will go through
my list and find something. Here I again use “The worst that can happen principle”. Basically, I just
sit down and start writing whatever I like without rereading or correcting much. The idea is to get
something out. Polishing is not a goal. In the worst case, I will reread it at some point and
just delete the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I have the first reasonable draft, I put it into “baking” stage. This should have been named
more like “aging” (like wine), but I like “baking”. I just leave the draft for at least 
a week without looking at it at all. The point is to completely forget about it. This is 
surprisingly easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;publishing&quot;&gt;Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choosing&quot;&gt;Choosing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually publish 2 posts per week these days - one on Tuesdays and one during the weekend.
This is completely arbitrary. I definitely started with publishing randomly, but having some
system helps to develop a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say it is Tuesday and I need to publish a post. I just go into my folder with drafts
and check whatever I have there. During good times I have 5-6 drafts at the same time
(i.e. posts for the next 3 weeks already baking). During average times only 1-2 drafts
(i.e. enough only for this week). Nowadays I am in the later stage. I should try to 
get to the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple benefits with having 5-6 drafts at any point in time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;posts are being baked for much longer (~3 weeks)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if something unexpected happens and I won’t have time to write new stuff, I will 
have enough posts in my reserve to get by for some time. On average publishing a draft is much faster
than writing a draft. You can treat this as my emergency post fund.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when choosing what to post, it is easier to find something resonating with me 
when I choose out of 6 posts (instead of 1 or 2).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-baking-processing&quot;&gt;Post-baking processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I selected something, I just go through it and fix whatever I don’t like.
Very often the structure is weird or there are a bunch of typos or weird language constructs.
Funny enough - this is impossible to see just after writing a draft and this almost screams
at me when I reread the post after “baking” it. If the post is too bad or I find a major flow
(e.g. false assumption), it can get deleted at this stage or postponed for additional improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this stage, the post gets published! Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-publish&quot;&gt;Post-publish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I also tweet about almost each published post in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;my twitter account&lt;/a&gt;.
This is a good exercise for my mind to clearly identify the gist of my post. If you are into Twitter, this might
be a good way to learn about the new posts. There is also &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml&quot;&gt;an RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve
heard that Google Reader is dead, so I don’t know how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I also publish on Reddit (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;my account&lt;/a&gt;).
I do this only for posts which are relevant to the reddits I am aware of.
There people can comment and I definitely enjoy this. Very often they propose corrections (e.g. I was thinking
that capital gain tax with solidarity tax in Germany was 26.25% (i.e. 25% * 105%) and it was pointed out that
it is 26.375% (i.e. 25% * 105.5%)). In such cases I do add corrections to my posts. Sometimes this involves redoing
all the calculations and graphs (a lot of fun - irony^100).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-details&quot;&gt;Technical details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; framework to run my blog. I already &lt;a href=&quot;/post/jekyll-post-url-not-working&quot;&gt;touched
the benefits of using Jekyll in an older post&lt;/a&gt;. Since I am into
programming, Jekyll’s approach fits me well. My blog has “source code”, the same way as programs in programming.
I also need to “compile” it to produce the actual final website. As a result, I can automate or simplify
a bunch of changes. Theoretically, I could completely change the design and then recompile and all
the pages would use the new design. Similarly with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/about/&quot;&gt;“About” page&lt;/a&gt; - yes, it took me
40 minutes to set it up, but now when I add a new post, I just mention its category and everything 
else happens completely automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have already guessed, I also use git for version control of the blog.
Theoretically this is not necessary for blog posts (especially since there is only me
writing them), but as I said with Jekyll there is some programming involved, so I definitely
prefer having git versions. This way if something goes wrong, I could easily go to a previous version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love this feeling of seeing how something great and sizable is made step by step, a little bit
at a time. Occasionally I look at my git log or blame and enjoy this feeling. This is also a good source
of raw data for statistics about me writing this blog (e.g. how much and when).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-last-section-normally-this-would-be-conclusions-but-there-is-nothing-to-conclude-in-this-post&quot;&gt;The last section (normally this would be conclusions, but there is nothing to conclude in this post)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hoped you enjoyed me giving you a peek into how this blog is getting created. That is a brief look
behind the curtains. Please don’t forget your shoes.
I definitely plan to continue with similar posts in the future (e.g. “Why I write this blog” and “Why I 
believe that everyone should write a blog”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any feedback, questions or suggestions, you are welcome to contact me with whatever channel you 
prefer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;,
email - merelycurious protonmail.com). If you are unsure whether you should write to me, please use “The worst that can happen”
principle. These days I don’t get that much feedback (I am going forward pretty blindly with the blog, mostly following
my curiosity), so I will
(with high probability) enjoy your feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy going meta in your lives, folks!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="meta" /><category term="about_me" /><summary type="html">I would like to go a bit meta and tell you how I write this blog. This includes somewhat technical details and just general process. You can treat this is an overview of a life of a post in this blog - from an idea to being published. Thus, please let me welcome you to the backstage, but take your shoes off first.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chrome Incognito, FlixBus and 5 EUR</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito-flixbus-and-5-eur" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chrome Incognito, FlixBus and 5 EUR" /><published>2019-08-03T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-08-03T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito_flixbus_and_5_eur</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/incognito-flixbus-and-5-eur">&lt;p&gt;Quite a peculiar story happened to me recently.
I was buying a FlixBus ticket for 24.99 EUR. I already had it in my “cart” and I had 
30 minutes to buy it before the cart expires. Then I started double checking other
details and in the end it expired (actually couple seconds before I pressed “pay”).
I tried to buy it again, but now the price was 29.99 EUR, i.e. 5 EUR more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;workaround&quot;&gt;Workaround&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uh, I was confused and surprised. They definitely knew that I am interested in this ticket.
I already almost bought it once and, yes, I still wanted to buy it.
But increasing the price by 5 EUR because of that would be mean.
Fortunately, I knew that they can recognize me (by my browser session) and perhaps if I start fresh
the price would be different. E.g. they could set a “cookie” in my browser saying
something like “hey, this chap tried to buy this ticked already, let’s do +5 EUR, cheers!”.
This cookie would be absent in my new session. Thus, I tried to open the same page
in a Chrome Incognito tab. Guess what - the price was the old one - 24.99 EUR.
They could potentially correlate my new session with my old one (e.g. by IP, time and my computer hardware),
but that would be cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I don’t remember precisely, but I feel like I refreshed the old session page as well after seeing 24.99 EUR
in the incognito tab and it was still showing 29.99 EUR. This is actually a very important detail to understand
how this happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypotheses&quot;&gt;Hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;someone-is-being-mean&quot;&gt;Someone is being mean&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, this could be intended. Theoretically, FlixBus almost made +5 EUR out of nowhere
(ok, out of my pocket to be precise). It is easy to see how this could benefit them.
However, this would be pretty mean and I would be very surprised if this is the case.
The approach does not look very sustainable, someone would definitely notice and complain.
Also it is better to assume positive intention and give benefit of doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bugs-bugs-bugs&quot;&gt;Bugs, bugs, bugs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit more plausible explanation is that this is just a bug. So far this is my best guess.
As far as I know, FlixBus uses “adaptive” pricing. I.e. if someone buys a ticket, the next 
ticket can cost more. This tries to adapt to the actual demand (people buy more tickets to
some destination, demand must be high, so the price can higher too). Airlines go crazy
with this stuff. I haven’t observed FlixBus increasing and decreasing their prices
frequently, but airlines (based on my experience) do this a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, when “almost” my ticket (24.99 EUR one) was in my “cart”, FlixBus could already raise the price for
the next one to 29.99 EUR. They could just assume that the first ticket is almost sold.
And then when the first ticket “expires”, they need to decrease the price back.
Perhaps there is some race condition here and I happened to open the state when my old not-bought expired ticket
was still in the cart (but in the reality it wasn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the question is why incognito helped. I could imagine them having multiple servers
and perhaps some caching. Theoretically, my new tab could have hit some other server,
which was already aware that 24.99 EUR ticket came back. Or the server serving the old
session could have cached 29.99 EUR (but caching price pages sounds weird).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that my hypothesis is somewhat weak, but, hey, the info I have is limited as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experiment&quot;&gt;Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design&quot;&gt;Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, originally I didn’t plan to experiment with this, but now I am curious.
The plan is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a couple tickets to “cart”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let them expire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check their price again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open incognito and check price there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I observe the increase, I could create a new Chrome profile, check the price and then and inject the cookie from the old profile
into the new one and check the price again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to add Berlin - Munich tickets to my “cart”. Unfortunately, one cannot add two tickets on the same day in the same
direction (which makes sense, but it is inconvenient for my experiment), so I added 3 tickets for each day from 21st of August to 
23rd of August. FlixBus shows when there are 0, 1 or 2 tickets left at this price, so I varied this parameter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21st of August - price 27.98 and 2 seats left at this price
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 21st of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;22nd of August - price 27.98 and 1 seat left at this price
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 22nd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;23rd of August - price 27.99 and no additional messages.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Initial ticket price for 23rd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall my cart was 83.95 EUR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/init_summary.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cart overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I waited for ~20 minutes and checked from an incognito window.
Only in the second case (22nd of August) price grew to 30.98 EUR.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;22nd of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes sense (they said I took the last seat at the previous price).
On the 21st of August they say that 1 seat is left at this price, but the price is the same.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;21st of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 23rd nothing has changed.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/mid_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;23rd of August ticket price before expiry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I let the cart expire.
Funny fact: they say “1 minute&lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;” when only 1 minute is left:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/1_minutes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;1 minute**s**&amp;quot; expiry warning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably so few people reach this point (and observe the page while doing that), that no one complained or it is
not worth fixing. Yeap, a minor nit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fun fact: the number turns red when it is 0:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/0_minutes.png&quot; alt=&quot;&amp;quot;0 minutes&amp;quot; expiry warning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally - expired:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/session_expired.png&quot; alt=&quot;Session expired message&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I checked all the prices from the same browser window, i.e. same session.
All prices were the same as they were when I started my experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_21st.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 21st of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_22nd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 22nd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_same_session_23rd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Final (after expiry) ticket price for 23rd of August&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I.e. I did not observe any price increase in any of the cases.
I was just able to rebuild my “cart” with exactly the same prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/incognito_flixbus_5_eur/final_summary.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rebuilt cart with exactly the same prices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not able to reproduce the issue.
Obviously they could do this trick only once in a while to prevent someone like me detecting this.
My gut feeling is that this is a weird bug due to multiple system part interaction (e.g. caching or distributed servers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;flixbus-opinion&quot;&gt;FlixBus opinion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have asked them on Twitter (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_/status/1157727264647372801&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;). Not sure whether they
will reply (that would be very unpleasant to debug for someone there
especially based on the scarce data I have here and me being unable to reproduce it), but let’s see.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="funny" /><category term="bugs" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html">Quite a peculiar story happened to me recently. I was buying a FlixBus ticket for 24.99 EUR. I already had it in my “cart” and I had 30 minutes to buy it before the cart expires. Then I started double checking other details and in the end it expired (actually couple seconds before I pressed “pay”). I tried to buy it again, but now the price was 29.99 EUR, i.e. 5 EUR more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dangers of “Work hard, play hard”</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers-of-work-hard-play-hard" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dangers of &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot;" /><published>2019-07-30T09:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T09:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers_of_work_hard_play_hard</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/dangers-of-work-hard-play-hard">&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered that people use expression &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot; as a way to
explain treating themselves something nice. The expressions itself often comes from
their workplace. At first, this felt ok to me, but when taking into account
Financial Independence / Early Retirement, I can see that one’s employer
can be incentivized in one following this expression. Let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work hard, play hard. Sounds pretty innocent and reasonable. You do a great job, 
you get to enjoy its results and “rest”. It also seems to make sense to use your time 
as efficiently as possible in both cases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when working - to improve your results,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when resting - to rest better and to have more fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often “Play hard” part involves
spending a lot of money. E.g. one could consider vacation nearby (e.g.
if they live in Germany, some city in Germany or neighboring country) or some exotic
far away destination (like Costa Rica). In the process one can say “I worked very hard, now I 
deserve playing hard, so Costa Rica it is”. You see the principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-comes-fire&quot;&gt;Here comes FIRE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Work hard, play hard” makes sense before one knows about FIRE. I have to admit 
that at some point in my life even I used “Play hard” part to decide whether to spend money.
However in the context of FIRE, it is very easy to see dangers of this
expression and why it can be good for one’s employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-1-obvious-one-work-hard-for-productivity&quot;&gt;Incentive #1 (obvious one): Work Hard for productivity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employers love when one works hard. They are extremely incentivized
to make this the case. The harder their employee works, the better the results are,
the more money employer makes. Normally one doesn’t get all the benefit which they
produce at work propagated back to them. Thus, even after a raise or a bonus for good
work, the employer still benefits from one’s hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-2-another-obvious-one-play-hard-for-rest&quot;&gt;Incentive #2 (another obvious one): Play Hard for rest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to work hard, you need to recharge your energy well.
Otherwise, you will burn out. Thus, based on the previous incentive, employers
also love when you rest very well and recharge before coming to work. Thus, if one
spends their personal time for their own very effective rest, this is very positive
for their employer (better performance, more money) and somewhat positive to the person
(somewhat more money theoretically, burnout sucks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-3-surprising-play-hard-to-spend&quot;&gt;Incentive #3 (surprising): Play Hard to spend&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is hard to notice without FIRE. Basically, imagine that your salary is magically 
2 million EUR per month. After couple months, you could likely quit, since you
will have enough money in your stash (not for getting 2kk EUR monthly during your FIRE, but still enough).
And now imagine that your employer manages to convince you to “Play Hard”. Heck, you
are making 2 million EUR per month. You can spend 1.8 million EUR every month and
still save 200k. You will still save more than majority of people. Very few people earn that much,
so you deserve this! Then you find many fancy ways to spend a lot of money. Inflate your
lifestyle. After vacation on a yacht in the Caribbean and an amazing 10 room apartment
with a jacuzzi (or 5), having a vacation in Stuttgart or living in a studio apartment
feels hard. And now you can’t quit anymore. You need a lot of money to support such
a lifestyle. By saving 10% of your income, you need ~51.4 years to save for your retirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You probably don’t get payed 2kk EUR monthly (otherwise, wow, I am proud that you
read this). However, the same approach applies to any salary. I just exaggerated the example
to make it easier to digest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;incentive-4-questionable-play-hard-to-not-grow&quot;&gt;Incentive #4 (questionable): Play Hard to not grow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you don’t know about “Play Hard” and just work.
In the evening, you tinker with various projects, learn new skills.
In some sense, this is good for your employer, because theoretically
you may become more productive. But at the same time,
this makes your more valuable on the job market. The raises are usually 
lower than starting bonuses (i.e. one will likely end up with more
money by changing a job instead of getting a raise). Thus, in this case
there is a risk that you will leave your employer. E.g. some other
company notices your projects and makes a more generous offer. 
Or you can even start a startup. I feel like the risk of losing you is higher
for the employer than the benefits from your learning. And with
“Play Hard” you are directed to just have fun without long lasting
effects (except rest and spending money). I understand that for some
of us, “playing” may involve learning or tinkering, but in the general
case this is considered work and normally people wouldn’t use this activities
for their leisure time. Even though it would make them much happier
(e.g. due to being in the flow, according to “The science of wellbeing” course, 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;summary of which I already posted&lt;/a&gt;
).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, if you notice yourself using “I worked hard, I may play hard” argument, especially to spend
more money, try to stop for a moment and reconsider. Is this really what you want? Is this really
beneficial for you and your life? I am pretty sure there are enough cases when it is, but your
employer may be heavy incentivized in you following this expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another funny way to understand this expression could have been “Work Hard” = “Save for FIRE”,
“Play Hard” = “Enjoy FIRE”, but even this does not work well. This seams to involve life style
inflation and implicitly says that your FIRE saving phase sucks and you won’t 
“work” during FIRE. It doesn’t have to be this way. Ideally your lifestyle shouldn’t change much.
You just replace ordinary job time (i.e. 40h a week) with some other activities, which you enjoy more.
This can be whatever you like (even just continue working).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I would rephrase the expression as “Work reasonably ok, analyze incentives, consider saving for
FIRE, enjoy your life in the ways you like (this does not have to be rest or expensive “play”, but it may”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy effective work and conscious rest!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;, &quot;Frugality&quot;]" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">I’ve discovered that people use expression &quot;Work hard, play hard&quot; as a way to explain treating themselves something nice. The expressions itself often comes from their workplace. At first, this felt ok to me, but when taking into account Financial Independence / Early Retirement, I can see that one’s employer can be incentivized in one following this expression. Let’s see how.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Physics, acceleration and FIRE\(^2\)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-squared" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physics, acceleration and FIRE\(^2\)" /><published>2019-07-28T01:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-28T01:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/fire_squared</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/fire-squared">&lt;p&gt;Financial Independence / Early Retirement is about reaching a state, in which you get enough passive income to live.
Let’s say you get \(Y\) EUR each month. The overall money you get over time is \( M = Y * t \), where \(t\) is time.
This resembles a physics equation for movement with constant speed (i.e. no acceleration).
Let’s explore this similarity and try to add acceleration to FIRE and get FIRE\(^2\) (FIRE squared, I just made this
name up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;physics-prelude&quot;&gt;Physics prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an object moves with a constant speed \(V\) in one dimensional space,
then its position can be obtained by \(x = V t + x_0\), where \(t\) is time
and \(x_0\) is the initial position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case above assumes no acceleration (the speed is constant).
If we have constant acceleration the equation becomes \(x = \frac{a t^2}{2} + V t + x_0\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-to-fire&quot;&gt;Back to FIRE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In physics the object moves by \(V\) for each unit of time.
In FIRE one gets \(Y\) EUR each month (i.e. unit of time).
Basically, if we denote cumulative number of money obtained through FIRE as \(C\),
the equation is similar to the equation above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = Y t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s try to add acceleration here.
The equation becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = \frac{a t^2}{2} + Y t&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
Y = a t + \text{&lt;initial value&gt;} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean? 
The first month we get \(Y\). The second month we get already \(Y + a\).
The third - \(Y + 2a\) and so on. In other words, the amount we get from
FIRE each month (our speed) should grow by \(a\) each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s check whether equation above works as we expect. At \( t = 1 \) 
the value is \( C = \frac{a}{2} + Y \), but we expect only \( Y \). This is likely, because the
speed in physics grows continuously, while here in FIRE the process is discrete.
E.g. for \( t = 0.5 \), the formula above gives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
Y = 0.5 a  + \text{&lt;initial value&gt;} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, let’s try to build our own equation then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At time \( t = 0 \), we have 0 EUR overall and our monthly income is \( Y \).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 1 \), we get \( Y \), overall we have \( Y \) and our monthly income becomes \( Y + a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 2 \), we get \( Y + a \), overall \( 2Y + a \), income \( Y + 2a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 3 \), we get \( Y + 2a \), overall \( 3Y + 3a \), income \( Y + 3a \)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\( t = 4 \), we get \( Y + 3a \), overall \( 4Y + 6a \), income \( Y + 4a \)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see the equation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
C = t Y + \text{&lt;something&gt;} \cdot a %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first we add no \( a \), then \( a \), then \( 2a \) and so on.
Thus, this is just a sum
of arithmetic progression. The formula for the general case is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S = (x_1 + x_n) \frac{n}{2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(i.e. sum of the first \( x_1 \) and last \( x_n \) elements multiplied by quantity \( n \) and divided by two).
In our case it is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(0 + t-1) \frac{t}{2} = (t-1)\frac{t}{2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our final formula becomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C = t Y + (t-1)\frac{t}{2} a&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under \( t = 4 \), we get \( 4 Y + 3 \cdot \frac{4}{2} a = 4 Y + 6 a \). Thus, it matches our manual calculations above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;even-further-back&quot;&gt;Even further back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am curious to see how much money one needs to build such FIRE with acceleration (FIRE\(^2\)).
In other words, what kind of safe withdrawal rate one needs for this (could be denotes as SWR\(^2\)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that we want our acceleration to be \( A \) and we start with 0 speed at first.
After the first month we get \( A \) units of money. Under 4% SWR, we would need \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot A \) EUR overall.
After the second month we get \( 2A \) EUR. In the normal FIRE we would need \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 2 \cdot A \) EUR overall
to achieve such withdrawal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this approach does not bring us far. Instead let’s say that in the first month we get \( A_1 \) EUR
and in the second month we want to get \( A_2 = A_1 + 1 \) EUR. This means that after \( A_1 \) our stash
should grow such that it starts producing 1 EUR more. Under 4% SWR one needs \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 1 = 300 \) EUR to
get 1 EUR per month. Thus, \( A_1 \) should be 300 EUR. Now we can try to extend this further.
We want \( A_2 = A_1 + A \) EUR. Thus, \( A_1 \) should be \( 300A \).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider an example. Our monthly FIRE target is \( 300A \) EUR. We have \( 25 \cdot 12 \cdot 300 \cdot A = 300^2 A \) EUR overall.
After the first month we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;300^2 A \cdot \frac{0.04}{12} = 300 A&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reinvest them. Now our stash becomes
\( 300^2 A + 300 A \) EUR. In the second month, we get&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(300^2 A + 300 A) \frac{0.04}{12} = 301 A&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oops, we wanted \( 600 A \). So it feels like the compound interest works differently from the physics motion equation.
Let’s say our principal is \( P \) EUR and it grows by 4% each year, then after \( n \) years we will have
\( P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \).
If we don’t spend anything, our monthly FIRE income after \( n \) years will be \( P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12} \).
In other words, in contrast to the motion equation, here the time \( n \) is in the power. Previously, it was just square multiplied. This is why our analogy breaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we know that \( Y = a t \). We can plug income from the above as \( Y \) here and see the acceleration (for simplicity we switch units to years here):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Y = a n = P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a = \frac{ P \cdot 1.04 ^ n \frac{0.04}{12} }{n}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words the acceleration is not constant, it grows as well.
In some sense, the real 4% is even better than the constant acceleration case above.
If we want \( Y \) to be \( 2A \), we need \( 2 A \cdot 12 \cdot 25 \) EUR stash. 
Let’s say our initial stash supports \( Y = A \), i.e. it is \( 12 \cdot 25 \cdot A \). 
We know that in \( n \) years it will be \( 12 \cdot 25 \cdot A \cdot 1.04 ^ n \). 
Thus, let’s find \( n \), such that \( Y = 2 A \), i.e. the stash of \( 2 * A * 12 * 25 \) EUR.
This is just \( 1.04 ^ n = 2 \), i.e. \( n = 17.673 \) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=1.04%5En+%3D+2&quot;&gt;wolfram alpha&lt;/a&gt;). That’s a long time, but when we want \( Y = 3 A \), \( n \) becomes 28.011.
I.e. the jump from \( Y = 2 A \) to \( Y = 3 A \) takes us ~10 years, while the jump from \( A \) to \( 2 A \) takes 17 years.
For \( 1000 A \), \( n \) is 176.125, while for \( 1001 A \), it is 176.151, i.e. one needs only ~10 days to go from
\( Y = 1000 A \) to \( 1001 A \), because the acceleration of compounding is not constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can visualize this well with a plot. Let’s draw \( Y \) for both cases (linear and compounding):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_10.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
Linear is much higher.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, linear is doing much better job at first. There is not much money to work in the compounding case yet.
However, if we look further right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_100.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 100 on x axis and compounding almost reaches linear.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding starts to reach linear. Even further right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_200.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 200 on x axis and compounding sky-rockets.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And kaboom! Compounding case just skyrockets.
Further to the right, it looks like linear is just flat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fire_squared/comparison_300.png&quot; alt=&quot;A plot showing how monthly FIRE income depends on time assuming linear and compounding growth.
This time we look from 1 to 300 on x axis and linear looks completely flat.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, the fact that acceleration is not constant feels now obvious. 
Basically, when one has more money, compounding growth has more effect, because each euro works separately. 
While in the physics motion equation, the speed is just time multiplied by acceleration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, building such FIRE scheme when one each months gets \( A \) more money
is not possible with the compounding growth. The compounding growth grows
faster than that scheme (it just starts slow).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a bit sad that my attempt to define FIRE\(^2\) and SWR\(^2\) didn’t work out,
because the real thing is in some sense cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-follow-up&quot;&gt;Possible follow-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t workout, because the time goes into power. However, there is a way (logarithm) to move
from exponent to linear. Thus, I could theoretically consider logarithm of the monthly income and try
to do exactly the same.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><summary type="html">Financial Independence / Early Retirement is about reaching a state, in which you get enough passive income to live. Let’s say you get \(Y\) EUR each month. The overall money you get over time is \( M = Y * t \), where \(t\) is time. This resembles a physics equation for movement with constant speed (i.e. no acceleration). Let’s explore this similarity and try to add acceleration to FIRE and get FIRE\(^2\) (FIRE squared, I just made this name up).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Health insurance during FIRE</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/health-insurance-during-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Health insurance during FIRE" /><published>2019-07-23T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-23T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/health_insurance_during_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/health-insurance-during-fire">&lt;p&gt;Health insurance is a very important part of retirement. Let’s see how it 
affects early retirement in Germany. In other words how one should account
for health insurance contribution when planning and by how much this delays
the FIRE date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual FIRE advice aka 4% rule aka Trinity Study says “multiple your yearly expenses by 25 and that’s how much you need”.
It is easy to forget about some implicit expenses though, e.g. taxes and health insurance, which are payed automatically
if you are an employee. Obviously, one has
plenty of time to look into these topics during their saving phase. This is me doing precisely that here.
Thus, let’s see how health insurance in Germany affects one’s FIRE and how to account for this effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;private-vs-public&quot;&gt;Private vs Public&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I am not very familiar with private health insurance in Germany. I’ve heard from multiple sources
that the monthly contributions in the (ordinary) retirement can become high. Overall the concept
looks a bit fishy to me. One pays less and gets a better service. Moreover, the one who referred you
usually gets a couple thousand EUR referral bonus, which also does not fit well with paying less and getting better service.
This is my not that well researched opinion, so if you know more, I would appreciate you sharing your knowledge with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I will consider a public insurance (for simplicity, Techniker Kran­ken­kas­se aka TK, in the worst case one
could switch to TK if they have something different).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tk-contributions&quot;&gt;TK contributions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can have no usual salary-based income during their retirement, but they still have to
pay health insurance contributions. Surprise-surprise. TK has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tk.de/service/app/2002868/beitragsrechner/beitragsrechner.app&quot;&gt;a calculator&lt;/a&gt;,
which supports only employees, self-employed and students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/insurance_during_fire/tk_calculator.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Techniker Kran­ken­kas­se contribution calculator intro-screen asking to choose out of employee, self-employed or student.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Fig. Choose your destiny! Obviously there won’t be a FIRE option with Mr Money Mustache picture…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tk.de/techniker/leistungen-und-mitgliedschaft/beitraege-beitragssaetze/beitragssaetze/tk-beitragssatz-und-zusatzbeitrag-2021472&quot;&gt;another page&lt;/a&gt;, which has&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Weitere Freiwillig Versicherte wie Beamte oder Versicherte ohne Beschäftigung&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the second part is what we are interested in - “insured without employment”.
This finally brings us to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tk.de/techniker/leistungen-und-mitgliedschaft/versicherung/freiwillige-krankenversicherung-tk/haeufige-fragen-zu-beitraegen-fuer-freiwillig-versicherte/beitragshoehe-freiwillig-versichert-nicht-erwerbstaetig-2006970&quot;&gt;the page&lt;/a&gt; with all the details.
There are two components of TK insurance (health Krankenversicherung and long term care Pflegeversicherung).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the health insurance, there are two rates - reduced (ermäßigte Beitragssatz) and general (allgemeine Beitragssatz).
The reduced rate is 14.7%. It applies to capital gain income (Einnahmen aus Kapitalvermögen, Aktien und Ähnlichem).
There are also lower and upper bound contributions - 152.64 and 667.01 EUR respectively per month.
The general rate is 15.3%, but this is irrelevant here, since it does not affect capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the long term care insurance, one pays 3.05% of their income and the contribution bounds are 31.67 &amp;amp; 138.39 EUR per month.
People who are older than 23 and have no children have to pay increased rate of 3.3% (bounds - 34.26 &amp;amp; 149.74 EUR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity (and the worst case scenario), let’s assume that we have no kids (and are older than 23). 
Thus, we already have to pay at least 152.64 (minimum contribution for health insurance) + 34.26 EUR (minimum contribution
for long term case insurance) = 186.90 EUR each month.
This amount will grow if we have large enough capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impact-on-fire&quot;&gt;Impact on FIRE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is already clear that one needs to add at least 186.90 EUR to their FIRE monthly expenses.
Under 4% rule this means saving 186.90 * 12 * 25 = 56070 EUR more than originally planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we will have capital gains too, which may increase the contributions.
Both Krankenversicherung and Pflegeversicherung lower bounds map to 1038 EUR income:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;152.64/0.147 = 1038.36&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;34.26/0.033 = 1038.18&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, once your income crosses 1038 EUR per month, you will have to pay more.
The upper bounds map to 4537 EUR of income:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;667.01/0.147 = 4537.48&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;149.74/0.033 = 4537.57&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a conclusion, unless you go for a fat FIRE, you will have to pay
max(186.90, &amp;lt;capital gains&amp;gt; * (14.7% + 3.3%)) each month for the health and long term care insurances.
As a rough rule of thumb, if you plan to spend X EUR each month during FIRE,
you have to save for X + max(186.90, 0.18*X) to account for the insurances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-go-deeper&quot;&gt;Let’s go deeper.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may feel like we are done, but not yet. The funny fact is that e.g. these 186.90 EUR will in the worst case be included
in your capital gains too. I.e. you will have to pay insurance contributions on your insurance contributions. 
Thus, the real number should be larger. Let’s find it.
So again we want to get X EUR after paying insurance contribution. 
Let’s say we should save Y EUR more to pay for the insurance.
Now we can calculate the insurance contribution in the worst case (when all the money are coming from capital gains).
It is max(186.90, 0.18*(X + Y)). Now we know that after paying the contribution
we want to have X left. Thus, we get an equation. It is (our overall income) - (contribution) = (what we want to be left with):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(X + Y) - max(186.90, 0.18*(X + Y)) = X
Y = max(186.90, 0.18*(X + Y))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we can consider two cases.
Let’s say the max collapses to 186.90. 
This happens when 0.18*(X + Y) &amp;lt;= 186.90, i.e. 0.18*X &amp;lt;= 186.9 - 0.18*Y or X &amp;lt;= 1038.33 - Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// A bit of a side thought here, but I probably should look into using TeX or something…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Y = 186.90, when X &amp;lt;= 1038.33 - Y = 1038.33 - 186.90 = 851.43.
This is a simpler case, since here we don’t technically pay contribution on our contribution,
because we hit the lower bound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then let’s say the max is reduced to the right argument. This means
X &amp;gt; 1038.33 - Y.
In this case Y = 0.18*(X + Y), i.e. 0.82*Y = 0.18*X and Y = 0.2195*X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, now I feel very rigorous. If during your FIRE you planned to have 851.43 EUR or less
monthly without taking into account taxes and insurances, you need to add to that 186.90 EUR,
i.e. X becomes X + 186.90 EUR. This will cover the insurance contribution. 
If your X is larger than 851.43 EUR, then you should have 1.2195*X instead per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the very pessimistic worst case for the insurances (we don’t look at taxes yet,
this is planned for later, the dessert, so to say). In reality our monthly capital gain
won’t be the entire X (especially at first). However, with time it will slowly approach X.
I.e. with time the larger and larger portion of our monthly money will be coming from capital gains
and not from our already taxed savings. This is easy to prove, because 
the non-taxed part grows with time and already-taxed part only gets depleted.
Thus…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lets-go-even-deeper&quot;&gt;Let’s go even deeper.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be dead sure you have enough for insurance, go with saving
for 1.2195*X EUR per month (when your original monthly plan was X).
In other words for each 1000 EUR of free monthly money during FIRE, plan to save for 1219.5 EUR instead.
Or if your FIRE target was 300k EUR, change it to 300k * 1.2195 = 365850 EUR to account for
insurances (worst case upper bound).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is a very big deal. This definitely means saving couple years more.
Thus, if we can get a more real and lower estimate, this would be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, getting this estimate is very non-trivial.
There are multiple forces at play - growth of capital, First-In-First-Out order of selling.
E.g. your older investments will likely have more capital gains then your fresher ones, 
but you will have to sell the older ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, having a simple spreadsheet here happende to be not feasible and I will have to write a proper
javascript calculator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TODO: write a calculator to get more realistic estimate for how much more one needs to save
to account for insurances during FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issues-with-my-approach&quot;&gt;Issues with my approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This can change gazillion times before one actually FIREs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taxes will have their impact, so to be 100% correct one needs to take them into account as well.
I plan another series of posts about taxes in FIRE, so addressing this issue may become a part of it. Let’s see.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perhaps there exist better selling strategies. Does one have to sell a little bit each month?
Could it be better to hit the upper bound once and then pay the lower bound contribution?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say your FIRE target is X EUR without taking into account insurances and taxes.
If you want to account for insurances, your FIRE target should become at most 1.2195 * X EUR.
This is the worst case scenario, which assumes entire monthly amount coming from capital gains
in Germany with TK insurance. I.e. this is an upper bound. In reality it may be somewhat
lower. Stay tuned to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;peculiar-question-of-morality&quot;&gt;Peculiar question of morality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing this, I’ve thought for a bit about morality of such somewhat low insurance
contributions during FIRE.
Basically one can end up paying ~200 EUR per month for the same service.
However, don’t forget that you already payed insurance contributions from your salary
while you were saving the money. Thus, if you average your contributions over your life,
it will likely end up being comparable to working entire life without FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy staying healthy during FIRE (and taking into account all the bits and pieces)!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Germany&quot;, &quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;, &quot;Simulations&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><summary type="html">Health insurance is a very important part of retirement. Let’s see how it affects early retirement in Germany. In other words how one should account for health insurance contribution when planning and by how much this delays the FIRE date.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Delaying capital gains taxes during saving for FIRE phase</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying-capital-gains-in-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Delaying capital gains taxes during saving for FIRE phase" /><published>2019-07-21T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-21T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying_capital_gains_in_FIRE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying-capital-gains-in-fire">&lt;p&gt;It is common knowledge that one should delay realizing their capital gains as much
as possible (especially when aiming for Financial Independence / Early Retirement).
Let’s focus on the phase, when one saves for FIRE, and see the magnitude of the effect
of such a delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own unique situation. This post is based on a number of assumptions,
thus, don’t rely on it as is. Have a look at the assumption and see how well this applies 
to your situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly known that usually one should delay realizing their investment capital gains
as much as possible to increase their returns. Basically, instead of just paying the tax now, one can
temporarily keep it and continue getting investment growth (compounding) out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simulation&quot;&gt;Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example of Annet.
We will use the following assumptions about Annet and her life:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lives in Germany&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pays German capital gain tax and always 26.375% (25% tax itself &amp;amp; additional 5.5% of it as solidarity tax)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has other income, i.e. the capital gain tax is never reduced to progressive income tax.
This is a strong assumption, but not for the collection phase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;never uses 801 tax-free capital gain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no dividends and no tax prepayment (this is different from the current German system)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;starts from 0 in January 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(the strongest assumption) the market always has constant yearly and monthly returns.
I use 4% return per year or equivalently 0.32737% per month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;earns 2k EUR and invests 1k EUR each month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We assume that Annet contributes 1000 EUR every month.
Her investment growths by 0.32737% at the end of every month.
I.e. she has 0 at 1st of January 2019. She invests 1000 in the end of January.
In the end of February her 1000 grow into 1003.27 and she invests another 1000,
thus, having 2003.27 pre-tax overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we compare 2 options. The first option is delaying realizing capital gains as
much as possible. Basically she never sells until becoming FIRE. At that point, she will pay 26.375% on her
capital gains. The second option is realizing capital gains as fast as possible (every month, alternatively
having only distributing ETFs).
Basically, once her 1000 grow into 1003.27, she immediately sells them (or receives dividends)
and buys the same asset again. While doing this, she pays 26.375% tax on the growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This is just a simplified model. Re-buying the same asset might be considered a wash sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also normally one does not sell everything after becoming FIRE, but here we
assume this to be able to compare the two approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve prepared &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/11iki1iPJawRdpLVxPoIGkBx0Oq5MowwRENDcuVZvbRQ/edit&quot;&gt;a Google Spreadsheet with the calculation&lt;/a&gt;. You can play with it by making a copy first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to 4% rule, her FIRE target is 300k. 
In the first case, she reaches 300k (after tax) in 222 months (July 2037) and pre-tax she has
327k. In the second case she has only 294k EUR at this point (i.e. 1.7% less).
She needs 4 more months (1.8%) to reach 300k EUR post-tax in the second case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-case&quot;&gt;General case&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above we considered only one particular setting. Now let’s have a look how the two cases differ
under various yearly investment returns and time horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/delaying_capital_gains/difference_based_on_return.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing them monthly) depends on number of months invested and yearly return on
investment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, for 7% yearly return and 30 years, the difference crosses 12%, which is a substantial amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-research&quot;&gt;Further research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible improvements of the simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;take into account 801 EUR capital gain tax free every year.
This won’t affect the result too much though as we have already seen
in 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/801-tax-free-capital-gains&quot;&gt;my previous post about tax-free 801 EUR per year&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, this can improve the second case (realizing gains immediately),
but at most 801 * 0.26375 = 211.26 EUR per year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;look into FIRE spending phase, which is much more dependent on capital gains.
In this simulation we pretended that we send everything once one reaches FIRE
to compare the two cases. In reality that’s not true. In this case not-realized
capital gains will have even more time to grow, thus, this should make
the difference even larger.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;take into account capital gain tax becoming progressive income tax.
Finally, this should reduce the tax paid after FIRE substantially.
Basically, if one has no or little income and their progressive income tax is less
than 25%, they don’t pay 25% on their capital gains either (but their income
tax instead).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;using real market data. Currently I just assume 4% per year growth, which
ignores sequence of returns completely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;taking into account yearly tax prepayment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will address some of these in my follow-up posts, stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delaying your capital gains matters less than I expected (1.7% difference under 50% saving rate and 4% yearly return case).
However, since by default you don’t realize them, it is better not to do anything extra and just don’t lose these 1.7%.
Overall, 1.7% (or even more if the yearly return is larger than 4%) can be a reasonable sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally one can be forced to realize their capital gains (e.g. an accumulating ETFs gets closed or 
changes its internal structure). Based on the numbers above, it makes sense to try to avoid this to some extent
(e.g. buying same ETFs from different providers).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Simulations&quot;, &quot;Germany&quot;, &quot;Investing&quot;, &quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><category term="taxes" /><summary type="html">It is common knowledge that one should delay realizing their capital gains as much as possible (especially when aiming for Financial Independence / Early Retirement). Let’s focus on the phase, when one saves for FIRE, and see the magnitude of the effect of such a delay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to disable notifications prompt in Chrome?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications-prompt-in-chrome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to disable notifications prompt in Chrome?" /><published>2019-07-16T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications_prompt_in_chrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications-prompt-in-chrome">&lt;p&gt;Numerous sites ask for permission “to show notifications”.
Some of them even obstruct the site itself unless ones makes a choice in this permission prompt.
Pressing “no” multiple times a day (with a probability to eventually misclick “yes”)
sounds like wasting of time. Fortunately, there is a way in Chrome
to say “no” by default (i.e. disable this prompts completely and never see them again).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/notifications_in_chrome/reddit_problem.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Reddit blacking out the website until one closes the 
notification prompt.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open chrome://settings/content/notifications and disable “Ask before sending (recommended)”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final result:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/notifications_in_chrome/solution.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Chrome settings with this notification prompt (finally!) disabled.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively in order to reach this screen you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to Chrome Settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for “notifications” or go to Advanced &amp;gt; Privacy and Security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose Site Settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open “Notifications”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;funny-story-from-my-life&quot;&gt;Funny story from my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I misclicked “yes” on some random website, which I opened only once. You can imagine my face when I noticed
a very weird pop-up notification some day after. I completely forgot about this website.
Obviously, I thought that I had some malware, but somehow I ended up checking notification permissions.
Yeap, that site was there. To be honest, I still don’t remember clicking “yes”, so I just assume that I misclicked.
This was the last drop for me to disable these prompts for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy browsing without useless distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;How-to&quot;]" /><category term="howto" /><category term="Chrome" /><summary type="html">Numerous sites ask for permission “to show notifications”. Some of them even obstruct the site itself unless ones makes a choice in this permission prompt. Pressing “no” multiple times a day (with a probability to eventually misclick “yes”) sounds like wasting of time. Fortunately, there is a way in Chrome to say “no” by default (i.e. disable this prompts completely and never see them again).</summary></entry></feed>