<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-10T23:26:54+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Overview of this blog’s life in 2019 and plans for 2020</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/blog-summary-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overview of this blog's life in 2019 and plans for 2020" /><published>2020-01-05T14:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-05T14:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/blog_summary_2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/blog-summary-2019">&lt;p&gt;I’ve got an idea to start a blog in the end of 2018 and published the first post
in the early January of 2019. In other words, this blog is now kind of one year old.
This was not my New Year resolution, but somehow it worked out.
Let’s reflect a bit, see some stats and what I am going to do differently in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest I don’t remember precisely why I wanted to start this blog. It was probably an attempt
to express myself, see what other people find interesting. However, with time these intentions
mutated greatly. Currently I consider a blog as a nice lever for doing stuff I like.
When I have an idea, I can not only do it, but also write about it on the blog
and this increases the impact of my idea. Moreover, I do enjoy writing itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;proposed-changes&quot;&gt;Proposed changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this blog is a living organism on its own and I constantly experiment
with my approach to it. And I definitely want to continue doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second part of 2019 I have adopted two posts per week schedule.
My hope was that this would make the blog more interesting to regular readers.
I also usually scheduled 1 hour per post for writing and ~30 minutes for after-baking
modifications (if you are confused by “baking”, I’ve described the process 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/how-i-write-this-blog&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). And as people often say -
“you get what you measure”. As a result, many of my posts are rather short and somewhat shallow.
I did do a couple posts which took much longer than allocated and I did enjoy working on them a lot
(e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;/post/luckiest-investor-or-investing-when-knowing-the-future&quot;&gt;luckiest investor&lt;/a&gt;).
Also it looked like others found such posts more interesting as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I am going to try to have no schedule from now on.
As well as no time allocation per post. This means that I may “disappear” for longer,
but eventually come back with much deeper posts (and hopefully of better quality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way I hope to preserve the part of the blog which I like (writing deep posts
and exploring the topic well) and to get rid of less interesting parts (having to post something
twice a week). The former was always a pure flow. The latter definitely felt like a chore sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I somewhat implicitly used to optimize for quantity. Quality might
have been implicitly sacrificed. Again, this was all implicit, I just wanted regularity.
Now I will try to optimize for quality and very likely quantity will suffer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;expected-challenges&quot;&gt;Expected challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already see one possible issue with my new approach. 
I am quite a perfectionist and having strict deadlines helps me to fight that.
However, without a schedule, I might polish a post forever.
I am not sure how to counter that, perhaps some upper bound time limit
per post. In any case, I will try to split the posts into smaller chunks
and to publish them sooner this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;topics&quot;&gt;Topics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also hope that the new approach will change topic allocation of my posts.
Due to allocated time limit in 2019 I often did write personal reflections on 
various topics. This is not bad per-se, but it is often very anecdotal,
doesn’t have any proof and not that rigorous. I hope that with the new approach
I will do more coding, simulations, deep rigorous posts with citations and
sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stats&quot;&gt;Stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, now let’s look back and see how 2019 went for this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started time tracking in March and overall I spent at least 120 hours since then.
This is clean time (i.e. just me actively doing something blog related) and might be a lower
bound. This also includes various non-writing activities, e.g. Jekyll related fixes, actually posting stuff,
updating twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, this feels less than I expected.
Overall there were 76 posts in 2019, 8 of which were before March.
Thus, we are left with 68 posts in 120 hours or 1 hour 45 minutes per post.
Funny enough this matches very closely my time allocation of 1 hour for writing
and ~0.5 hour for after-baking corrections. Unfortunately, I don’t have time tracking with per 
post granularity, but I definitely remember that there was a lot of variation.
Some posts did take 7-10 hours (very few though), some more like 10-20 minutes.
After-baking fixes often took 5-10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s now analyze the posts themselves and build various graphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-counts&quot;&gt;Post counts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at posts published over day of week, we definitely see my chosen Tuesday - Sunday schedule.
Closer to the end of the year, I replaced Sunday with “weekend”, so that explains the Saturday’s value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/1_posts_per_day_of_week.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bar plot of #posts published per day of week&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking per month only October is unusual. Unfortunately I was traveling and didn’t have much chance to write.
It is peculiar to observe me ramping up in January and February and reaching steady state in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/2_posts_per_month.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bar plot of #posts published per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at number of posts published per day for the entire year, we can definitely
see how I started with no schedule and then in March switched to 2 posts per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/3_posts_per_day.png&quot; alt=&quot;Calendar histogram #posts published per day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;characters-published&quot;&gt;Characters published&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity I just look at file sizes, which may be different from number of characters one observes
on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at average post size in characters per day of week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/4_average_characters_per_day_of_week.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bar plot of average #characters per post per day of week&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow magically Thursday happens to have the longest average post.
Actually there are only 2 posts on Thursdays - 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/underestimating-ter&quot;&gt;“Underestimating TER”&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-7-true-happiness&quot;&gt;“Thought experiment #7 about true happiness”&lt;/a&gt;
, both of which are 11-12k characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The longest post is &lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;the review of “The science of wellbeing” course&lt;/a&gt;. 34411 characters, I am not surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shortest one is about &lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee&quot;&gt;interactive brokers monthly fee&lt;/a&gt;, 1657 characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The median is &lt;a href=&quot;/post/book-summary-the-dip&quot;&gt;the summary of “The dip”&lt;/a&gt; with
7505 characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at a histogram of post sizes, we can see that almost all posts are up to ~15k characters
with only few outliers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/5_post_sizes_histogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Histogram of post sizes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a look at characters published per day over entire year:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/blog_summary_2019/6_characters_per_day.png&quot; alt=&quot;Calendar histogram #characters published per day&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some variation, but nothing peculiar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;words&quot;&gt;Words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top 10 most common words with their occurrence counts (case sensitive):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘to’ - 2970&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘the’ - 2749&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘and’ - 2028&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘a’ - 1940&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘is’ - 1925&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘I’ - 1815&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘of’ - 1715&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘you’ - 1358&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘in’ - 1278&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘this’ - 1161&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny that there is so much “I”, but fortunately “you” is not that far back.
This quite matches the general distributing in English (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Wiktionary:Frequency_lists/PG/2006/04/1-10000&quot;&gt;Wiktionary&lt;/a&gt;). There you get 1.94 “I” for each “you”, 
while in this blog it is 1.33. In other words, it is more about you than an average English text. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I suspect that I sometimes don’t use “the” where I should (the count is lower
than on average in English).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some notable mentions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘time’, 450 occurrences, rank 27 vs 69 in English&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘people’, 369, rank 40 vs 135&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘something’, 259, rank 63 vs 219 (I should try using this less frequently)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘FIRE’, 218, rank 69 vs 351 (for ‘fire’)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘life’, 206, rank 74 vs 114&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘money’, 159, rank 96 vs 271&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this illustrates well what this blog is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;popularity&quot;&gt;Popularity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post with the most unique pageviews is 
about &lt;a href=&quot;/post/interactive-brokers-fixed-vs-tiered-commissions&quot;&gt;fixed vs tiered Interactive Brokers commissions&lt;/a&gt;.
It also has the largest average time spent on the page.
Somehow people find this topic very interesting.
I myself was also confused by all the intricate details and that’s why I decided to write the post
in the first place. I definitely didn’t expect it to become that relatively popular.
It also gets the most interest in search engines and badly dominates all
search clicks and queries. What a peculiar world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The runner up in unique pageviews is &lt;a href=&quot;/post/luckiest-investor-or-investing-when-knowing-the-future&quot;&gt;luckiest investor&lt;/a&gt;.
This one was peculiar and I did expect it to pique some interest.
This post also became my by far &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/investing/comments/cmnbyb/the_luckiest_investor_of_2018_or_how_much_you/&quot;&gt;most popular post on Reddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;afterword&quot;&gt;Afterword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is 2019 for “Merely Curious”.
I am definitely looking forward to build similar graphs for 2020 after getting rid of publishing schedule.
There must be much less structure there and, thus, observations to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to you all for motivating me!
You are very welcome to contact me, I am definitely not overwhelmed
by reader communication at this point.
See my email and twitter below.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; would do too if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy 2020 with plenty of beautiful stats!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’ve got an idea to start a blog in the end of 2018 and published the first post in the early January of 2019. In other words, this blog is now kind of one year old. This was not my New Year resolution, but somehow it worked out. Let’s reflect a bit, see some stats and what I am going to do differently in 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 14)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-14-limbic-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 14)" /><published>2019-12-21T13:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-21T13:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_14_limbic_system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-14-limbic-system">&lt;p&gt;Limbic System. Finally we get closer to emotions and this gets super interesting fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limbic system is a part of brain, which is involved in emotions, but does not get much interest e.g. in
medical schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rats olfactory bulb is a large part of the brain. Its signals are processed in limbic system. Rat’s emotional
world is driven by olfactory information. In birds it is more based on sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;triune-brain-model&quot;&gt;Triune brain model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ancient, archaic part. Hypothalamus talks to pituitary, so called reptilian part. It is responsible for purely
automatic regulation. E.g. monitors and controls temperature, blood pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Ondine’s curse - stroke damage to this area. As a result no capacity for automatic breathing. Affected
person dies of sleep deprivation. One can’t fall asleep, because then they don’t breathe and get at
the edge of asphyxiation and wake up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[On top] Limbic system - mostly mammalian.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[On top] Cortex. Greatly expanded in primates and especially in humans. Cortex can be influenced by other two
systems or influence them (e.g. emotional/physiological response after thinking about future death).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;subparts-of-limbic-system&quot;&gt;Subparts of limbic system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say that parts are &lt;em&gt;connected&lt;/em&gt;, when neurons located in that part have axons in the other part (i.e. this area
&lt;em&gt;projects&lt;/em&gt; into the other area).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entire limbic system is structured around how to influence hypothalamus. Each part tries to inhibit other parts
and tell hypothalamus what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fewer hops (synapses in-between) to hypothalamus some projection has, the better control that part has
(faster, neurons downstream don’t affect the signal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olfactory system is the only system, which is only 1 synapse away from limbic system. All other sensory
systems have minimum 3 synapses (e.g. layer responsible for detecting dots and lines in visual signal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amygdala - cluster of neurons. Means almond in Greek. Responsible for fear, anxiety, aggression. 
Thus, there is connection between fear and aggression. Also covers male sexual motivation. This partially explains
why one can confuse sex behavior and aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Septum - inhibits aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypocampus - handles memory &amp;amp; turns off stress response. This combination (memory &amp;amp; stress) in one center is
important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;saving how you got away from a stress situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when ending up in the same situation, retrieving how you fixed it last time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mammillary bodies - maternal behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PFC - cortical component of limbic system. It is responsible for impulse control, postponing gratification,
long-term planning, learning appropriate sexual behavior, how not to be aggressive and when to be.
PFC is larger in humans (that’s what makes us humans). It is only recently evolved and
also the last part of the brain to fully mature (not fully myelinated until mid 20s).
Best predictor for ratio of PFC over entire brain is size of species social group. I.e. PFC is important
for gossip, social intelligence, appropriate behavior.
Part of PFC is anterior cingulate - empathy (related to clinical depression).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VFA - depression, release dopamine -&amp;gt; pleasure. All addictive drugs (e.g. cocaine) affect this area.
This activates when you anticipate getting pleasure (i.e. not getting the reward itself, but just
anticipation). As a result, this powers the behavior to get the reward.
Motivation for pursuing pleasure is more addictive than pleasure itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypothalamus - sexual behavior. Size depends on sexual orientation (e.g. transgender people have
configuration of self-identified gender).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FCN - circadian rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PT - makes CRH, i.e. stress response. All other parts send projections here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LHT - hunger. Measures glucose and insulin in blood. Also hunger for other rewards than food, e.g. other types 
of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ways-to-study-limbic-system&quot;&gt;Ways to study limbic system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Evolution is not an inventor, it is a tinkerer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warfare is a good source of subjects for brain experiments (there are often casualties, which lead to removal
of parts of the brain). After a war, neuroscientists get their careers jump-started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. patient NA, who had their septum taken out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;N.A. has been amnesic since 1960 when at the age of 22 years he sustained a penetrating brain injury with a miniature fencing foil.
Source: Description of brain injury in the amnesic patient N.A. based on magnetic resonance imaging. Squire LR et al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frontal lobotomy - “intentional” brain damage (e.g. cutting off limbic structures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gray matter - nuclei, cell bodies, white matter - cables of axons wrapped in myelin (they do actually
have these colors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experimental animals - destroy part of the brain, look what does not work anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put an electrode in a brain region and stimulate it (i.e. provide an input signal there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put a recording electrode and see when that area is excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays it is possible to record one neuron and even one ion channel of a neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way one can find out which parts of the brain send their signals into a particular area and how many
hops it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imaging brain regions (CT scan, CAT, MRI, functional brain imaging).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;difficulties&quot;&gt;Difficulties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hard to distinguish centers from fibers of passage. I.e. did one destroy a center responsible for some
function or a passage which carries this signal? One can imagine that we want to find out source
of garlic, that brings garlic to Stanford. And we can do this only by carpet-bombing. Eventually garlic
stops coming to the campus. Did we destroy the garlic farm or a highway?
Sometimes fibers can pass very close to nuclei (no way to destroy only one of them).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is a center in the brain? Everything is highly intermixed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You need to know your species (i.e. to know ethology). 
Let’s say you put stimulating electrode and observe a lion extending its claw.
When you do the same to a human, they start cursing. I.e. this is irritation
and lion just expressed it this way. Another example is a rat running around and
collecting pieces of a newspaper. When the same is done to a rhesus monkey,
it grabs something cylindrical and hugs it. This is nursing behavior.
It is also difficult to distinguish aggression from food acquisition (e.g. a rat attacking a mouse after
a stimulation). This can also vary across individuals even in the same species, e.g. in case of portraying dominance,
a subordinate won’t do power display (even when this area is stimulated).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;james-lange-theory-of-emotion&quot;&gt;James-Lange theory of emotion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stimulus comes into brain. Before brain processes it, your body already responds (e.g. increased heart rate).
How do you figure out which emotion you feel? Your brain looks at changes in your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an old experiment, where adrenalin was given to people without them knowing it (nowadays this
wouldn’t be allowed). Then people sit in waiting room. There is an accomplice. For one group,
the accomplice is pissed off. For another group - happy and friendly. People in the experiment
just overtook the emotion. I.e. adrenalin mediates emotion you socially observe. It does not cause
a concrete behavior, but exaggerates the emotional state provoked externally (i.e. like Gaba inhibition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, one can affect emotional state by affection body. E.g. when one is anxious, they get valium.
When one needs to relax muscles, they get something similar. I.e. to get rid of anxiety, one needs to relax,
since anxiety is based on feedback from muscle tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same with aggression. E.g. let’s say your significant other pissed you off. Then they apologize and you
accept the apology. Cognitively you have resolved the conflict, but your body is still in pissed off state.
It takes time to change the state. You can easily fall back into being angry due to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same can work other way around, e.g. meditation &amp;amp; biofeedback for blood pressure control. One can find trigger
(e.g. a pleasant thought), which decreases blood pressure and by using it, make the effect even stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a gender difference in how long it takes to get back to baseline (including after orgasm) - males
faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take someone in depression, force them to smile mechanically repetitively. Eventually they will start feeling better
due to this body-emotion feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;misc&quot;&gt;Misc&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peculiar motor system inefficiency. When you want to bend one particular finger, there is a system which
tells all 5 of them to bend. Then there is another system which tells other fingers: “if you receive command
‘bend’, ignore it”. This shows evolution of these systems. Many species don’t need to bend one finger, thus,
they have a system for bending all fingers (e.g. claw) at the same time. It was “easier” to add an add-on 
to allow bending one finger instead of redesigning everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some regions change size with time. Amygdala gets bigger in people with post traumatic stress disorder.
In people with long term major depression, hippocampus get smaller (atrophy).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Limbic System. Finally we get closer to emotions and this gets super interesting fast.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 13)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-13-advanced-neurology-and-endocrinology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 13)" /><published>2019-12-17T07:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-17T07:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_13_advanced_neurology_and_endocrinology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-13-advanced-neurology-and-endocrinology">&lt;p&gt;Advanced Neurology and Endocrinology. Basically we consider simplifications made during the last two
lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 3 last lectures, everything was very simple and smooth. Let’s now see ways in which everything is more
complex than it seemed (e.g. what was omitted, simplified).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuro and endocrine systems can change their function over time in many ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cells in pituitary gland are specialized (each produces only one hormone). However, they are mixed in terms
of location (i.e. not clustered). Moreover, how strongly a given cell reacts depends on its neighborhood.
Brain can use this to control the production better (i.e. target only specific cells in specific
neighborhood). This means that there is a communication across cells in pituitary to achieve the neighborhood
differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dales-laws&quot;&gt;Dale’s laws&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two of them, both have been disproved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First: action potential of a neuron starts in its body and causes neurotransmitters to be released from every
single terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;False, you can get blockades, which prevent signal propagation in some branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second: each neuron has one and only one characteristic type of neurotransmitter, that it releases through all
its terminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are examples of multiple neurotransmitters in the same neuron. Peculiarly in this case every single axon terminal
contains both types of neurotransmitters (i.e. there is no division across axon terminals). There are even
examples of 3 neurotransmitters in one neuron. Usually one neurotransmitter has short effect and the other - long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-ways-to-trigger-same-hormone-production&quot;&gt;Multiple ways to trigger same hormone production&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACTH in pituitary gland can be produced due to receiving CRH or many other hormones. Brain can create different
mixtures of these. This affects the shape of ACTH production curve. It also has additional effects (i.e. not
only produces ACTH). There are also hormones inhibiting ACTH production. E.g. when one goes to sleep,
there is no need for stress hormones. Hormone profile released to produce ACTH during stress due to thinking
about “mortality” differs from stress when “burning big toe”. I.e. by having different “cocktails” the brain is
able to react differently to different stress situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantity-regulation-feedback-loops&quot;&gt;Quantity regulation (feedback loops)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neuron&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autoreceptor - a receptor at the axon on the neuron, which binds the same neurotransmitter this neuron produces.
Every time the receptor binds something, neuron “concludes” “I released N neurotransmitter
units” (i.e. counts in a statistical way). This enables a negative feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hormones&quot;&gt;Hormones&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain also measures how much of a specific hormone there is in blood. Thus, there must be brain areas counting specific
hormones. Then it can inhibit hormone production when there is enough of it (negative feedback loop). Most
feedback works by “the more of a given hormone I observe, the more I inhibit”, i.e. inhibition is proportional
to an absolute number. However, there are examples when a rate of change is measured instead. I.e. the 
faster the rate of change is, the stronger the inhibition is. In this case, increase from 10 to 12 &amp;amp;
from 10M to 12M cause the same level of inhibition. This happens at a level of pituitary gland, not brain.
Measuring rate of change is a non-obvious approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also examples of positive feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;autoregulation&quot;&gt;Autoregulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone constantly screams at you, you stop paying attention to them. Cells do the same to hormones.
If there is too much of some hormone, they decrease number of its receptors to become less sensitive.
This can happen when system fails. This may be related to depression, however people still don’t know whether
depressions is due to too much or too little serotonin (because the mechanism is so complex).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diabetes&quot;&gt;Diabetes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You eat sugar, glucose ends up in blood. Pancreas secretes insulin to tell fat cells to capture sugar
from the blood. Fat cells are already full (due to western diet) and they can’t take more sugar, so they
ignore the signal. Pancreas secretes even more insulin to compensate. Fat cells decrease number of receptors.
You get a feedback loop. Fat cells become less and less sensitive and pancreas produces more and more insulin.
Eventually pancreas “burns” its insulin producing mechanism and can’t produce it anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amount of the messenger is as important as cells sensitivity to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;variability-in-receptor-structure&quot;&gt;Variability in receptor structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ligand - whatever the receptor binds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receptors consist of proteins, thus, are encoded using multiple genes. This creates variability. Cells can
change subunits of their receptors. This changes how well receptor does its job. E.g. an epilepsy can be
caused by cells reacting too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corticosteroids have cell type specific functions (due to having variability in subunits on the other end
of the receptor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;variability-in-receptor-triggers&quot;&gt;Variability in receptor triggers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many receptors can bind more than one ligand.
E.g. Gaba binds Gaga. It is inhibitory.
It also binds the following 3 things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;major tranquilizers (barbiturates) - that’s how anesthesia works&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;minor tranquilizers (Valium &amp;amp; Librium) - inhibits not that much&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;derivatives of progesterone - this has been used as anesthesia in 1950s. This may be related to mood shifts
over the course of reproductive cycle. Premenstrual syndrome = shortage of progesterone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;modulation&quot;&gt;Modulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine two neurons A &amp;amp; B. A sends signal to B. When Gaba inhibits, it actually does not affect B (i.e.
how it reacts to the signal). Instead it affects terminals of A (i.e. its ability to impact B). Thus,
Gaba has effect only when A is triggered. Tranquilizers have the same modulation effect on Gaba. I.e.
they have any impact only when Gaba already has some effect (i.e. A is triggered).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hormones can do modulation too. E.g. CRH + Vasopressin can produce much more ACTH than just CRH alone, but
Vasopressin alone produces very little ACTH. Thus, Vasopressin just modulates effect of CRH and does not
trigger ACTH production on its own. Thus, it has effect only when CRH has effect.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Advanced Neurology and Endocrinology. Basically we consider simplifications made during the last two lectures.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #9: brave new world with all needs met</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-9-brave-new-world-with-all-needs-met" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #9: brave new world with all needs met" /><published>2019-12-15T07:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-15T07:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_9_brave_new_world_with_all_needs_met</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-9-brave-new-world-with-all-needs-met">&lt;p&gt;Thought experiment #9 about a magical planet where all your needs are met by a magical entity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, I am actually looking forward to the next thought experiment and feel pretty excited
before starting to write (even though I haven’t read it yet). I think I got a habit now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“How will you live in a brave new world?” from the tweet sounds very interesting.
It reminds me of Brave New World by Aldous Huxley. Now I am actually pretty sure that they
two are connected. Look, all 3 words are the same. Hm… Let’s have a look inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-statement&quot;&gt;The statement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You’ve arrived at Firearto, better known as ‘Earth 2.0’, an exo planet located over 200,000 light years away. As you walk down the exit corridor of your spaceship along with another million colonizers you think to yourself: What will I do here? Firearto is a planet that has no monetary system, all of your needs are provided for by FSY (Firearto Space Corp). How will you live your life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment page is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/a-brave-new-world&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and it has links to other answers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-answer&quot;&gt;My answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WTH?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is like Universal Basic Income, but without money?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a little bit more of explanation would be helpful. What confuses me is that it is hard to 
imagine such no money system. Is it like communism? Or I don’t have to work? Somehow from the text
it looks like no work is required. Can I have different needs from others? What if I want more than others?
Tricky…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more freedom and vagueness we have, the more unique and personal our response can be.
So let’s happily start reducing all this ambiguity. 
Many of us are united by the idea of Financial Independence, so I assume that the thought experiment
is at least somewhat about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;all of your needs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is boring to assume that this literally means “any” need. First, I could just go to this magical entity and ask for anything,
so there is not much to write about here. Second, this is hard to imagine in practice (yeah, I may have peculiar needs).
Third, if anything is available so easily, life will probably be quite boring. No goals to reach, no targets to hit, no
competition. It is actually funny to understand that I do enjoy this part of life. Before writing that I would have struggled
with claiming so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we say “all of your &lt;em&gt;basic&lt;/em&gt; needs” are covered. So we have shelter, food, basic fun probably. Oh, it is very hard not
to regress to something-like-money system. I immediately think about people having different needs. Perhaps I want more
books and other people like movies more. Thus, there should be some balance, which gets reduced with each need satisfied.
And, abracadabra, we just implemented money. Sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so we assume that everyone gets the same and somehow magically there are ways to request additional stuff.
E.g. if I want to do wood carving, I can hypothetically get the materials and tools. As you noticed above I have
no clue how to preserve fairness in such a system, but this thought experiment is about me doing stuff and not
designing such a system. Thus, I just ignore this inconsistency. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, but doesn’t then the question just become “what would you do if you were fat FI on a different planet”?
Like I have access to resources (e.g. requesting wood carving tools), it is not that limited (i.e. not a lean FI),
but I am just on a different planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we back to square one. What does this planet have to offer? If it is all just metal rooms without anything,
then it is quite tricky to live there. If it is exactly like Earth, then the answer is completely different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought for a moment that I could read comments in the Twitter, perhaps someone tried to clarify, but there are none
and it would be a spoiler. I could also ask SavingNinja in a private message, but I feel lazy to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, time to enable “thinking - no, writing - yes” mode and just go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No money raises an interesting question of motivation. Currently many people (including me) do a lot of stuff and
spend great portions of their lives being driven by money. This is not per-se bad. This new planet completely removes
this incentive (somewhat similarly to FIRE, but there it is only partially removed, since more money = smaller chances to run
out of money). For someone who is very work driven, such change can be dramatic. Many people experience this on Earth
when going into their retirement. So-called empty desk syndrome. I don’t think I am affected much. My money pursuits are motivated by
FIRE and I am trying to build my FIRE life still while working. I.e. I want to have enough activities, so that 
when I get more free time once I am FIRE, these activities just naturally fill the free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I am tempted to say that I would try to live on that planet the same way as I plan to leave on Earth during FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, not yet, I could probably elaborate a bit more on the details. But this will just boil down to how to be happy.
I am now super curious what others will write and how they will understand the question. Looking forward to reading that.
It will likely be something very different from mine and I will be like “oh, how I could have missed this way to
understand the statement, it is indeed so easy and makes sense”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There still can be competition, it just won’t be motivated by money much, but instead by self-improvement and being
better than others. In some sense that’s what sport is meant to be doing. So there will be a lot of sport (often
non-physical) on that planet. Not sure whether I will participate much in the actual sport, but I will definitely 
find some hobby in which I will try to get as best as I can and which I enjoy. Becoming the best is usually not 
enough - there is always someone who is better than you, because they have spent plenty of time on it and
are probably naturally inclined to excel in that activity (aka talent). I am a fan of growth mindset, but still people
vary and e.g. one’s height matters in basketball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from that I will try to form a lot of relationships. Probably with people interested in the same hobby and
just people whose company I enjoy in general. At least on Earth this seems to affect my happiness greatly. So I assume
that there it will be the same. Having basic needs satisfied by a magic entity is quite good for forming romantic relationships.
Often ways of satisfying needs (or having different needs) can become a source of conflict. E.g. if one person likes
one kind of food and other likes something different, it may be tricky for them to live together.
To be honest I struggle to come up with a good example of such kinds of food. But if you take the food out of equation,
they just eat what this entity provides, then they can enjoy other qualities of each other. E.g. they could be a perfect
match in all other categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I will also continue learning. Probably try to do some research. Even though this magic entity providing all the
basic needs seems to be quite powerful, I don’t think that humanity will ever solve all the research. It would be pretty
weird to at some point say: “Oh, we have researched everything, we are done”. Somehow it feels like there is no
end and one will always be able to improve something or discover something new. Obviously no proof here, just random
speculations. Some deep research always feels like a connection to nature for me. In many areas you solve problems
which other people created. These feel somewhat artificial. In research you may be touching problems in some sense
created by nature. This can then be perceived as you are a part of humanity, i.e. one entity competing with nature.
This looks intrinsically beautiful. It is not some artificial problem created by someone else, it is something
deep and intrinsic instead. Thus, if you take away money, this intrinsic beauty should become so much more important.
This can be a powerful source for finding meaning in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a bit scary to get lazy and start fulfilling all my needs without a limit. E.g. one can crave fatty or sugary foods.
Does it mean that one should eat them? Probably not. If all needs can be met, it is much easier to give up to such desires
and just start fulfilling them. Also postponing something for tomorrow might be a problem. Why doing something today if you can
do it later? I think the answer is “no reason, if you don’t want to, i.e. there is no intrinsic motivation”. The first issue
is not that prominent in FIRE due to limited resources and in some sense I am exposed to this now. I could eat plenty of 
sweet and fatty stuff already now, but I don’t. For the latter, it is hard to say. For intrinsically motivated stuff,
I will do it just because I want to do it now. For other, I probably just won’t do it at all then. I assume that there won’t
be any stuff which one has to do, since their needs are met. This also illustrated FI well. While not FI one has to work
because one needs to satisfy their basic needs. After FI, one just needs to take care of themselves (still satisfying basic
needs but on a different level), apart from that they are free to do whatever. E.g. they can lay in bed for days just because
they feel so. Probably a stupid example, but I like it, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely interesting to see this connection between life on this magic planet and FIRE. I am now even curious
whether SavingNinja intended it this way. “Let’s ask them what they will be doing during their FIRE in a very implicit way”.
A bit “disappointed” that this has nothing to do with Huxley’s book. But the book was quite sad and dark, so I am happy
that this experiment is not like that. Funny enough I discussed satisfying too many needs too much above, which was also
in that book. In some sense even today people satisfy too many of their needs too well. Some shortage is beneficial (especially 
voluntarily, since then you can stop it at any moment and it is not dangerous). You don’t get to enjoy the sun without having rain
or winter. If you live by the sea you just get used to it and don’t care much anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting how thinking about this magical planet brings ideas about issues in FIRE. That’s an interesting thought
experiment and it does precisely what thought experiments are intended to do - uncover stuff by thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I thought for a moment how one could increase the difficulty of this thought experiment directly to insane level.
Just assume that you are immortal on that planet. Oh, it is even scary for me to think about this, but I am not saying
that being immortal is bad. In the worst case one can voluntarily die I assume (unless in jail, oh, it is probably a very
tough punishment).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, happy finding, building / reaching and then living in your own brave new world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. I will now associate “brave new world” and this romanticism around the term with FIRE.
A bit dangerous since FIRE does not solve all your problems automatically, but still looks interesting.
Chao!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;About me&quot;, &quot;Thought experiments&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Thought experiment #9 about a magical planet where all your needs are met by a magical entity.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 12) - Endocrinology</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-12-endocrinology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 12) - Endocrinology" /><published>2019-12-14T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-14T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_12_endocrinology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-12-endocrinology">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 12, Endocrinology. I suspect that many people talk about this topic without having any clue
(“oh, this is must be due to hormones”). Thus, I am very excited to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;function-of-hormones&quot;&gt;Function of hormones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything started with single cell organisms. When multicell organisms appeared, the issue arised - how to
communicate across cells? There are 4 main mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cell-to-cell contact - physically touching, thus, short range. Like passing a note to a neighbor in a class.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paracrine (secreting paracrine factors) - local. Like whispering to several neighbors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neuronal - fast. Like texting your friend during class.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Endocrine (hormones traveling through blood) - long range, but slow. Like sending email to entire class. Enables coordination across cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coordination is useful for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple coordinated cell transformations (e.g. metamorphosis)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To respond to environment (e.g. stress or sexual stimuli).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;types&quot;&gt;Types&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Peptide&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Steroid&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Made of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Amino acids&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Cholesterol&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hydrophilic (lypophobic)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hydrophobic (lypophilic)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Soluble in water?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Travel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Freely through blood stream&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bound to chaperones&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Onset&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Quick&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Slow&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Affect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Existing protein activity&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Transcription (rate of new protein synthesis)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Can travel through cell membrane&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Examples&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;insulin, vasopressin, oxytocin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;glucocorticoids&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hormones have subtle chemical differences in structure, but the higher level structure is similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hormone-release&quot;&gt;Hormone release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many endocrine glands in our body. Each secretes certain signal. Some are located in the brain. Often
peripheral glands are regulated by brain glands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signal flows from brain to hypothalamus, then pituitary gland and finally rest of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pituitary-gland&quot;&gt;Pituitary gland&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consists of two parts - anterior and posterior. They secret different set of hormones and use different mechanisms.
To secrete hormones in anterior part, hypothalamus has to release its hormones. For posterior part hormones come
directly from neurons (i.e. there is a direct neural connection).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anterior releases e.g ACTH, posterior - vasopressin, oxytocin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-loops&quot;&gt;Feedback loops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of hormones can be controlled through feedback loops, e.g. cortisol negative feedback loop.
Cortisol gets secreted through CRH and ACTH. Each of glands producing these have receptors for cortisol.
When they detect cortisol in blood stream, they start producing less of CRH and as a result ACTH, thus, lowering
cortisol production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;effect-on-brain&quot;&gt;Effect on brain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To affect brain hormones have to travel through blood stream (i.e. cross blood brain barrier). 
This barrier is located in blood vessels. It regulates what gets inside/outside brain’s bloodstream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steroid hormones can simply pass this barrier. Peptide can’t on their own, but have a carrier transport for this.
Alcohol also passes blood brain barrier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a hormone to have an effect in brain, neurons have to have its receptors.
Different parts of the brain can be more or less receptive. Some areas just have more receptors.
There can also be individual variation in number of receptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Level of hormones can affect number of receptors. E.g. if there is too much of some hormone, cells
can decrease number of its receptor.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Lecture 12, Endocrinology. I suspect that many people talk about this topic without having any clue (“oh, this is must be due to hormones”). Thus, I am very excited to learn more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 11) - Neuroscience</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-11-neuroscience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 11) - Neuroscience" /><published>2019-12-08T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-08T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_11_neuroscience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-11-neuroscience">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but steadily…
Lecture 11, Neuroscience - part 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time you heard about neuroscience, now something in your head has changed and you remember that you
heard about neuroscience before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;memory&quot;&gt;Memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;super-memory&quot;&gt;Super memory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Wiltshire - an autistic savant. He can draw a very precise city view only after looking from an airplane
for some time. Savants take spacial tours through their memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mechanism&quot;&gt;Mechanism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory (learning) happens (to the best of our knowledge) in synapses. People used to assume that each new
memory leads to a new neuron. That is learning was perceived as equal to growing new neurons. Then people 
discovered synapses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is synaptic plasticity. When your presynaptic neuron fires a lot in a given time, eventually this will
cause a stronger response in the post synaptic neuron. I.e. a simplified version of Hebbian Plasticity -
neurons that fire together - wire together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excitating neurotransmitter is glutamate. It is excitatory and information is transmitted in the brain through 
activation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-term-potentiation&quot;&gt;Long term potentiation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long term potentiation (LTP) - getting more output for the same input. This can be achieved through e.g.
releasing more glutamate, reacting stronger in each of receptors, having more receptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a way for post-synaptic neuron to communicate back - retrograde neurotransmitter, e.g. nitric oxide gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hippocampus is the site of memory and LTP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is adult neurogenesis and adult plasticity. In the last 20 years it was discovered that adult brain
forms new neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HM - person with their hippocampi surgically removed. As a result he could no longer form any new memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But LTP happens all over the brain e.g. for motor and emotion memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LTP can also go wrong, e.g. post traumatic stress disorder, when context brings undesired memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ltp-disruption&quot;&gt;LTP disruption&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also mechanics for intentional disrupting LTP:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hypoglemic states (i.e. when one is really hungry) lead to insulin cascades, which in turn reduces LTP.
In other words, if you starve, it is not a good time to remember something, but to find food instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stress hormones - improve short term memory (e.g. one may be able to remember tinniest details after
a car crash as if in slow motion). However, if the impact is chronic, this damages LTP and memory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alcohol directly disrupts LTP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;networks--inhibition&quot;&gt;Networks &amp;amp; inhibition&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you connect each neuron to e.g. 10k others and overall you have 100B of them, small changes in each
synapse start having large effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be random and spontaneous generation of signal.
It is important for the brain to filter out the noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to consider neurons as groups instead. They also have capability to inhibit. A neuron can
inhibit itself. This allows temporal sharpening. A neuron can inhibit its neighbors:
“this is my signal, ignore my neighbors”. This creates spatial sharpening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be fast sharp pain and dull aching throbbing pain. There are two types of neurons and each type
is responsible for each kind of pain. Fast pain generates slow pain. Slow pain can inhibit first spike
of fast pain. If you get stung by a scorpion, the fast pain forces you to pay immediate attention, perhaps
the scorpion is still there. But there is no sense to keep this forever. Instead slow pain comes to remind you
that you still have the issue and have to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also allows retinal cells to be responsible for specific types of receptive fields.
Each neuron in your eye just gets a certain angle of light. This allows e.g. edge and contrast detection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you activate a neuron in your retina, you get spatiotopic (oriented and aligned in a similar way)
field in the back of your visual cortex.
This was detected by tracing back which neurons a given retina neuron was connected to. Then this has been 
repeated for the next level. However, no single neuron activation was propagated. Instead a group of neurons
forming a line lighted up a neuron in the next layer. This was e.g. a neuron responsive to a vertical line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can construct visual world in layers by extracting features. The further you get, the higher order
abstractions you create (e.g. orange, banana). However, no one has found orange neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can simplify your brain to a neural network. Once a neuron is activated, it doesn’t know where the input came
from. I.e. it is a one-of function. So you can have concepts and categories. E.g. you have separate neurons
for impressionist painters. Then all of them are connected to one neuron. This one neuron can represent
impressionism. This is also how you remember stuff. You first remember a category and then try to narrow it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotionally salient memories last longer.
Context (like emotion) can get represented neurally too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory is encoded in such a neural network, not a single neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;variation&quot;&gt;Variation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory variation can come from variation in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much glutamate gets released&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how strongly post-synaptic receptors respond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ways in which neural networks are constructed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result there is spectrum from HW to Stephen Wiltshire.
We are in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;autonomic-nervous-system&quot;&gt;Autonomic Nervous System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It controls anything that happens automatically.
E.g. heart beating, digesting, goosebumps, orgasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;context&quot;&gt;Context&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nervous system can be divided into Central and Peripheral.
Peripheral divides into Somatic and Autonomic.
Somatic system is responsible for transferring sensory information from periphery to Central Nervous System
(CNS) and voluntary control (e.g. moving muscles). It is fast and myelinated (covered with 
myelin which allows faster signal propagation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic - moves organs, unmyelinated and, thus, slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;parts&quot;&gt;Parts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic system is further divided into Sympathetic and Parasympathetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sympathetic&quot;&gt;Sympathetic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for arousal, alertness, emergency, flight or fight.
Releases norepinephrine (NE) into target organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;parasympathetic&quot;&gt;Parasympathetic&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible for growth, repair, calm vegetative function.
Releases acetylcholine (ACh) into target organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;Interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sympathetic and Parasympathetic have opposing functions.
Homeostasis - dynamic balance between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one exception - in male reproductive system they work together. Erection is controlled by 
Parasympathetic (and that’s why one needs to be stress free). Then Sympathetic overtakes and culminates
in ejaculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case of erectile dysfunction - 60% of cases are due to stress and not organic basis in the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premature ejaculation - transition from Parasympathetic to Sympathetic happens too quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;effects&quot;&gt;Effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Parasympathetic system is active, immune system works. In Sympathetic - contrary.
As a result, it is easier to get sick when you are stressed out (Sympathetic gets activated).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NE &amp;amp; ACh can inhibit and excite depending on the organ. E.g. in case of heart, there is excitatory NE reception
and, thus, it is excited by NE. Gastrointestinal tract has inhibitory NE receptors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulation&quot;&gt;Regulation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The center of regulation of Autonomic Nervous System is hypothalamus.
Even reptiles have it.
Then there is limbic system, which is responsible for emotions in mammals.
As a result, seeing someone you hate can cause sympathetic response through limbic system (emotion) and then
hypothalamus.
In primates, cortex is responsible for thoughts and memories. As a result, just a thought can cause
a sympathetic response (from cortex to limbic system and so on).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when you think about a test, this activates your cortex, then limbic system, then hypothalamus
(so-called triune system of the brain). This cases sympathetic response. It can be similar to a reptile’s body
response to losing blood, but caused only by your thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Autonomic Nervous System is highly plastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biofeedback can be used to cure high blood pressure. You think of something pleasant. This decreases blood 
pressure. You repeat. Get further decrease. This makes the connection between this cortical thought and 
parasympathetic activation even stronger.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><summary type="html">Slowly but steadily… Lecture 11, Neuroscience - part 2.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 10) - Neuroscience</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-10-neuroscience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 10) - Neuroscience" /><published>2019-12-03T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-03T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_10_neuroscience</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-10-neuroscience">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 10, Neuroscience - part 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;broader-context&quot;&gt;Broader context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course tries to show how various sciences answer “why chicken crossed the road”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;evolution - how behavior evolved, why it is adaptive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;molecular genetics - genes controlling the evolution, how they change over time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;behavioral genetics - what individual genes are responsible for variation in behavior&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ethology - studying behavior in nature, stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we consider neuroscience - what happens in brain before the behavior and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Chief function of the body is to carry the brain around. (attributed in Internet to Thomas A. Edison)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nervous-system--brain&quot;&gt;Nervous system &amp;amp; brain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nervous system is divided into central and peripheral. Central consists of brain and spinal cord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain consists of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stem - responsible for communication with spinal cord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;cerebellum - motor movements (especially when learning new stuff and correcting mistakes).
There is a peculiar experiment with prism glasses (everything appears normal, but in reality shifted
to the side). When wearing such glasses, one struggles with touching a target, because their brain
calculates object position as if there were no glasses. After some time (~minutes) one gets used to the glasses
and learns to touch the object as precisely as without glasses before. I.e. their brain learned 
how to correct for the shift. Once one takes off the glasses, they have the same “problem” again, but in the
other direction, and it takes time to autocorrect back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cortex
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;frontal lobe - plans actions, controls movements, each body part has its own part here and they
are located the same way as in the body.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;parietal lobe - sensory touch info. Area per body part can differ, e.g. fingertips are overrepresented.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;temporal lobe - auditory info + memory formation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;occipital lobe - visual info (back of the brain)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;limbic system
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hippocampus - forming new memories.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;amygdala - fear and anxiety - sweat of scared people (experiment described in a previous lecture)
lights up amygdala.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hypothalamus &amp;amp; pituitary gland - hormone secretion&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A joke about 4 F’s of brain - flight, fight, feeding and reproduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spinal cord has specialized areas too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peripheral system - all motor and sensory nerves + nerves for heartbeat, digestion, breathing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brain-cells&quot;&gt;Brain cells&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago Ramón y Cajal is considered by some a grandfather of the modern neurobiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before people thought of a brain as a web. He stained individual cells in the brain with black
and drew pictures of them. This way he investigated brain structure on cellular level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cell examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;90% of cells in brain are glia (means glue).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;astrocytes supply nutrients to neurons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;myelin wraps around neuron wires and makes the signal go faster.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;microglia - immune system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neurons - computational units (100B in average, each has 10k synapses-connections).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neuron&quot;&gt;Neuron&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consists of dendrites (inputs), nucleus (cell core), soma (cell body), axon hillock (start of output),
axon (output) and terminal (end of output branch).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuron is binary (on or off) instead of gradual (i.e. there is no middle level of activation). This helps to keep
resting potential. Sending of information happens through movement of ions (charged chemicals).
Neuron keeps itself quiet by keeping positive ions outside of the cell by using pumps.
Net charge inside is as a result negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When dendrites receive neurotransmitter, channels for positive ions are opened. This changes the charge.
If there is a lot of positive charge, neuron may fire further. If there is enough, channels on axon
hillock open to let more positive ions in, this creates a positive feedback loop.
Positive ions in the terminal trigger sending the signal further to the next neuron.
As it was said above, this is also binary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stop, cell opens other channels to let some positive ions out.
Axon terminal stores large amounts of neurotransmitter packaged in vesicles (discrete structures).
After that a channel can be opened in the next neuron to let ions in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurotransmitter might induce transcription factor.
Neurotransmitters are located in terminals.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dopamine - commonly associated with reward, pleasure, but it has many other functions too&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;epinephrine (adrenalin) - involved in flight or fight response&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;norepinephrine - pretty much interchangeable with epinephrine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;serotonin - e.g. regulation of sleep, appetite and mood.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gaba - inhibitory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;glutamate - excitatory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to remove used neurotransmitter from receptor (re-uptake), otherwise it will keep signaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neuropharmacology&quot;&gt;Neuropharmacology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;External manipulation of synaptic events, e.g. for research or to correct a disease state.
Often this involves something resembling a neurotransmitter, but not fully. Hallucinogens often
work like that (e.g. LSD resembles serotonin).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can weaken synaptic response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with Parkinson’s have low level of dopamine in brain areas responsible for movement. One can increase level of dopamine globally, but this will cause other issues (e.g. schizophrenia-like symptoms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hm&quot;&gt;HM&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient HM - a man who had terrible seizures. As a fix, his hippocampus was removed. As a result, he 
couldn’t form any new memories. He could remember some stuff from childhood.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 10, Neuroscience - part 1.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diversifying over ETF providers</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying-over-etf-providers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversifying over ETF providers" /><published>2019-11-30T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-30T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying_over_etf_providers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/diversifying-over-etf-providers">&lt;p&gt;Many people talk about diversification in terms of geographic areas or economy sectors.
However, the diversification does not stop there. One can also diversify over brokers
where the shares are held. This way if something happens to one broker or the account gets hacked,
not everything is lost. Another dimension is over ETF providers.
This decreases impact of forced capital gain tax realizations. Let’s see how and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a company behind each ETF. E.g. for Vanguard S&amp;amp;P 500 ETF it is Vanguard and for iShares STOXX Europe 600 - BlackRock.
Each of these companies have their own history and can potentially go bankrupt. That’s the worst case. Alternatively
they can decide to change ETF structure or its ISIN. In both cases we are not worried about loosing our money.
However, a forced capital gain realization due to such an event can be unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it is hard to imagine Vanguard going busted, but in FIRE community we are talking about investment horizons
of 30-60 years. This is a long period of time and our imagination is pretty useless for such timescales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-impact&quot;&gt;Possible impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by evaluating how bad the impact can be. For simplicity, let’s say we’ve been investing into one
ETF and now we have \(X\)€ invested and portion \(Y\) of these are unrealized capital gains (e.g. for 35% \(Y = 0.35 \)). For even more simplicity, we will 
assume that the investment is in Germany and, thus, the capital gain tax is 26.375% (25% tax + 5.5% of that for Solidaritätszuschlag).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if we are forced to realize capital gains, our \(X\)€ will become \(X * (1 - Y) + X * Y * (1 - 0.26375) = X - X * Y * 0.26375\) €.
In this abstract form, we can’t conclude much, because we don’t know \(X\) and \(Y\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we can notice that \(X\) actually does not matter. Once we know \(Y\), we know which percentage of our money
we will have to pay as a capital gain tax and that’s what we are the most interested about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;estimating-y&quot;&gt;Estimating Y&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made a quick &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1Gh-Sh6GNh3g0Cm5Csr-RXaHfU54EWlWPmUQIhITYIc4/edit&quot;&gt;spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;
for this. Please use “File &amp;gt; Make a copy” to put your numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spreadsheet shows that \(Y\) at a time when we reach FI is affected by how long it took us to save
(i.e. our savings ratio, expected safe withdrawal rate and yearly market growth). The slower we save,
the larger is \(Y\). In other words, the slower we save, the larger role market has in our FI path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 7% yearly market growth and 4% safe withdrawal rate, we get the following values of \(Y\) based on savings ratio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.11 for 90% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.4 for 60% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.66 for 30% savings rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, if you have 30% SWR, at the time your reach FI, 66% of all your money are unrealized capital gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worst-case-impact&quot;&gt;Worst case impact&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you reached FI today. Let’s ignore capital gain tax for now (i.e. if you are forced to realized all capital
gains, you won’t be FI anymore).
I will look in the following posts whether this assumption is reasonable (i.e. how much more one should save to account for capital
gain tax and other mandatory expenses like health insurance), but for this post this is not that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then something happens to your only ETF and you are forced to realize capital gain tax.
Depending on your savings rate (90%, 60% or 30%), you will have to say goodbye to 2.9%, 10.5% or 17.4% of your stash
right away. For 30% savings rate, this means working 20 more months to reach FI again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;events-which-can-be-taxable&quot;&gt;Events which can be taxable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a tax advisor and this varies across countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ETF liquidation is the most obvious example. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/articles/exchangetradedfunds/09/etf-out-of-business.asp&quot;&gt;Investopedia says&lt;/a&gt;
that investors get their money as a check and this may force an investor to pay capital gain tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is ISIN change, e.g. to due to a merger.
E.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyxoretf.de/pdfDocuments/Merger%20Q&amp;amp;A%20-%20Lyxor%20MSCI%20Turkey%20UCITS%20ETF_0b7b4493f192ea25211a8d348553fd26.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
is a document from Lyxor about the merger of Lyxor MSCI Turkey UCITS ETF in March 2019.
They very vaguely say that you may need to pay some taxes, but this depends on your country.
Fortunately in Germany, figuring this out will likely be broker’s problem, not yours, but you are
the one paying the taxes in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-solutions&quot;&gt;Possible solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose ETFs which are less likely to get liquidated or merged (usually this means large liquid funds from well-known companies and for popular indices)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diversify across providers. This increases probability of you being affected by such an event (now there are more 
ETF companies your work with, each of them can have troubles and this will affect you). At the same time this decreases
an overall impact of such an event (each provider has only a small portion of your money).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy diversification!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Many people talk about diversification in terms of geographic areas or economy sectors. However, the diversification does not stop there. One can also diversify over brokers where the shares are held. This way if something happens to one broker or the account gets hacked, not everything is lost. Another dimension is over ETF providers. This decreases impact of forced capital gain tax realizations. Let’s see how and why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Value does not have to be perfect</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/value-does-not-have-to-be-perfect" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Value does not have to be perfect" /><published>2019-11-26T17:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-26T17:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/value_does_not_have_to_be_perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/value-does-not-have-to-be-perfect">&lt;p&gt;I am interested in startups and try to pay attention to how exactly value is created around me.
I am also somewhat a perfectionist and when I try to create value myself, I tend to over-polish 
the details, often not being even sure whether the value is actually created. I noticed a couple examples
of projects with imperfections (sometimes major), which people use anyway. Let’s look at these examples more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anki---memorizing&quot;&gt;Anki - memorizing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anki is a program to memorize whatever you want using spaced repetitions. The idea is that you forget
exponentially and each repetition resets the curve and makes it not so steep. However, it does not make sense to
repeat too often. Anki tries to estimate what you are about to forget and shows you these &lt;em&gt;cards&lt;/em&gt; for repetition.
It works especially well for learning languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, there is only one major Anki program on Desktop. There is also one on Android and iOS. At least Desktop and Android
ones allow one to synchronize and backup their data through cloud for free. Pretty convenient, especially when one uses
Anki one their phone (e.g. when travels). As a result, the data needs to be merged occasionally. This merge logic can
become a nightmare pretty quickly. To my surprise, the authors of Anki just decided to refuse to merge in some cases.
E.g. when a card type is changed (e.g. instead of “show me both sides as 2 items”, you replace it with “show me only 1 side”),
the program just says - “hey, next time you will have to reupload all your data to the cloud, just FYI”. Then the other device
just asks you whether you want to download or upload your data and whether you really want to overwrite your local data.
My software engineering part feels pretty uncomfortable seeing that, but this is a great example of prioritization.
The desktop and Android versions are completely free (even cloud storage). Thus, the authors probably didn’t have too much spare time.
This reupload is definitely not perfect, but it is also not that bad at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely get plenty of value from Anki and this reupload is just a minor nitpick. I personally would feel uncomfortable
about making such decision not to merge some cases and just reupload everything. However, I haven’t seen anyone refusing to
use Anki because of that. Also I am not aware of any competitors either (probably, because it is free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shotcut---video-editing&quot;&gt;Shotcut - video editing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember I needed to compose a small video. I definitely didn’t need any serious software, because this was a one-off thing.
Thus, the goal was to have it done as easy as possible (i.e. no learning curve at all). Somehow I discovered Shotcut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program itself is pretty simple and easy to learn. At the same time there are some rough edges. It is obviously free.
However, occasionally it could crash (pretty rarely though). Also my computer is not the newest, so keeping all the high
resolution videos in memory got impossible pretty fast (especially when using preview function). Surprisingly, there is
no built-in fix for that. However, the Shotcut community found a workaround. Basically, the program does not store videos
themselves, but only their paths in the file system. Thus, we make a project with all the high resolution videos (add them from
some folder). Then we backup this folder into some other temporary folder. In the old folder, we downscale the resolution of all
videos. Now reopen the old project. Shotcut will just use downscaled versions as if it always was like that. Now you
can do everything as usual (just the quality will be poor). Even the preview works. Once you are done, you restore the old
high resolution backup and reopen the project again. Now you don’t need to look at the high resolution preview, you just
produce the final video. This is not that RAM intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised by this solution. However, I discovered got stuck with this issue pretty far in the process,
so I already had some part of my video
done in Shotcut and what was even more important - I already knew how it worked. So I did the workaround precisely as described above.
In the end it went very well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, if I need to do another video, I will consider using Shotcut again (mostly because I already know how to use it).
I even don’t mind this workaround at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like quite an imperfection to me, however, the program still provides plenty of value.
There are many competitors in this area, but they are not free and not so easy to use without much preparation.
This “easy-to-start”-ness is the main value of Shotcut for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a reminder to myself to focus on the value when creating something. It is very easy to get stuck with small details
and polish them forever. However, this polishing does not make sense, if there is no value provided. Unfortunately, it is much easier
to do such value analysis once there is a finished product with some history and customer base. When I do
something myself, it is also unclear whether I will be able to provide any value at all. Anyway, this is a great reminder to focus
on what should be the most important to the customer, prototype it as fast as possible and polish later once you see that it
works and provides value (if any polish is needed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy value creation!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am interested in startups and try to pay attention to how exactly value is created around me. I am also somewhat a perfectionist and when I try to create value myself, I tend to over-polish the details, often not being even sure whether the value is actually created. I noticed a couple examples of projects with imperfections (sometimes major), which people use anyway. Let’s look at these examples more.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 9) - Ethology" /><published>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_9_ethology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-9-ethology">&lt;p&gt;Lecture 9, ethology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethology is a field, which studies behavior under the following assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will need to study the behavior in as many environments as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these environments must be as natural as possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you will have to translate a language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, ethology is a process of interviewing animal in its own language,
i.e. an expansion of “if you want to understand behavior, get your animal out of the lab”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;history&quot;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the historical context, let’s have a look at the history of psychology.
At first it was a branch of philosophy and wasn’t about numbers (i.e. not a science in the modern terms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then behavioralism appeared, which treated an organism as a black box and the goal was to measure as much as possible.
The field had number of strong beliefs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extreme environmentalism - impact of environment is very high.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcement theory - when I can control positive/negative reinforcement, I can form any behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Universality across species. Everything is black box, thus, it does not matter whether it is a human child,
a puppy or an elephant. As a result, the studies used mostly rats and pigeons for practical reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then meanwhile in Britain people started to collect butterflies as a hobby. The goal was to just observe
variability. Then ethology emerged, which was like butterfly collection, but for behaviors. 
There were 3 main figures in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nikolaas Tinbergen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Konrad Lorenz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Karl von Frisch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field was about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gene-environment interaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;examples of animals acquiring new (often unexpected) behaviors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;every species solving its own evolutionary challenges in its own way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: in 1960s it was discovered that, if a lab rat was placed in a richer environment (cage with toys), 
its cortex got thicker. As a result, people started to assume reversibility of early brain damage using
richer environments. However, then it was observed that a simple wild rat had very thick cortex, which was
unreachable using any artificially rich environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;approach&quot;&gt;Approach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethologists look for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the behavior was - fixed action pattern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what triggered it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what happens in the head of the animal, when it is triggered by the stimulus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what the adaptive value of this behavior is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fixed-action-pattern&quot;&gt;Fixed action pattern&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed action pattern - a sequence of actions, which animals don’t have to learn, but they have to improve it.
Experience can also change context of fixed action patterns.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a squirrel raised in a cage on a liquid diet still can crack a nut without any preparation. It will get even better at it practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“visual cliff” = baby animals scared to sit on glass over a height (floating = falling). Baby sloths are not scared of this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a male monkey, which was raised in isolation and have never seen another monkey. Show him a video of a face of huge scary
monkey of the same species with threating display. He will freak out and do subordinate gesture. Experience: who to do the subordinate
gesture to, i.e. not kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vervet monkeys have different alarm calls for eagle, snake and leopard. As kids they know how to do the call, but may not know when to do it
(i.e. mix up them). Adults don’t trust young monkey calls, but double check.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In humans:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Infants smiling as well as fetuses and blind babies. Learning: who to smile to.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Nursing. Learning: increase efficiency.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Detecting anger, fear, disgust in others; Learning: social context (i.e. when the meaning is not obvious).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adaptive-value&quot;&gt;Adaptive value&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand adaptive value, they did experiments. E.g. Tinbergen experimented with a bird turning egg shells non-white side up
after its chick hatching. Tinbergen turned them back. As a result, predators could detect the nest better. Frisch looked into bee
dancing. Bees communicate info about food sources (direction, how far, how much). They do this by dancing on the floor in patterns
shaped as “8”. Axes of “8” define the direction. The duration of the dance - distance. The more frantic the dance is (more back
wiggling), the more exciting the food source is. E.g. Frisch rotated a bee hive after the dance and all bees went in wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stimulus&quot;&gt;Stimulus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are number of techniques to study stimulus (so-called releasing stimulus in the field). One can assume what the stimulus is and then
subtract it, then put it back (replacement), then substitute (replace with something else), then superstimulate (exaggerate).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently people started to use robotic animals (e.g. bees or cockroaches) for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample findings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female deer ovulate when they hear male mating calls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats can be tickled on their ribcage and they giggle in ultrasonic
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=78PfGQbL-g0&quot;&gt;youtube&lt;/a&gt;). Other rats come over to check “the party”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female ovulation in human leads to higher voices. Males can subliminally detect this.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was research (&lt;em&gt;Stimuli eliciting sexual behavior&lt;/em&gt; by Schein, M.W., &amp;amp; E.B. Hale, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/how-to-seduce-a-turkey-the-bizarre-poultry-sex-experiments-of-the-1960s&quot;&gt;atlasobscura&lt;/a&gt;) on what makes a female turkey attractive to a male turkey.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Olfactory information in people. People can subliminally
(amygdala activation) distinguish scared people sweat from normal exercise sweat.
After “scary” sweat, they tended to interpret ambiguous faces as more frightened.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electric fish - males jam each other frequency when courting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vibration in insects - animals have vibration detectors in their feet. They can communicate this way.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrogate mom monkeys - a monkey is given a choice of two fake moms - one made with cloth (warm) and one
made out of wire, but with milk. Behaviorists claimed that mom attraction is due to milk. However, animals choose cloth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Baby animals look cute (large eyes, ears) even across species. Early illustrators of Disney studied this
(e.g. evolution of Micky Mouse, youtube: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4vDiykIUwSo&quot;&gt;with commentary&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3hWXfrANSd8&quot;&gt;without&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.wwu.edu/rcm/mickey.pdf&quot;&gt;“A biological homage to Mickey Mouse” by S. Gould&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;neuroethology&quot;&gt;Neuroethology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before it was hard to study how stimulus is processed in the brain. Currently there is neuroethology. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;neurobiology of bird songs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Lordosis” reflex in female hamsters. When having a pressure on their back, they arch their back to make mating easier.
Only works when the hamster is ovulating. Specific neurons responsible for this are known, even which ones of them 
are affected by estrogen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be done in the field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding electrodes to the brain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sapolsky studied baboons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of learning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Female childcare competence in female monkeys is not a strong instinct. Evidence: later offsprings have higher likelihood to 
survive. If she has a sister with a baby, her first child is more likely to survive (observed sister doing the care). The same
when having a niece or a nephew.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meerkats eat scorpions. Mom has to teach her kids. First, she brings a dead one, baby learns how to eat it.
Then mom brings alive scorpion, but she bites off the stinger. Kid has to tackle this one. Finally, she brings 
a normal scorpion. Thus, incremental learning steps (with progressing difficulty).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Animals make tools (e.g. apes). Chimps use sticks to get termites. One learns by observing others.
Daughters learn better (much more attentive). The larger the social group is, the earlier in life kids learn to use tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One trial learning (imprint after one exposure) - after hatching bird chicks imprint on something big around to bond for mom.
In this case, there is no place for trial and error.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepared learning, e.g. Sauce-Bearnaise Syndrome. One ate the sauce and then went to opera. They had stomach pain.
The next time they were to taste the sauce, they had repulsion (unpleasant smell). The pain was not attributed to opera
(even though it occurred during opera), but to the sauce, since there is a prepared learning of food -&amp;gt; stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bees learn smell better than color or shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humans are not inherently scared of spiders and snakes, but have prepared learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cognitive-ethology&quot;&gt;Cognitive ethology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Griffin (random fact: discovered echolocation in bats) wrote “On awareness in animals”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;self-awareness&quot;&gt;Self awareness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can test for self awareness. E.g. dogs are not self aware.
Take a chimp, anesthetize, put a black dot on its forehead with a marker. When looking into the mirror,
chimps are much more likely to start scratching their head where the dot is. Elephants pass this test too.
Marmoset monkeys don’t. They don’t look into eyes normally. Thus, when the dot is on their neck, they
start noticing it too. An example of “interviewing” an animal in its own language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;theory-of-mind&quot;&gt;Theory of mind&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Realizing that other individuals can have different information than you. Humans start understanding this at the age of
4-5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test, one can tell a child a story about another child X, who has a doll called Sally. X goes to school.
Mom washes Sally and puts it into a different place. When X comes back, where would it look for Sally?
With the theory of mind the child will say “the old place” (since X does not know that they doll has been moved).
Without the theory of mind - “the new place” (since the child knows where the doll is and can’t imagine X having
different info).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chimps have this too. E.g. you can have two chimps (one high ranking, one low ranking) and a banana (all divided by dividers). 
If there is a glass divider between high ranking and banana, low ranking won’t try to get the banana (he knows that high
ranking knows). When you swap high ranking chimp with a different high ranking one, low ranking will go for the banana, 
because he understand that the new high ranking chimp does not know about banana. However, they can do this only in
competitive setting (no cooperation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corvus have this too. If they see someone observing them when they hide food, they won’t proceed with hiding the food.
I.e. they understand that other birds will know about the food hidden here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can distinguish intentional action from unintentional. In chimps - they react more dramatically to a person throwing
away their food vs. tripping over it. Dogs know the difference between an intentional kick and someone tripped over them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animals can plan for the future. E.g. take corvus living in a cage with 2 areas. In each of the areas, there is a place
where researchers put food every other day. In one of them, they put more. Corvus starts bringing food from this place to another one for tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;flexible-cognitive-strategies&quot;&gt;Flexible cognitive strategies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bees will distrust implausible dances. E.g. researchers put food in the middle of the lake. A bee tells others about this. Others
don’t do anything, because there can’t be food in the middle of the lake.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Numerosity.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Teach chimp to detect series of 3 objects, e.g. “ABC” and “HIJ”. When they see them, they should pull the lever and
  they will get food. When shown “HI&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;”, they make less mistakes than when shown “H&lt;strong&gt;B&lt;/strong&gt;J”. In the former case, the third object
  was replaced with the first. In the latter - second with second. I.e. chimp detects that this object is “second”, but forgets
  which triplet it belongs too.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Take a chimp troop. Record foreign male chimp vocalizations. Play one foreign male chimp vocalization in the bush. The troop will
  investigate. Play vocalizations of the same number or more other chimps than in the troop, the troop will know that they are outnumbered and
  silently run away. They understand that 4 is more than 3.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In fish. Fish C sees A defeating B and then B defeats C. C gives subordinate gesture to A (transitivity).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Course reviews&quot;]" /><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Lecture 9, ethology.</summary></entry></feed>