<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-27T23:25:05+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Frugal travel or how much does FIWE 2019 cost</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how-much-travel-to-fiwe-2019-cost" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frugal travel or how much does FIWE 2019 cost" /><published>2019-01-27T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-27T20:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how_much_travel_to_fiwe_2019_cost</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/how-much-travel-to-fiwe-2019-cost">&lt;p&gt;I’ve accidentally discovered that there will be another &lt;a href=&quot;https://whatlifecouldbe.eu/fiwe/fiwe-2019/&quot;&gt;Financial Independence Week Europe (2019)&lt;/a&gt; in Budapest in May. 
I felt like it might be interesting to go there. However, before commiting, I definitely should know how much it will cost,
since my willingness to go is a function of cost. For example, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fichautauqua.com/&quot;&gt;Chautauqua 2019&lt;/a&gt; everything is extremely simple - 
€2300 is just too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s see how much FIWE 2019 actually costs (at least for me) and consider some frugal (aka cheap) ways of attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, before we start, we can break down our task into multiple subtasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One needs to get to Budapest and back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One needs to stay somewhere in Budapest.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conference fee.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fun.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are inevitable expenses (assuming that you are going to the conference) and they provide a good lower bound,
which we can improve later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conference-fee&quot;&gt;Conference fee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;€25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was easy, wasn’t it? While we at it, thanks a lot to the organizers, this is the real frugal conference fee (do you still remember €2300?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-to-budapest-and-back&quot;&gt;Getting to Budapest and back&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one is less obvious, but still manageable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May I will likely be in Munich, so that’s my starting point. The main part of the conference happens from 2nd to 4th of May,
but since I will be travelling there anyway, I consider it reasonable to stay for FIWE Extra as well (i.e. until evening of 8th of May).
Thus, our constraints are Munich, 2nd-8th of May. Let’s consider travel options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bus&quot;&gt;Bus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geography wasn’t my favorite subject, so let’s check the bus first (in case if Budapest is not that far from Munich).
Flixbus is a somewhat default bus option in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/flixbus.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Flixbus website with trips from Munich to Budapest. The prices are 30-40 euros and duration is at least 13 hours.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh. Ok, Budapest is much further than I thought. Spending 13 hours in a bus is just inefficient and for 40 euros one way there must be alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight&quot;&gt;Direct flight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be naive and see how much it costs to have a flight from Munich.
We can do this in Google flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/google_flights_direct.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Google Flights website showing a Lufthansa flight. No price is shown.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it costs 140 euros. Plus 11.2 * 2 to get to and back from the Munich airport. Plus something for Budapest airport (but I am lazy to look it up now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 22.4 (MUC &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; MUC airport) + 140 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight)  + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-dates&quot;&gt;Other dates&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes playing with the dates helps (e.g. ticket price difference is larger than one night stay), but not in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/google_flights_direct_other_dates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Google Flights website showing price matrix for different dates around 2nd and 8th. 140 is the cheapest.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight-but-not-from-muc&quot;&gt;Direct flight, but not from MUC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to know about Memmingen airport, which has a bunch of lowcosters.
Check Google Flights again  - and no flights whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t give up yet. I know about azair.com flights search engine, which is very flexible.
By default it suggests me to search starting from MUC,SZG,FMM,INN,NUE and this works well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are really cheap (like €36 for a return flight cheap) flights from Nuernberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_nuernberg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with cheap flights from Nuernberg.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we just need to get to NUE airport. There is blablacar, but this does not sound good before a flight.
So Flixbus, it is. Unfortunately, they don’t have a schedule for May and April yet,  but in March
the prices are 5-6 euros. The only issue is that the outward flight is pretty early (10:40am),
but there are no early morning buses. So I could come one day earlier and explore Nürnberg as well.
Or the schedule for May may change. Or my application for FIWE won’t be approved. We will see. Also the return flight
is pretty early too, so I might need to stay in BUD until 9th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 12 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE) + ? (a night in NUE) + ? (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE airport) + 36 (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-flight-but-not-from-muc-1&quot;&gt;Direct flight, but not from MUC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a typo. Didn’t I say that azair.com is very flexible? It also has a list of nearby airports and knows about various local lowcosters.
Moveover it allows you to search for all trips e.g. from 7 to 9 days between two dates. Pretty cool, huh? So let’s add all airports close to Munich&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_airports_close_to_muc.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with list of airports close to Munich.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, how I could have forgotten about Stuttgart. Sorry, Stuttgart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/azair_airports_close_to_muc_to_bud.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of azair.com with flights from airports close to MUC to BUD. Stuttgart is cheapest.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still magically low 36 euros, but a bit better timing. Wrong date though, but I don’t mind spending additional day in Budapest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Flixbus again - direct early bus from MUC to STU airport, 3 hours, 10-14 euros.
Getting back is a bit less pleasant (on 8th there is a bus at 12:35 from the airport, but the next one is at 22:00).
But I don’t have to commit now, I just consider my options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 20-28 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;STU) + 36 (STU&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;making-budapest-just-a-part-of-vacation&quot;&gt;Making Budapest just a part of vacation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually you can make the problem even harder by allowing traveling with changes and spending time in stopover cities.
Inside Europe this works well with buses and blablacar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually you should start by looking at the map and checking which cities between the target cities sound interesting.
I’ve been to Vienna, so I am not interested for now. Bratislava sounds interesting. However, I don’t want to visit
the same city on the return trip (picky). So probably Graz in Austria is the second. But then it is not connected well to Budapest.
And Bratislava is not connected well to Munich. So blablacar, but this is a risky territory if you want to be at a given 
time at a given place with high probability (especially since one can’t book well in advance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the optimization problem gets too large here. And if you allow more than one stopover… Don’t do this, it is just too tricky to plan
(unless everything is well connected with a bus or you don’t mind unexpectly spending additional day in one of the cities visited).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, nope for now. But if I hadn’t visited Vienna…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;travel-options-overview&quot;&gt;Travel options overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from MUC &amp;gt;= 162.4&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;22.4 (MUC &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; MUC airport) + 140 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight)  + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from NUE &amp;gt;= 48&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;12 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE) + ? (a night in NUE) + ? (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;NUE airport) + 36 (NUE&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Flight from STU &amp;gt;= 64&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;20-28 (MUC&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;STU) + 36 (STU&amp;lt;-&amp;gt;BUD flight) + ? (BUD &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; BUD airport) + ? (a night in BUD).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can fill in accomodation prices later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accomodation&quot;&gt;Accomodation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With accomodation there is less room for optimization. Usually it is just Airbnb or hostels depending on my prediction how social I will feel during the trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;airbnb&quot;&gt;Airbnb&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Airbnb it is important to remember that you can filter by price (especially if you save money):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/fiwe_2019_costs/airbnb_price_filter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of airbnb price filter.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They say average nightly price is 74, but there are plenty of options cheaper than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, there are some options for 15-18 euros per night, which might be too extreme.
But 20-25 range seems ok and 30 per night should be plenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a way to optimize, I could cooperate with fellow conference goers and book something together.
This is definitely quite far fetched (I haven’t even applied yet), but it would bring the price down
for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 15-30 per night&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hostels&quot;&gt;Hostels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For hostels booking.com seems to work okeyish. I definitely couldn’t ever recommend it just due to how pushy the UI is, but it is the only site I know, where I can quickly see for how many people a room in a hostel is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the prices are from 8 to 13 euro for a bed. 8 euro is a mind-boggling number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 8-13 per night&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food is tricky to estimate, since we will likely eat as a group. However, we can give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually numbeo.com (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.numbeo.com/cost-of-living/in/Budapest?displayCurrency=EUR&quot;&gt;Budapest’s page&lt;/a&gt;) is very handy for this task. 
So meal in an inexpensive restaurant is 5.6 euro on average (7.78 upper bound), 12 eggs - 1.7, bananas - 1.34, apples - 1.06.
Let’s say I will have 2 eggs - banana - apple breakfast (~0.76 euro) and lunch/dinner in an inexpensive restaurant (~14 euro). I could do all three meals myself in airbnb’s or hostel’s kitchen, but the main goal is the conference, so let’s not waste time and focus on it. I would rather spend time in a restaurant talking with others than saving 3-5 euros per meal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: 15 euro per day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fun&quot;&gt;Fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun is impossible to estimate at this stage, since the plan is not known.
So let this be a surprise. In worst case I could drop out of any pricey group-goings, but again this is a FI conference and I would be extremly suprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;total&quot;&gt;Total&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€25 conference fee&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;\&amp;gt;= €64 flight from Stuttgart&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€8-30 per night for accomodation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;~€15 per day for food&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;€? for some fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grand total is &amp;gt;= €265 - 419 + fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s see whether my application will be approved.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="frugality" /><category term="travel" /><category term="FIWE" /><category term="FIRE" /><summary type="html">I’ve accidentally discovered that there will be another Financial Independence Week Europe (2019) in Budapest in May. I felt like it might be interesting to go there. However, before commiting, I definitely should know how much it will cost, since my willingness to go is a function of cost. For example, with Chautauqua 2019 everything is extremely simple - €2300 is just too much. So let’s see how much FIWE 2019 actually costs (at least for me) and consider some frugal (aka cheap) ways of attending.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“My time costs X” fallacy</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/my-time-costs-x-fallacy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;My time costs X&quot; fallacy" /><published>2019-01-19T15:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-19T15:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/my_time_costs_x_fallacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/my-time-costs-x-fallacy">&lt;p&gt;Often I hear people invoking “my time costs X” argument when discussing ways to save money. Usually that’s how they explain why it does not make sense to spend time to save some amount Y, especially when it is much smaller than what they earn (i.e. X).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are likely wrong. Let’s see why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we start, I would like to draw your attention to the fact that calculating X is less obvious than it looks. Your work can lead to non-obvious expenses and you may be spending more time on it than you think. For example, you need to commute, perhaps buy business clothes, go somewhere for lunch or even you may be tired in the evening after work. All of these adds up to your 8 hours a days. If you did not working, you wouldn’t have to do all of these, thus, they are caused by your work and should be taken into account when calculating X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, let’s assume that we trust the number X. I.e. a person works full time (e.g. 40 hours a week) and makes X &amp;lt;some currency&amp;gt; per hour after taking into account all effects of the job on their life. Basically their argument against saving amount Y by spending some time is that they can make amount Y in minutes/hours by working instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fallacy because most likely they just can’t work additional hours. I agree that there are various exceptions here like paid overtime (but this is not very sustainable) or freelance. However, often people invoking this argument just work fixed 40 hours a week. That is for them the actual comparison is between “work 40 hours a week + do something instead of saving Y” vs “work 40 hours a week + spend time to save Y”. Thus, from the perspective of getting more money, saving Y &amp;gt; 0 always makes sense. However, this just applies to “saving non-zero amount” in some way, the exact way of doing this may indeed make no sense, due to existence of more efficient ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, one should not compare this saving money gig with their work time. It takes your free time instead. After work you can have a rest / spend time with your family / do sports or try to save amount Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also funny to consider that person’s time is in a way priceless - one will likely have a finite life and there is no way to get any time back. At the same time, by saying “my time costs X” people ignore this fact. Moreover, from this perspective even their working time could be considered wasteful, because they sell their priceless time only for X per hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, think twice before saying “my time costs X”. Your time likely costs much more to you, but you should still go forward with that weird way to save money if you feel like it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="fallacy" /><category term="frugality" /><category term="saving" /><summary type="html">Often I hear people invoking “my time costs X” argument when discussing ways to save money. Usually that’s how they explain why it does not make sense to spend time to save some amount Y, especially when it is much smaller than what they earn (i.e. X). They are likely wrong. Let’s see why.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Learning how to learn” - my impression and conclusions</title><link href="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn-course-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Learning how to learn&quot; - my impression and conclusions" /><published>2019-01-12T21:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-12T21:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://merelycurious.github.io/post/learning_how_to_learn_course_review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://merelycurious.github.io/post/learning-how-to-learn-course-review">&lt;p&gt;Recently I took somewhat famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/learning-how-to-learn&quot;&gt;&quot;Learning how to learn&quot;&lt;/a&gt; course at Coursera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience was pretty mixed. I would like to share my impression and a brief summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I started the course it looked very intriguing: “invaluable learning techniques used by experts”, promises to “change your thinking and change your life” and so on. However, afterwards the course felt pretty shallow. They did touch various interesting topics, but they almost never went into any details (e.g. why something is like how they say or how exactly this works in a brain). They also used multiple analogies without explaining their underlying concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the course was extremely chaotic. We jumped from topic to topic and sometimes the topics were not even mentioned in the videos (“Renaissance Learning”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tests are odd as well. Approximately half of the answers were obviously nonsensical. One did not even have to read a question to understand that these answers were wrong. The other half are just pretty close quotations from the videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lists of recommended articles were difficult to use. The articles there were not explicitly matched with the facts from videos. Also there were many of them. Overall I struggled to read these articles due to lacking background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The videos are pretty short (3-10 minutes) and in the end of each video the lecturer says something like “I am &amp;lt;some name&amp;gt;, thanks for learning how to learn”. I heard this phrase probably around 50 times during the course…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say that you shouldn’t take this course, but I also cannot recommend it. I feel like this information could have been presented in a much shorter way or with more background details, but I don’t regret ~6 hours spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important disclaimer: while I personally don’t look very found of the course, I tried applying what I learned to learning how to juggle clubs and it worked surprisingly well. I am going to tell about this in a separate post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-summary&quot;&gt;Brief summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me briefly share what I learned, so that I recall it one more time and remember it better. Yeap, I learned this during the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;modes-of-thinking&quot;&gt;Modes of thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brain has 2 modes of thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focused&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diffused.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is always in one of these two modes. The focused mode is used when you are thinking specifically about something you are familiar with. Usually in this mode you just follow the approach you learned before. In diffused mode, you can get into “new territory”, gain new ideas, combine already known ideas in unusual ways and gain high level context about what you already learned. Basically, when you sit and think how to solve a given problem, you are in focused mode. Then, when you go to make a tea, you enter the diffused mode. The diffused mode explains why often you get great ideas during a walk, while taking a shower or before sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lecturer shared anecdotal stories about e.g. Edison, who would intentionally get into diffused mode by relaxation. He would hold metal balls in his hand, sit in a chair, relax and fall asleep. While he felt asleep, he would involuntarily drop the balls on the floor and this would wake him up. During this “getting asleep” time, he would enter diffused mode and get new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a to-do list before sleep or just in advance utilizes your diffused mode. You start unconsiously working on the items and already have some ideas when you actually start working on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;memory&quot;&gt;Memory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have 2 kinds of memory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working memory has only 4 slots and it is not very efficient. One needs to apply mental effort to keep data in these 4 slots. Long term memory is like a storage warehouse - good for long-term storage of a lot of data, but retrieval is trickier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can move data from working to long term memory by repetition and practice (better when over several days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a to-do list helps to free some space in your working memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;importance-of-sleep&quot;&gt;Importance of sleep&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sleep is very important for memory and learning. Just being awake creates toxic waste products in a brain. They get cleaned during sleep. Moreover, a brain also organizes memories during sleep (garbage collecting unimportant data, rehearsing and strenghtening important data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;chunks&quot;&gt;Chunks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All data in memory is organized as chunks. A chunk incapsulates all the details of the underlying skill and, thus, takes only 1 slot in working memory (i.e. like a hyperlink - this “increases” your working memory). It also requires less mental effort to perform. E.g. solving quadratic equations. You can have a chunk for “quadratic equations solving” and then just use it instead of going through all of the underlying details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can combine multiple chunks into one chunk. One can create a chunk from scratch by practising a specific skill. E.g. in language learning, saying a sentence requires multiple skills (form a sentence with proper grammar, remember the words from vocabulary, pronounce them correctly). Thus, you can practise each subskill, form a chunk for each of them and then combine them into one chunk responsible for the entire skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the following to “chunk”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus 100% of your attention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the basic idea&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gain context (e.g. when to use this chunk)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Practise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context is very important, since then you know when and how to apply and how to combine different chunks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can transfer knowledge to new areas through chunks. A chunk can make it much easier to understand similar chunks in different fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;memory-palace-technique&quot;&gt;Memory palace technique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have good visual and spatial memory due to evolutionary reasons. One can utilize this to remember better. E.g. try to represent what you learn with an unusual image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memory palace technique involves imagining a well known place, where you put objects you need to remember in unusual or weird ways. E.g. for a shoping list you can imagine your living room with a huge loaf of bread in your chair and a bunch of broken eggs on your sofa and milk dripping from the ceiling. Coming up with these weird ways is difficult at first, but gets better with practise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;illusion-of-competence&quot;&gt;Illusion of competence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are reading a book or seeing a solution of a sample problem, you will likely feel that it is easy and that you can manage it. This is an illusion of competence. In order to avoid it, try to recall what you have read so far or go through the sample problem on your own after (or instead of) looking at the solution. Testing yourself also helps. Overall, actively recaling the informination is more efficient than just rereading when you try to learn something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overlearning&quot;&gt;Overlearning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you learned a concept, practising it further can lead to automaticity. This is good in some areas (sport, public speaking), but normally you don’t want this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overlearning can cause Einstellung, i.e. when an idea you have learned makes it hard to learn something new (you just follow the old familiar approach instead). A peculiar saying was mentioned to illustrate this: “Science progresses one funeral at a time”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also tend to practise areas they are already good at (this feels better). Instead one should do deliberate practice - identify areas they struggle with and practise them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interleaving&quot;&gt;Interleaving&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you need to practise multiple skills (even from different subjects), it is much better to practise each of them a bit by bit one by one multiple times instead of just learning the first skill completely and then going to the next one. In other words, if you want to learn skills A and B, practising in order “ABABAB” is better than “AAABBB”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;procrastination&quot;&gt;Procrastination&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something you don’t like activates pain-like feeling and you shift your attention to something more pleassant. Similar to addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution is to focus on process (let’s write for 20 minutes) instead of product (get homework done). &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique&quot;&gt;Pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt; (setting timer for 25 minutes of focused work and then having 5 minute break) helps to focus on process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;habit&quot;&gt;Habit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procrastination is closely related to a habit.
A habit consist of 4 parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cue (trigger)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Routine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reward&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Belief&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To overwrite a habit, one needs to change their reaction to a cue. A cue can be a location, time or even your feelings. Rewarding yourself e.g. after learning session can be helpful as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planning your quiting time in your to-do list helps to focus on process. Also try to accomplish the least pleasurable but most important tasks first (“eat your frogs in the morning”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start your learning session, it is normal if you don’t feel too excited about it. Everyone has such feelings, you can just start anyway for couple of minutes and see how it goes. Most likely you will get into it very quickly and just continue working.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Recently I took somewhat famous &quot;Learning how to learn&quot; course at Coursera. My experience was pretty mixed. I would like to share my impression and a brief summary.</summary></entry></feed>