<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-07-21T19:49:17+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Delaying capital gains taxes during saving for FIRE phase</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying-capital-gains-in-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Delaying capital gains taxes during saving for FIRE phase" /><published>2019-07-21T19:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-21T19:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying_capital_gains_in_FIRE</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/delaying-capital-gains-in-fire">&lt;p&gt;It is common knowledge that one should delay realizing their capital gains as much
as possible (especially when aiming for Financial Independence / Early Retirement).
Let’s focus on the phase, when one saves for FIRE, and see the magnitude of the effect
of such a delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own unique situation. This post is based on a number of assumptions,
thus, don’t rely on it as is. Have a look at the assumption and see how well this applies 
to your situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly known that usually one should delay realizing their investment capital gains
as much as possible to increase their returns. Basically, instead of just paying the tax now, one can
temporarily keep it and continue getting investment growth (compounding) out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simulation&quot;&gt;Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an example of Annet.
We will use the following assumptions about Annet and her life:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lives in Germany&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pays German capital gain tax and always 26.375% (25% tax itself &amp;amp; additional 5.5% of it as solidarity tax)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has other income, i.e. the capital gain tax is never reduced to progressive income tax.
This is a strong assumption, but not for the collection phase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;never uses 801 tax-free capital gain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no dividends and no tax prepayment (this is different from the current German system)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;starts from 0 in January 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(the strongest assumption) the market always has constant yearly and monthly returns.
I use 4% return per year or equivalently 0.32737% per month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;earns 2k EUR and invests 1k EUR each month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We assume that Annet contributes 1000 EUR every month.
Her investment growths by 0.32737% at the end of every month.
I.e. she has 0 at 1st of January 2019. She invests 1000 in the end of January.
In the end of February her 1000 grow into 1003.27 and she invests another 1000,
thus, having 2003.27 pre-tax overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we compare 2 options. The first option is delaying realizing capital gains as
much as possible. Basically she never sells until becoming FIRE. At that point, she will pay 26.375% on her
capital gains. The second option is realizing capital gains as fast as possible (every month, alternatively
having only distributing ETFs).
Basically, once her 1000 grow into 1003.27, she immediately sells them (or receives dividends)
and buys the same asset again. While doing this, she pays 26.375% tax on the growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This is just a simplified model. Re-buying the same asset might be considered a wash sale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also normally one does not sell everything after becoming FIRE, but here we
assume this to be able to compare the two approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve prepared &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/11iki1iPJawRdpLVxPoIGkBx0Oq5MowwRENDcuVZvbRQ/edit&quot;&gt;a Google Spreadsheet with the calculation&lt;/a&gt;. You can play with it by making a copy first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to 4% rule, her FIRE target is 300k. 
In the first case, she reaches 300k (after tax) in 222 months (July 2037) and pre-tax she has
327k. In the second case she has only 294k EUR at this point (i.e. 1.7% less).
She needs 4 more months (1.8%) to reach 300k EUR post-tax in the second case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-case&quot;&gt;General case&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above we considered only one particular setting. Now let’s have a look how the two cases differ
under various yearly investment returns and time horizons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/delaying_capital_gains/difference_based_on_return.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing them monthly) depends on number of months invested and yearly return on
investment&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, for 7% yearly return and 30 years, the difference crosses 12%, which is a substantial amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-research&quot;&gt;Further research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible improvements of the simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;take into account 801 EUR capital gain tax free every year.
This won’t affect the result too much though as we have already seen
in 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/801-tax-free-capital-gains&quot;&gt;my previous post about tax-free 801 EUR per year&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, this can improve the second case (realizing gains immediately),
but at most 801 * 0.26375 = 211.26 EUR per year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;look into FIRE spending phase, which is much more dependent on capital gains.
In this simulation we pretended that we send everything once one reaches FIRE
to compare the two cases. In reality that’s not true. In this case not-realized
capital gains will have even more time to grow, thus, this should make
the difference even larger.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;take into account capital gain tax becoming progressive income tax.
Finally, this should reduce the tax paid after FIRE substantially.
Basically, if one has no or little income and their progressive income tax is less
than 25%, they don’t pay 25% on their capital gains either (but their income
tax instead).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;using real market data. Currently I just assume 4% per year growth, which
ignores sequence of returns completely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;taking into account yearly tax prepayment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will address some of these in my follow-up posts, stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delaying your capital gains matters less than I expected (1.7% difference under 50% saving rate and 4% yearly return case).
However, since by default you don’t realize them, it is better not to do anything extra and just don’t lose these 1.7%.
Overall, 1.7% (or even more if the yearly return is larger than 4%) can be a reasonable sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally one can be forced to realize their capital gains (e.g. an accumulating ETFs gets closed or 
changes its internal structure). Based on the numbers above, it makes sense to try to avoid this to some extent
(e.g. buying same ETFs from different providers).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Simulations&quot;, &quot;Germany&quot;, &quot;Investing&quot;, &quot;Financial Independence / Early Retirement&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><category term="taxes" /><summary type="html">It is common knowledge that one should delay realizing their capital gains as much as possible (especially when aiming for Financial Independence / Early Retirement). Let’s focus on the phase, when one saves for FIRE, and see the magnitude of the effect of such a delay.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to disable notifications prompt in Chrome?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications-prompt-in-chrome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to disable notifications prompt in Chrome?" /><published>2019-07-16T20:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T20:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications_prompt_in_chrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/notifications-prompt-in-chrome">&lt;p&gt;Numerous sites ask for permission “to show notifications”.
Some of them even obstruct the site itself unless ones makes a choice in this permission prompt.
Pressing “no” multiple times a day (with a probability to eventually misclick “yes”)
sounds like wasting of time. Fortunately, there is a way in Chrome
to say “no” by default (i.e. disable this prompts completely and never see them again).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/notifications_in_chrome/reddit_problem.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Reddit blacking out the website until one closes the 
notification prompt.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open chrome://settings/content/notifications and disable “Ask before sending (recommended)”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final result:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/notifications_in_chrome/solution.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Chrome settings with this notification prompt (finally!) disabled.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively in order to reach this screen you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to Chrome Settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for “notifications” or go to Advanced &amp;gt; Privacy and Security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose Site Settings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open “Notifications”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;funny-story-from-my-life&quot;&gt;Funny story from my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I misclicked “yes” on some random website, which I opened only once. You can imagine my face when I noticed
a very weird pop-up notification some day after. I completely forgot about this website.
Obviously, I thought that I had some malware, but somehow I ended up checking notification permissions.
Yeap, that site was there. To be honest, I still don’t remember clicking “yes”, so I just assume that I misclicked.
This was the last drop for me to disable these prompts for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy browsing without useless distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;How-to&quot;]" /><category term="howto" /><category term="Chrome" /><summary type="html">Numerous sites ask for permission “to show notifications”. Some of them even obstruct the site itself unless ones makes a choice in this permission prompt. Pressing “no” multiple times a day (with a probability to eventually misclick “yes”) sounds like wasting of time. Fortunately, there is a way in Chrome to say “no” by default (i.e. disable this prompts completely and never see them again).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">801€ tax free capital gains each year in Germany</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/801-tax-free-capital-gains" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="801€ tax free capital gains each year in Germany" /><published>2019-07-13T16:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-13T16:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/801_tax_free_capital_gains</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/801-tax-free-capital-gains">&lt;p&gt;In Germany, one does not pay any tax for their first 801€ of capital gains each year.
I personally try to realize at least 801 EUR each year to use this benefit, but I am
now curious how much of a difference in the long term this makes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone has their own unique situation. This post is based on a number of assumptions,
thus, don’t rely on it as is. Have a look at the assumption and see how well this applies 
to your situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met some people who did not bother with these 801€ per year at all. However, I do try to use them.
Basically, when realizing 801€ of capital gains, one pays no taxes in Germany.
Normally one would pay 26.25% tax (25% capital gain tax and 5% of that is solidarity tax).
Thus, one can get free 801 * 26.25% = 210.26€ each year by doing this. This is definitely
not a life changing sum, but I am curious what the impact is when saving e.g. for FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dividends do count against this sum as well. Moreover not realized capital gains now have to be partially
realized up to basic interest rate (Basiszins) each year which goes against these 801€ as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;simulation&quot;&gt;Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assumptions&quot;&gt;Assumptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider Jannet.
We will use the following assumptions about Jannet and her life:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lives in Germany&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;does not have any other capital gains except from her stock portfolio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has other income, i.e. the capital gain tax is always 26.25% and never gets replaced
with the progressive income tax (in a future post I will look more into how this works).
This is very realistic for the collection phase&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;starts from 0€ in January 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(the strongest assumption) the market always has constant yearly and monthly returns of
 4% and 0.32737% respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;earns 2k€ and invests 1k€ each month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we assumed above, Jannet contributes 1000€ every month to her portfolio.
Her investment grows by 0.32737% at the end of every month.
I.e. she has 0 at 1st of January 2019. She invests 1000€.
In the end of February her 1000€ grow into 1003.27€ and she invests another 1000€,
thus, having 2003.27€ overall pre-tax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we compare the two following options. The first option is to never realize capital
gains during the savings phase. I.e. she has 2003.27€ pre-tax and she does nothing.
The second option is to realize capital gains up to 801€ per year, in order to use this
tax benefit. I.e. she would immediately realize these 3.27€ and have 2003.27€ already taxed.
At some point she will reach 801€ for this year and stop realizing capital gains
to delay paying capital gain taxes into the future (there will be a post on how this delaying
affects the investment growth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we compare the two approaches, we always compare post-tax sum. I.e as if Janet sold all her 
investments at that months. Here we take into account 801€ in both approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spreadsheet&quot;&gt;Spreadsheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve prepared &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1WGdB1HYkCbbj0_C1Ap3ELpAWIsxr97B4lyN7mU6CEAE/edit&quot;&gt;a Google Spreadsheet with the simulation&lt;/a&gt;. You can play with it by making a copy.
The simulation inputs are all the way on the right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, making the spreadsheet was quite tricky.
I had multiple mistakes at first and had to compare the numbers with my python simulation
to fix them. As a result, the spreadsheet is quite complicated and may be hard to follow.
However, the most interesting field is diff percentage (i.e. difference in percents between
the two options). There are also actual overall savings after tax for each months (columns adjacent
to the diff column).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to 4% rule, Jannet’s FIRE target is 300k€. 
In the first case, she reaches 300k€ after tax in 222 months (July 2037) and pre-tax she had
327k. In the second case she reaches 300k€ after tax 2 months earlier (May 2037).
By this time she had realized 14542€ of capital gains tax free by using this 801€ benefit.
I.e. she has got 14542€ * 26.25% = 3817.27€ for free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between the two approaches (in percents) jumps to 1.37% and then slowly falls down to ~1.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s plot the difference for each month:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/jannet_s_case.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801 EUR tax free yearly) depends on number of months invested
for Jannet's case&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does look peculiar and we can make a number of observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, for some time the difference stays at 0. This happens before Jannet’s overall capital gains
reach 801€. This is just a consequence of me applying this 801€ bonus when calculating the final amounts
saved in both cases. For example, in May 2019 the investment growth is 32.84€. In the first case,
these are fictitiously realized before the comparison. In the second case, they are realized each month.
In both cases, Jannet pays no tax on these 32.84€, because of 801€ tax-free benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we observe a peculiar unexpected sawtooth pattern. This can be explained
by the yearly nature of this 801€ tax benefit. In January each year, the 801€ counter
is reset. As a result, before Jannet uses this limit completely the difference grows.
However, once Jannet exhausts these 801€ for a given year, the difference stops growing and
actually relative percentage starts slowly decreasing. This happens because the mixed tax sum
(sum of already taxed and not yet taxed parts)
is the same in both cases. Whether a gain is taxed or not does
not impact capital gains obtained from it. As a result, the investment growth
in both cases is exactly the same. Then in the next January, 801€ counter is reset again
and the difference grows for some months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can compare the plot with the spreadsheet to see precisely how this happens.
In month 32, Jannet exhausts 801€ for the first time. As a result, for the remaining
months in this year (33-35) the difference falls. Then the 801 counter gets reset
and the difference starts growing again (months 36-41) until it gets exhausted again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-case&quot;&gt;General case&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above we considered only one case - investing 1000€ monthly @ 4% yearly return.
Both variables affect the result, e.g. if we invest 10k€ monthly, the effect of
exactly the same old 801€ becomes much smaller. Also, if the investment grows
faster, this will decrease the difference as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, let’s have a look how the difference between the two approaches
depends on yearly returns, monthly investment amount and time saving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by extending Jannet’s case (1000€ monthly @ 4% yearly growth) to various yearly
investment returns (1-7%):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/1000_different_roi.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801€ tax free yearly) depends on time saving and yearly return on
investment when investing 1000€ per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we can see, for approximately all yearly return value the difference reaches around 1.2% and the starts to fall
down. The speed of the decrease is larger for higher yearly returns, as we already predicted above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at investing 100€ per months:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/100_different_roi.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801€ tax free yearly) depends on time saving and yearly return on
investment when investing 100€ per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The observed difference gets much more substantial and reaches 7% at a peak.
This is natural, since 801€ is a substantial amount of money, when one invests 100€ per month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining plots for 500, 2000 and 5000€ invested per month you can see in the appendix below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-research&quot;&gt;Further research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible improvements of the simulation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;look into FIRE spending phase, which is much more dependent on capital gains.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take into account capital gain tax becoming progressive income tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will address some of these in my follow-up posts, stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 801€ tax free capital gains per year do matter! You can get additional 1.2% post tax when investing
1000€ monthly @ 4% yearly by realizing at most 801€ tax free each year.
If you invest less, e.g. 100€, the effect becomes even more dramatic and the difference can reach staggering 7%.
And if you invest something like 5k€ per month, the difference reaches 0.3%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, these are free money, which are very easy to get. Thus, I advise you to use this opportunity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy realizing 801€ of capital gains each year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;appendix&quot;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/500_different_roi.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801€ tax free yearly) depends on time saving and yearly return on
investment when investing 500€ per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/2000_different_roi.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801€ tax free yearly) depends on time saving and yearly return on
investment when investing 2000€ per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/801_tax_free/5000_different_roi.png&quot; alt=&quot;a plot showing how difference (in percents) between the two cases (delaying capital gains and
realizing at most 801€ tax free yearly) depends on time saving and yearly return on
investment when investing 5000€ per month&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Simulations&quot;, &quot;Germany&quot;, &quot;Investing&quot;]" /><category term="fire" /><category term="analysis" /><category term="mini-project" /><category term="taxes" /><summary type="html">In Germany, one does not pay any tax for their first 801€ of capital gains each year. I personally try to realize at least 801 EUR each year to use this benefit, but I am now curious how much of a difference in the long term this makes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Mindless eating” - impression and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/mindless-eating-book-summary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Mindless eating&quot; - impression and summary" /><published>2019-07-09T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-09T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/mindless_eating_book_summary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/mindless-eating-book-summary">&lt;p&gt;Recently I read “Mindless Eating: Why We Eat More Than We Think” by Brian Wansink.
Here is my impression (somewhat positive) and summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before reading this book I discovered that there was a controversy associated with Brian Wansink.
Wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brian_Wansink&quot;&gt;gives&lt;/a&gt; a good summary:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;These problems included conclusions not supported by the data presented, data and figures duplicated across papers, questionable data including impossible values, incorrect and inappropriate statistical analyses, and “p-hacking”. The lab had 17 papers retracted (one twice) and had 15 corrections issued. On September 20, 2018, Cornell determined that Wansink had committed scientific misconduct and removed him from research and teaching, limiting his activity to cooperating with further investigation of his papers; he resigned effective June 30, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely don’t have enough insight to judge this, but Cornell announced that Wansink would retire
[&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/science-and-health/2018/9/19/17879102/brian-wansink-cornell-food-brand-lab-retractions-jama&quot;&gt;source: vox&lt;/a&gt;] (by the way
on 30th of June, i.e. pretty recently) and this is a substantial argument that something was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this I decided to read the book anyway, but didn’t pay attention to the precise numbers much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the book felt quite insightful. For some weird unexplainable reason, it also felt somewhat hard and not that interesting to read.
Once I wrote this summary, I also understood that the structure was quite chaotic (i.e. the same or very similar 
piece of advice was mentioned multiple times) and often the topic of a given chapter was not immediately obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book contained many of my observations from my life. I did make some changes in my life and I was definitely able
to observe a lot described in this book around me (e.g. in restaurants and cafes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 3/5 (not a waste of time, but I wouldn’t recommend unless you have bad eating problems, also the fact
that I had to ignore precise numbers due to the controversy affected the score as well, otherwise it could have been 4)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[note: I have heavily reordered my notes to make them more structured.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple labs studying food choices (like the author’s). Food producers do their research too (e.g. how customers
will like a new product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have millions of years of evolution telling us to eat as often and as much as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-suck-at-estimating-how-much-to-eat&quot;&gt;We suck at estimating how much to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much we eat is heavily affected by external factors and we underestimate the effect of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After each bite we don’t stop to reconsider whether we are now full. Instead we look for external cues (e.g. empty plate
or other people leaving). As a result, the more food you are given, the more food you will eat
(even if you don’t like the food - e.g. stale popcorn).
People mistakenly claim that this does not apply to them.
It also does not matter whether they are hungry. One eats more when given a larger container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also get anchored. E.g. when they get a signal that the meal is good, they will convince themselves so and vice versa.
Another example: when asked whether apple has 50 or more calories - their average response is 66, when asked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;150 or more - the average response becomes 114. That’s how promotions in shops work - any sign with a number promotion
increases purchases by 30-100%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try dishing out 20% less than you think you might want before you start eating. People can detect 30%
difference, but not 20%. For fruits &amp;amp; veggies - have 20% more (e.g. cut 20% of pasta, but have
20% more veggies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are bad at remembering what we ate and how much. Normally food does not leave a trace, but when it does
we will eat less (e.g. chicken bones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also don’t notice gaining weight (unless we measure). Our clothes don’t lie - they fit or they don’t.
For dieters, these are called “signal clothes” (e.g. being able to fit in a favorite pair of jeans).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We usually try to eat the same portion as yesterday. We think that we will be full if we eat a full plate,
half plate - half full. As a result, if the food looks bigger, we will feel more full (e.g. by adding veggies).
You can do this with air (e.g. keeping a smoothie in blender for longer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we think that we ate less that typical volume, we will think that we are hungry. More - full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We eat the volume we want, not the calories. E.g. 2x calories food is perceived exactly the same as 0.5x.
People would consider themselves to be exactly the same full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t stop eating when our stomach is full. It seems to be a combination of how much we eat,
taste, swallow, think about food and how long we’ve been eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need 20 minutes to signal satiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often decide how much to eat before putting food in our mouth. We also don’t ask ourselves constantly whether
we are full yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stomach has 3 settings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Starving (bottom level, not eating for 8 or 18 hours leads to the same feeling)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m full but can eat more&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m stuffed (top level, you can’t continue eating)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should rely on your internal cues and stop when you are not hungry (instead of when full or
by external cues). This is actually very different from stopping when you are full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See it before you eat it. When preplating, people eat 14% less than when they refill.
Put everything you want to eat on a plate before you start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See it while you eat (e.g. soda bottles or chicken bones).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People tend to eat 20-25% more from larger packages (even worse for snacks).
This applies not only to food (e.g. shampoo, laundry detergent).
Big packages suggest a consumption norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People assume that 1 package is 1 serving.
If you empty six 100 cal servings into a bowl, the serving becomes “how much we want to eat”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brains have a tendency to overfocus on heights at the expense of width. E.g. people
pour more liquid in short wide glasses and underestimate (even bartenders, i.e. with
experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Size contrast illusion - we use background objects as a benchmark for estimating sizes.
A larger plate influences you to serve more (same for large spoons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/mindless_eating/illusion.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Ebbinghaus illusion illustration. Two groups of circles. The left one is an orange circle with
large circles around it. The right one - an orange one with small circles around it. 
The orange circles seem to be of different sizes (the left one is smaller), but they are actually the same.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fig: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ebbinghaus_illusion&quot;&gt;Ebbinghaus illusion&lt;/a&gt; - the central circles are the same
[&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mond-vergleich.svg&quot;&gt;source: Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informing people about this does not help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it is easier to estimate small values (see psychophysics for more details), e.g. building height
or calories you ate. As a result, the bigger the meal, the more people underestimate how much they ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, mini-size your boxes, bowls and packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 year old children are not affected by the serving size, 5 year old are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Rozin has shown that amnesiac patients ate a second complete meal within 30 minutes after having eat a prior
meal, once they were told it was dinner time
[note: the article has only 2 patients and 3 occasions: &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1111/1467-9280.00073&quot;&gt;What Causes Humans to Begin and End a Meal? A Role for Memory for What Has Been Eaten, as Evidenced by a Study of Multiple Meal Eating in Amnesic Patients by P. Rozin et al&lt;/a&gt; ].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variety&quot;&gt;Variety&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diets based on food restriction work, because people get bored of the same allowed foods and eat less of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasing the variety of food increases how much we eat. 
“Sensory specific satiety” - senses get numb or sated if they continually experience the same stimuli.
The first of anything is almost always the best. We also eat more, when we simply think there is more variety.
E.g. people eat more M&amp;amp;M’s from a bowl with 10 colors vs. 7 colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friction-ie-visibility--effort&quot;&gt;Friction (i.e. visibility &amp;amp; effort)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we see food, we start wanting it and will eat more of it. Every time we see it, we have to say “no”.
Eventually it will turn into “yes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of sight = out of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply thinking of food can make us hungry.
The more you think of something, the more of it you will eat. The more hassle it is to eat, less we eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TODO: buy chopsticks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even opening an ice cream fridge can repel people from eating ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;distractions&quot;&gt;Distractions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we eat, we often follow eating scripts. Eating with people we like causes overeating - takes longer and we are more
distracted. However, you can finish eating the last. Use the slowest eater at the table as your
pace setter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eating is like shopping - the longer you stay at the mall, the more you buy.
If we stare at a cookie, it is only so long before “no, no” becomes “maybe” and then “yes”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The less people watch TV, the skinnier they are (because they have more time to exercises and fewer reasons to snack).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distractions of all kinds make us eat more, forget how much we ate and extend how long we eat - even when
we are not hungry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physical-vs-emotional-hunger&quot;&gt;Physical vs emotional hunger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Physical hunger&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Emotional&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;builds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;gradually&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;suddenly&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;strikes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;below the neck (e.g. growling stomach)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;above the neck (e.g. a “taste” for an ice cream)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;occurs several hours after a meal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;unrelated to time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;goes away when full&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;persists despite fullness&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;eating leads to&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;satisfaction&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;guilt and shame&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;healthy-food-something-free-or-low-like-low-on-fat&quot;&gt;“Healthy” food (“something”-free or low, like low on fat)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We view food as black and white and often consider food free of “something” (e.g. low fat or sugar) as healthy,
even though it may contain similar number of calories (e.g. due to a compensation for the taste).
E.g. people eat more of low fat products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;company-incentives&quot;&gt;Company incentives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No food company is in business to make us fat. They just sell food.
If we want to mindlessly eat fattening food - they will do it. If we want healthy food -
they will find a way to do it (assuming it is profitable). They don’t care if we 
throw away the food as long as we pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;food-perception&quot;&gt;Food perception&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our taste buds are biased by our imagination (see “expectation assimilation” and “confirmation bias”).
That’s why presentation of a dish plays a role. Fancy dish names work the same (preprogram us). Brands work
similarly (set some expectation, e.g. real Coca-Cola vs. a similar drink with a different brand).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feelings we have when we first eat some food can follow us for a lifetime (e.g. 
World War II US soldiers who served in the Pacific and had more intense combats tend to dislike Chinese food more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The order in which you eat your food (i.e. whether the best first) depends on whether you are the only child
(or from a small family).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can rewire your comfort foods - e.g. start pairing healthier foods with positive events, e.g.
celebrate with “desired” comfort foods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;family&quot;&gt;Family&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nutritional gate keeper - the person who decides / buys food for the house. Also the one cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unhealthy food tools extremes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food as reward (ice cream for exam)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food as guilt (finish because people starve)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food as punishment (finish or no TV)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Food as comfort (eat and then you will feel better)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diets&quot;&gt;Diets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normal diets are deprivation diets. Our body fights against them by using stored calories more efficiently (like during a famine).
This type of diets is like pushing a boulder uphill every second every day.
If we deny ourselves something, we end up craving it even more.
Normally such diets are like sacrifices and after finishing them we are prone to catch up.
The bigger the deprivation the bigger the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting out favorite food is bad, instead we should just eat less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dieting strategy “I will never eat X again in my life” (e.g. fried chicken or ice cream) is destined for a failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t deprive yourself - keep comfort foods, but eat them in smaller amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;this-book-methods&quot;&gt;This book methods&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food tradeoffs - “I can eat X if I do Y” (e.g. I can eat this candy if I take the stairs for the rest of the day).
Food policy - just some rule (e.g. never eat at my desk), this helps not to spend any effort on making this decision each time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can use external cues to unknowingly lose weight (i.e. without deprivation).
Mindless margin - we can’t identify whether we ate 300 calories too much or less yesterday,
i.e. the zone where we can slightly overeat or under-eat without noticing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting only 100 calories a day would prevent weight gain in most of the US population (or walking 1 extra mile a day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just making 3 changes (100 cal each) in your daily food routine is enough to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half plate rule - half the plate for vegetables and fruits, the other half for protein and starch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rule of thumb for estimating calories in drinks - 10 calories per ounce (~30 ml) in thin drinks (soft drinks, juice, milk),
20 calories in thick (smoothies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drinking with ice burns calories (body needs to warm the liquid up) - 1 cal / ounce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you drink 8 glasses, 8 ounces (240 ml) of water each with ice, you burn ~70 calories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes 28 days to break an old habit and replace it with a new one.
Set up a check list (i.e. for each day and each 100 cal change) to make it more accountable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are two miles away from your home. You can run and get there 3x faster, but
walking gets you there as well - at a reasonable and painless rate though. Each step brings you
a little closer. It is the same with losing weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best diet is the one you don’t know you are on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Book reviews&quot;]" /><category term="book" /><category term="summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Recently I read “Mindless Eating: Why We Eat More Than We Think” by Brian Wansink. Here is my impression (somewhat positive) and summary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kids and impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/kids-and-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kids and impro" /><published>2019-07-06T10:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-06T10:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/kids_and_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/kids-and-impro">&lt;p&gt;Some participants brought their children to our impro workshops a couple times
(mostly due to not having anyone else to leave them with). Observing children
in impro context made me think and I made a number of observations about the connection
between impro and childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have no clue what impro is, here is my &lt;a href=&quot;/post/beauty-of-impro&quot;&gt;“Beauty of impro” post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, at first the impro-workshop-with-children experience was suboptimal.
Children misbehave. They shout, run, make noises, completely ignore their 
parents and others, bump into everyone, get into dangerous situations.
For me and others this was quite distracting at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impro-gods&quot;&gt;Impro gods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I understood that when we are doing impro, we are in some sense
trying to be like these kids. I.e. we are scared of disapproval and
rejection and try to get over this. The kids don’t know the rules yet,
so they are in some sense free and, thus, can do whatever they like.
I noticed this when we were trying to play a game and one kid
was shouting really badly. Imagine 20 adults trying to play a game
and one kid just shouts loudly making the game impossible.
After that the kid went through the group completely ignoring
everyone. I couldn’t do that and still can’t. I can’t just shout loudly
whenever I want. This is definitely more plausible at an impro
workshop than outside, but, still, if I misbehave too badly,
I don’t have “being a child” card anymore and others will just 
stop inviting me. I can’t just bother others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I now call kids the gods of impro. They are constantly in impro mode
and don’t care about others’ opinion much. They also lose this
ability with time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was extremely peculiar to observe all of this during the workshop.
I felt like other people were not that happy about the situation.
At the same time, they were actually implicitly trying to become like 
these kids. They wanted to come on stage and come up with stuff and do 
something unplanned (even if embarrassing or weird). That kid was doing
exactly that and constantly (without even knowing that it may be considered
embarrassing or weird).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-did-impro-as-a-kid&quot;&gt;I did impro as a kid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another observation is that I used to do something similar to the scenes we are doing now
during impro workshops (I already mentioned this
in my &lt;a href=&quot;/post/beauty-of-impro&quot;&gt;“Beauty of impro” post&lt;/a&gt;, I suspect that
the idea there is actually coming from this workshop with kids). We would just gather together
and then build some shared reality completely on the go. I have no clue how this could work,
because it must be very hard to agree on something. E.g. one wants to play as some medieval
knights and another as futuristic robots. But somehow it used to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is extremely peculiar that I lost this ability so badly. I clearly remember that it
was very natural as a kid and now it is so hard. I definitely enjoy redeveloping this skill
through impro. However, it may be hard to find someone to “play with”
(especially outside of impro).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;playing-with-kids-is-hard&quot;&gt;Playing with kids is hard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, playing with kids for me now is extremely hard.
Somehow I find them to be extremely unpredictable. They also don’t
follow any rules. E.g. playing a game where I need to catch them
and then they should catch me can be impossible. I catch one kid
and they just don’t react at all and run away as if I didn’t catch them.
This feels frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I loved to observe how limited I was.
I just had these rules in my mind - “catch game” - 
“I catch him - he starts catching me” - and I was 
following this approach precisely - as a script.
I speculate that the kid does not have this yet.
I don’t know whether they even understood the rules
(presumably, yes, because they did catch others
somehow, they just didn’t react to me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yes, playing with kids is hard, but it is not their
fault, but mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impro-is-cool-for-kids&quot;&gt;Impro is cool for kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was also very peculiar that in the end many people
at impro can play well with kids (I am curious whether
this correlates with impro experience). They could
play the same game kids play (including shared reality) and at a similar 
level. Thus, impro workshops are in some sense cool for kids too,
since playing such games with adults must be quite a different
experience. I speculate that adults outside of impro community
may struggle more with such games (or even reject playing completely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I definitely enjoyed observing kids’ behavior during an impro workshop
and their interactions with other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy observations!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Improvisational theatre&quot;]" /><category term="impro" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">Some participants brought their children to our impro workshops a couple times (mostly due to not having anyone else to leave them with). Observing children in impro context made me think and I made a number of observations about the connection between impro and childhood.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Negative reactions during impro</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/negative-reaction-in-impro" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Negative reactions during impro" /><published>2019-07-02T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-02T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/negative_reaction_in_impro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/negative-reaction-in-impro">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing impro for quite some time now, however, I still often get
disapproving reactions in my mind when others do something.
Here are my reflections - mostly about reactions, handling and this being ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think today is a good day to stop describing the concept of impro in the prelude.
Instead here is a link to
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/beauty-of-impro&quot;&gt;“Beauty of impro” post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is peculiar that beginners in impro worry more about negative reactions
coming from other people. However, with time one learns that everyone
in the group is very nice and kind. Trust appears. I think that I am
close to this state now. I am definitely much less scared of other people 
reacting badly than I was before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently I noticed quite a few times that I still get negative
reactions in my head when others do something. This piqued my interest.
On the one hand I learned not to be scared of other people reacting negatively,
but, on the other hand, I still get such reactions myself in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;negative-reactions&quot;&gt;Negative reactions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can vary a lot. The simplest example is someone making a sub-optimal
(in my view) choice when building their scene. I very quickly get a thought like
“oh, they could have done X and it would have been so much better”. Another example
is when someone does something very unusual or almost controversial
(a controversial joke, weird noises, an insult, does not follow
the rules of the game). Here I mostly become very conscious of their action
and view it negatively for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;handling&quot;&gt;Handling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I don’t express my negative reactions during impro.
I am grateful that others didn’t do this when I just started
doing impro (otherwise this would have quickly killed any desire to
learn). Thus, I don’t do this either. However, this is not
the main reason why I don’t express. Somehow when I remind myself that this is impro
and that I did something similarly crazy, weird or cringey before,
the negative feeling goes away on its own pretty quickly. Somehow this works
even outside of impro. This reminds me about my recent
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/not-getting-angry&quot;&gt;post “How not to get angry?”&lt;/a&gt;.
There I observed that reflecting helps to avoid getting angry about something.
Perhaps the same mechanism is at play here as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, such reactions seem to be completely out of my control.
They just appear in my mind as a response to what I observe. 
Like “Oh, this is awkward / weird / cringey “. I am wondering why this happens.
I speculate that this might be a consequence of one trying not to be
weird themselves. You definitely get similar thoughts when you do something
weird yourself (like singing when you have no clue how to do it well).
Perhaps some part of the brain detects such situations (e.g. to be able to avoid
them and in this way to improve one’s position in a prehistoric community).
And it looks like by doing impro I learned to turn off (or ignore)
such thoughts related towards me. However, I still get them towards others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-this-bad&quot;&gt;Is this bad?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, there are multiple ways to interpret that question, I see a couple options
(but the answer to all of the variations is still - no).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, when you get such thoughts, then you are on the boundary of your
comfort zone and something unusual and interesting must be happening.
I consider this positive. Imagine all people around you behaving “normally”,
such that you never get such thoughts. That would be extremely boring.
For everyone. Basically, when you get negative thoughts, you must be in 
a situation with increased “variance” and “amplitude”. Such situations
can lead you to unexpected ideas, which you would not discover yourself.
I think this is one of the main parts of impro - experiencing something,
which you would not be able to experience on your own. Basically, having 
a thought “Wow, I couldn’t imagine this developing this way, but now I do
enjoy it enormously”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, is the fact that you get these reactions bad by itself?
Nope. This is somewhat outside of our control. We’ve been impacted by
society, traditions and norms our entire life. As long as you can
hold them inside, everything is fine! Just remind yourself that you
were doing crazy stuff as well and let it got!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy impro with crazy situations but few negative reactions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Improvisational theatre&quot;]" /><category term="impro" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html">I’ve been doing impro for quite some time now, however, I still often get disapproving reactions in my mind when others do something. Here are my reflections - mostly about reactions, handling and this being ok.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment #6 overview: unpopular opinions</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions-overview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment #6 overview: unpopular opinions" /><published>2019-06-30T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-30T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_6_unpopular_opinions_overview</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions-overview">&lt;p&gt;Saving Ninja had a new thought experiment recently (#6, about unpopular opinions).
I again felt like making an overview of responses. Thus, here it is!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the general description of these experiments, see 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;my last post-response&lt;/a&gt;.
I previously did &lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;an overview&lt;/a&gt;
for the experiment #5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main goal here is to try see whether there are any peculiar similarities and differences.
This is also a good excuse to read all the responses (otherwise I would not find time for it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, it is just interesting. I still remember &lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;“A Way to Less”&lt;/a&gt;
goal to learn to handstand from the previous overview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experiment official page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
You can find links to posts in the Notes section below. I will refer to people by their twitter username for simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;observations&quot;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the group happened to be very diverse and majority of opinions were mentioned only once.
Therefore, this time I will just describe my observations and highlights without making a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common unpopular opinion was FIRE or something related (@SavingNinja, @financeyourfire, @FretfulFinance, @merely_curious_).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both @TheIndeedably and @DrFIREUK didn’t like peer-to-peer landing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For @asimple_life and @merely_curious_ (i.e. me) there happened to be almost a bingo situation.
Both of us happen to consider alcohol unnecessary (thus, don’t drink as much as others normally do)
and think that the society affects other people lives too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@SavingNinja believes that doing more yourself makes one happier. @TFSRetireEarly suggests, on the other hand, that
people should DIY less and it is overrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peculiar to read responses of Andy and James from Rebo. They took different sides of the same
argument - whether one should be altruistic and how moral this is. The posts resembled a light duel or a debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@SavingNinja has touched relationships a bit. The opinion is to split expenses 50/50 in a relationship.
@FretfulFinance went all in on a relationship path. She never had a relationship, does not want to live 
with someone else, does not like weddings (but not anti-marriage), does not want children and does not
like public displays of affection. The post felt very personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These were all the matches and below are remaining unique opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@MoneyModernGirl finds Italy too traditional and welcomes more innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@financeyourfire believes in crypto currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@TheIndeedably has multiple unpopular opinions and presented a compilation of them: simpler tax code, more efficient social security,
one should own wealth generational assets, leverage is good, P2P landing is bad, innovation is slowing,
luck plays a large part in life (especially health), nothing really matters (we will be dead anyway), life is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@ditchthecave believes that our appearance affects our lives more than we think. Also everything can be learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr. @awaytoless finds electric cars not so environmentally friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs. @awaytoless reminds us that we are not entitled to anything and feeling so can even have negative impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@DrFIREUK suggests to invest in equities, pay more attention to personal finance, avoid credit card debt and P2P investing. 
For them early retirement is not a goal (they plan to work). Also the last season of Game of Thrones was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@fi_left finds public ownership better than private. In other words, we need more parks, libraries,
free health care and good public transport instead of buying something for yourself for your short term happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;@TFSRetireEarly believes in no free market. Also not everyone can become FIRE. One can beat the market and win money
by gambling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I my notes from what I read.
I have no clue why you would like to read this,
but I don’t see any harm in putting them here either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;saving-ninja&quot;&gt;Saving Ninja&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/unpopular-opinion&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SavingNinja&quot;&gt;twitter @SavingNinja&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thought experiment to take part in, since the topic was from Indeedably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weird one in private (reading, FIRE), with some quirks leaking externally (money saving tips guy at work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matched betting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being into FIRE is already weird, but let’s not focus on this, since majority of readers are into it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belief that “spending less makes you happier”, e.g. outsourcing to a bread maker instead of doing it with your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splitting expenses 50/50 with one’s partner independently of income difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;-indeedably-&quot;&gt;{ in·deed·a·bly }&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/against-the-tide/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheIndeedably&quot;&gt;twitter @TheIndeedably&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressing disapproval at board members meeting showing that an approach won’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to the experiment is “peer”.
If you don’t care about someone’s opinion, they are not your peer.
As a result, you can have very small peer group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to live in a society where one can have and even express unpopular opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our opinions can be used to other parties for their own benefit (e.g. through media).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tax code should be simple (a single-sided sheet of A4). All income should be taxed the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better social security. Evaluate the actual need for social security (e.g. whether one has
assets to sell). If the money are needed urgently (before being able to sell an asset), the
help should be a loan. Free education and healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Own wealth generating assets (i.e. work for your own wealth instead of someone else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leverage is good (if used correctly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peer-to-peer lending is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation is slowing (and goes backwards in some areas due to short term views).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luck plays a large part (especially in one’s health).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing really matters (you will be dead anyway). Deadlines are arbitrary.
Stress is mostly self inflicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is pretty good. It could be so much worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caveman--ditchthecave&quot;&gt;Caveman @ DitchTheCave&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ditchthecave.com/unpopular-opinions/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ditchthecave&quot;&gt;twitter @ditchthecave&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People don’t share their REALLY unpopular opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How you look matters and impacts how successful you are in life. But the “good look” is defined by the culture and society itself and
changes with time. There is “beauty premium” (physical beauty affects wages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything can be learned (i.e. natural ability is a myth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can do anything, but you can’t do everything&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mr-a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;Mr A Way To Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-6&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/awaytoless&quot;&gt;twitter @awaytoless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric cars aren’t environmentally friendly. The batteries can have negative effects.
Power generation still can be environmentally unfriendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;miss-a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;Miss A Way To Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-6-miss-way/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/awaytoless&quot;&gt;twitter @awaytoless&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not entitled to anything. Feeling entitled affects your work - why working for something if you “have” a right for it? 
People feel entitled to start a family even when their financial position is nut suited for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We [Mr and Mrs Way] are entitled to be treated fairly. However, we have to remind ourselves that this is not a given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merely-curious&quot;&gt;Merely curious&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-6-unpopular-opinions&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;twitter @merely_curious_&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about “peers” is good, because with “people in general” answering the question would be impossible.
Estimate rarity by remembering anecdotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I should not drink alcohol aka there is no point in alcohol” (only 2 peers share).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FIRE is good (only 1 peer shares).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Average” opinions in society are often wrong and one should treat them less seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Age agnosticity when it comes to communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marc--financeyourfire&quot;&gt;Marc @ FinanceYourFire&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/06/15/thought-experiment-oh-hi-marc/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/financeyourfire&quot;&gt;twitter @financeyourfire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A part of me wants to be an outlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The room” - because the movie is so bad, it is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going against the grain just for the sake of it makes no sense, instead you should believe into something and have strong character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being an outlier is relative to the group you compare with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My FIRE plans make me an outlier when compared to my work colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in crypto currency. This does not fit the general FIRE narrative well (too risky).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dr-fire&quot;&gt;Dr FIRE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drfire.co.uk/unpopular-opinion/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DrFIREUK&quot;&gt;twitter @DrFIREUK&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Money
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Invest in equities&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pay attention to personal finance (e.g. seek the best deals, get sign up bonuses)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid credit card debt&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Avoid P2P&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Early retirement is not a goal (i.e. continue working after FI)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Last season of Game of Thrones was good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-simple-life&quot;&gt;A Simple Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/2019/06/14/saving-ninja-thought-experiment-6/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/asimple_life&quot;&gt;twitter @asimple_life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to drink alcohol when I was a teenager.
You don’t have to drink alcohol to have good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People struggle to challenge peer pressure to conform to the unwritten rules of society.
If you want to reach FIRE, you need to learn not to follow the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;money-for-the-modern-girl&quot;&gt;Money For The Modern Girl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moneyforthemoderngirl.org/my-unpopular-opinion-italy-traditions-and-innovation/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MoneyModernGirl&quot;&gt;twitter @MoneyModernGirl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italy is too traditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italians live off their country and have no innovation and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a black market in Italy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;people reporting incomes of less than 20,000 euros (about $26,000) per year cumulatively own 188,000 supercars, 
(such as Ferraris, Lamborghinis, Porsches, or BMW coupes), 518 private airplanes or helicopters, and some 42,000 yachts.”
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2012-01-12/italy-poor-drive-ferraris&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fretful-finance&quot;&gt;Fretful Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fretfulfinance.co.uk/im-a-relationship-and-romance-outlier/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FretfulFinance&quot;&gt;twitter @FretfulFinance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dilemma which topics to choose and how open to be when writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retirement planning could be an option, but readers enjoy it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political views (slightly left)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing details about relationship history feels much harder than personal finance numbers (even though the blog is anonymous).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never had a relationship (early 30s) and wouldn’t be surprised to never have one.
Hard to imagine living together with the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t like wedding, but not anti-marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t like public displays of affection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t want children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t understand obsession with sex and can live without ever having it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a relationship is dictated by the popular culture (music, films, TV).
I actually preferred to be alone (but it took time to understand this).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50% preferring being single, 40% happy to wait and see if something comes along and 
10% actively wanting a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10% above are coming from the fear of loneliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if I manage to form a long-term relationship, I would ideally live close but separately.
In practice, I could imagine moving in for financial reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marriage can be good for tax purposes and to show one’s commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of a wedding itself is absurd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not an asexual, rather the attraction is rarely strong enough to act on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;left-fi&quot;&gt;Left FI&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leftfi.home.blog/2019/06/15/my-unpopular-opinion-public-is-better/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fi_left&quot;&gt;twitter @fi_left&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public ownership is better than private. One can buy something to maximize their short term happiness. 
At the same time, the public sphere (library, park, free health care, public transport) improves life a lot too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;andy--liberatelife-on-rebo&quot;&gt;Andy @ liberate.life (on Rebo)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reboapp.co.uk/blog/2019/06/17/andys-unpopular-opinion/?__s=rcyijymopus5qozgh6si&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reboapp&quot;&gt;twitter @reboapp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-founder of Rebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Altruism is not self-evidently morally good/necessary. Rather, people act in ways that
appear to be self-sacrificial only when it benefits them (even if that benefit is just making them feel ‘good’).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Altruism - acting in such a way that seems to harm your own self interest in order to benefit somebody else’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;james--rebo&quot;&gt;James @ Rebo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reboapp.co.uk/blog/2019/06/17/jamess-unpopular-opinion/?__s=rcyijymopus5qozgh6si&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/reboapp&quot;&gt;twitter @reboapp&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-founder of Rebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As someone on the path to financial independence, or who has achieved financial independence,
you are in an enormously privileged position, and positions of privilege like that come with
increased responsibility for helping others who are less fortunate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A person with more independence in how they spend their time, or with more money, has a larger
duty to help others than someone with fewer resources&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thefirestarter&quot;&gt;theFIREstarter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thefirestarter.co.uk/the-contrarian-thought-experiment-6/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TFSRetireEarly&quot;&gt;twitter @TFSRetireEarly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no free market and the ones we have are highly inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The favorite argument is that advertisement industry is meant to prevent rational buyers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.randomthoughts.fyi/2014/04/free-market-vs-capitalism-what-is-free.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). Another one is absence of the perfect information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everyone can become FIRE (e.g. some people already live frugal enough to have no room for downscaling and no money to save).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible for one to beat the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t DIY everything (trying to do it once yourself is sufficient).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can win money gambling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Thought experiments&quot;]" /><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Saving Ninja had a new thought experiment recently (#6, about unpopular opinions). I again felt like making an overview of responses. Thus, here it is!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How not to get angry?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/not-getting-angry" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How not to get angry?" /><published>2019-06-23T14:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T14:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/not_getting_angry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/not-getting-angry">&lt;p&gt;I’ve discovered a peculiar trick for coping better with negative events
in one’s life. The idea is to try to find a reasonable explanation.
I suspect that this may be connected to meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays it is very easy to be reactive in life. In other words, letting
external events to drive you - your emotions and your actions. The most
prominent example is getting angry when something goes wrong. More often
the target of one’s anger is another person, but it can be a company
or just the situation itself. I don’t see any benefit of such anger. It
does not help to solve the problem, but instead biases your perspective,
can make the problem worse (especially when other people are involved)
or in the best case just takes your time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-little-trick&quot;&gt;My little trick&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve understood that I’ve been using a peculiar trick
in such situations without recognizing it. Imagine that something negative for me happens, which
normally would make me angry. For now, let’s assume that there is another
person involved and this is their fault. The moment this happens, I am immediately
ready to jump into a negative reaction. However, instead of doing this, I try
to take other person’s perspective and see why they could have done what they did. 
In particular, I try to find some plausible explanation of their action.
Ideally the explanation should be such that, if I were in a similar situation,
I could imagine myself doing exactly the same as they did. Somehow once I find such
an explanation (usually this happens very quickly), I don’t feel an urge to
jump into the negative state at all. Unfortunately, I don’t know why this works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider an example. You take an underground and there are construction works.
As a result your train does not go directly to where you need (as it normally would),
instead you have to e.g. stop and switch trains. Our natural reaction would be -
“this is a bad service, why do I have to pay for this, I hate this company, they
always have these problems, I am angry”. However, one can pause for a moment and try
to imagine themselves leading such a company. It is actually hard. And stuff breaks
a lot, so one needs to repair and maintain. Thus, I would likely do exactly the same
closures to be able to do construction works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example is crossing a street on a crosswalk. Let’s say we are in a country where it is common
for cars to give way to pedestrians on crosswalks. Then imagine that a car
does not give way. I.e. you had to stop for them to drive by, otherwise, you would 
probably get hit. Again, the first reaction is exactly the same as above. 
However, if I were a driver, I could imagine various situations. First, this is just
a game of probability, so even if I were a very strict driver, eventually some coincidences
would align and I could do something similar (e.g. just not noticing pedestrian by
chance). Or perhaps the driver was really badly in a hurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is easier to do in situations involving other people (since there is some
other perspective to take). However, with some practice one can do something
similar for general situations. E.g. one started having foot pain. It is very
easy to be sad and angry about this. Instead one can remember that they did
a lot of aggressive running recently and shouldn’t have pushed that far.
Somehow this helps to cope with the situation better and avoid emotional
reaction at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prerequisites&quot;&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that meditation can be a prerequisite for this trick.
In other words, whenever an emotional reaction happens, one needs to stop
and don’t follow that reaction, but start reflecting instead. I speculate
that meditation helps with this. That’s partially how meditation works - you
get thoughts, but choose not to follow them. Thus, if you have difficulties
with going to the meta level instead of an emotional reaction - perhaps try a meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may also be related to emotional intelligence and empathy. In order to find
a plausible explanation, you really need to take other person’s perspective and
imagine yourself in it. This can be non-trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mechanism&quot;&gt;Mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, I don’t know how or why this works. I suspect that finding a
plausible explanation may be not the key. E.g. it could be that getting
distracted is the most important part. In other words, perhaps if you just
start dancing when you feel an emotional reaction to a negative effect,
this could have a similar distracting effect. This is an open question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-step-further&quot;&gt;One step further&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to just somehow rationalize a situation or look at it from a different
perspective instead of getting angry. In our underground example, one can try to remember
how often does something like this happen. In my case, it was not often and this did help
me to have a healthier view on the situation. Alternatively one can treat almost any situation
as an adventure. E.g. in the underground case, one was passing this station numerous times
and it just felt boring, but here something new is happening and this feels like an adventure
and adds variety into life. I agree that this may sound artificial, but I hope that you
see the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy conscious reactions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="perspective" /><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html">I’ve discovered a peculiar trick for coping better with negative events in one’s life. The idea is to try to find a reasonable explanation. I suspect that this may be connected to meditation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Brokers monthly fee</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Brokers monthly fee" /><published>2019-06-18T23:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T23:30:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive_brokers_monthly_fee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/interactive-brokers-monthly-fee">&lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers have monthly “inactivity” (aka Monthly Minimum) fee.
It is not obvious how one can see this fee being applied.
Here is one way (spoiler: through statements).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interactive Brokers have somewhat unusual fee structure 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interactivebrokers.com/en/index.php?f=4969&quot;&gt;official source&lt;/a&gt;),
which is always a pain to explain. Basically, they require one to spend at least
10 USD for trading transactions per month. If one spends less, they anyway charge the difference
up to 10 USD and call this “inactivity” fee. However, they remove this fee
if one has 100k USD (or equivalent, e.g. in stocks) with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an account for quite some time with IB now, but I have never seen this “inactivity” fee
in action. In other words - when is it charged? How much did I actually pay?
What if I misunderstand the system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I have found only one way to observe this fee - through statements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Left Menu &amp;gt; Reports &amp;gt; Statements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Default Statements”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Activity” statement type.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose  “Year to Date” period.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Run Statement”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for “Fees” section and open it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/ib_monthly_fee/fee_statement_screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Fee section from the statement showing the fee for April applied in May.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, in this case the fee for April was applied in May and it was 2.37 EUR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy transparent and easy to understand fees!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;Investing&quot;]" /><category term="Interactive Brokers" /><category term="fees" /><summary type="html">Interactive Brokers have monthly “inactivity” (aka Monthly Minimum) fee. It is not obvious how one can see this fee being applied. Here is one way (spoiler: through statements).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to connect a Namecheap domain to Linode?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting-namecheap-domain-to-linode" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to connect a Namecheap domain to Linode?" /><published>2019-06-11T23:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-11T23:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting_namecheap_domain_to_linode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/connecting-namecheap-domain-to-linode">&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I need to link a domain parked at Namecheap to a Linode
and each time I forget how to do it. Thus, here is a guide
(i.e. a cheat-sheet for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;linode-part&quot;&gt;Linode part&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-link-a-domain-to-your-linode-account&quot;&gt;To link a domain to your Linode account&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Linode account dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Create” dropdown and select “Domain”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose “Master”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type the domain (without www).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enter some email as “SOA Email Address” (this will be public, e.g. can be looked up with 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mxtoolbox.com/SOALookup.aspx&quot;&gt;this tool&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Do not insert default records for me”. Alternatively you can select “Insert default records
from one of my Linodes” and select the target Linode machine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Click “Create” button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-link-a-domain-to-a-specific-linode&quot;&gt;To link a domain to a specific Linode.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you linked a domain to your account, you can connect it to a specific Linode:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open Linode account dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy the target Linode machine IPv4 address.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open “Domains” on the left.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select the target domain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add A/AAAA record with the IPv4 address and empty hostname.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy IPv6 address.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add A/AAAA record with the IPv6 address and empty hostname.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;namecheap-part&quot;&gt;Namecheap part&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to a given domain dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set “Nameservers” to “Custom DNS” (by default it is Namecheap BasicDNS).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add “ns1.linode.com”, “ns2.linode.com” and so on up to “ns5.linode.com” as nameservers
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linode.com/docs/platform/manager/dns-manager/#use-linode-s-name-servers-with-your-domain&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To save, click at the green checkmark (righthand side from “Custom DNS” dropdown).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait until the change is propagated across the world (1-2 days, but often 5-10 minutes can be enough).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linode.com/docs/platform/manager/dns-manager/&quot;&gt;Linode docs about DNS Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="[&quot;How-to&quot;]" /><category term="how-to" /><category term="technical" /><summary type="html">Occasionally I need to link a domain parked at Namecheap to a Linode and each time I forget how to do it. Thus, here is a guide (i.e. a cheat-sheet for me).</summary></entry></feed>