<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://merelycurious.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-17T09:02:54+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Merely curious</title><subtitle>Everything I find interesting enough.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment overview: projects when FIRE’d</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment overview: projects when FIRE'd" /><published>2019-04-17T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-17T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_overview_projects_when_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-overview-projects-when-fire">&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what other people are going to do once they reach FIRE
(based on their responses to SavingNinja thought experiment #5).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;my response to the previous thought experiment&lt;/a&gt;
I thought
that it would be cool to write an overview of all the responses. Perhaps
there are some patterns and peculiarities. This is my first attempt at this.
Obviously I have no clue where this will go, but I will just start reading
all the responses and then see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please find it in &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1uDRC1HheipxzNJWfaS-xhy2aj7NPqLD5ndsu_gRmGMg/preview&quot;&gt;this Google Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions--peculiarities-discovered&quot;&gt;Conclusions / peculiarities discovered&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were 2 ways to understand the problem statement. One is to describe
what you will do once you reach FIRE somewhen in future (i.e. after your normal
FIRE date). Another is to assume that you magically reach FIRE today (at least
3 responses did this).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I forgot about some stuff when was writing my post, like reading and languages.
However, this probably just illustrates that these are less important for me.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One can use this overview to find like minded people,
e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/&quot;&gt;Sam @ A Simple Life&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://thefireshrink.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;The FIRE Shrink&lt;/a&gt; would both
like to do more gardening once reaching FIRE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surprisingly, at least 4 responses do include part time work
and only one (&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-fire-now-what/amp/?__twitter_impression=true&quot;&gt;Marc @ Finance Your Fire&lt;/a&gt;) says 100% no to work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For some reason, learning French is very popular (at least 3 responses).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only one post was from an already retired author (&lt;a href=&quot;https://youngfiguy.com/retiring-from-retiring/&quot;&gt;Young FI Guy&lt;/a&gt;), I did enjoy their perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-notes&quot;&gt;My notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure why you would like to read them, but below all the notes I took
while reading the responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;savingninja&quot;&gt;SavingNinja&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-will-i-do-when-i-retire/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not fired yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do people want FI? They want time (like during their childhood).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always wanted to be a game developer, but went to mobile development for money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dream: having a title on Steam (or Project Stadia).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a novel (an epic fantasy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating my own mobile apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building (shed, sawmill, barn, stables, home)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-deed-a-bly&quot;&gt;in-deed-a-bly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indeedably.com/whats-next/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not fired yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes one project to be done in the nearest future
(next step for personal finance and budgeting software).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get an impression that the author assumed that “they have reached FI today,
what would they do”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;caveman--ditchthecave&quot;&gt;CaveMan @ DitchTheCave&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ditchthecave.com/when-i-grow-up/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes their experiences during Brexit vote day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to the gym multiple times a week (plus possibly some sword fighting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to bed whenever feeling like it, the same for waking up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning. French and Spanish. Joining a choir, relearning the piano.
Doing a masters degree in Shakespeare.
Doing this already, but giving more time and attention after FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteering (conservation works in the countryside).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow travel. Spending weeks rather than days, being able to speak the language and culture immersion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buying 1€ house in Italy. Training at Muay Thai camp in Thailand. Going to India or Bali to become a qualified yoga teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decompressing and understanding real priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fears. Absence of motivation to stay fit, family rejection, busy friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-way-to-less&quot;&gt;A Way to Less&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awaytoless.com/thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assumption: hitting FI today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably continuing working part time as a transition before the trip to Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning Swahili and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport: training better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending more time with family (e.g. niece) and friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength training 3 or 4 times a week instead of 2 now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing learning to do handstand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food - interesting restaurants and trying different cuisines from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finishing DIY projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the trip, probably quiting work.
Doing another trip, but to South America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a family (having a kid).
Full time parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More slow travel.
Spending more time with their partner.
Improve at sports.
Watch sporting events and music.
Play music.
Volunteer.
Building a house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cashflow-cop&quot;&gt;Cashflow Cop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cashflowcop.com/beyond-financial-independence-tracing-my-roots/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dream of not being tied to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of usual “stuff” they could do
(spending time with their wife and kids, traveling, reading, writing, learning to play piano, carpentry, photography, build our forever home, gym, hiking, learning French)
but there is no point to go into this.
Let’s rather consider a project, for which he will have more time and energy once FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Describes his childhood visit back to the country of origin 9 years after leaving for the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is to return to the native country, but not for a holiday.
Understand history and culture. Know their relatives better.
Enable children to understand roots and mother-tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity work in their birth country - helping children to get out of poverty.
Probably introducing financial literacy as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their wife is worried, that they will be too busy during FIRE.
Family is the highest priority, especially after FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merely-curious&quot;&gt;Merely curious&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No precise projects, since plenty of time before FIRE to achieve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programming, data analysis, making websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing projects differently - sprinting (focusing on one project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects are defined very broadly (a finite chunk of work with a title).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derailing into how to collect ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing more in the blog, including posts requiring more time.
Art (juggling with humor, learning to draw, playing music and composing).
DIY - sewing. 
Cooking - more unusual and time consuming dishes, including for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggests to upscale current lifestyle in FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably stand up comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sport (everyday)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubt whether answered Saving Ninja question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving short term examples (FIRE game, making rain-stick, FIRE calculator).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sam--a-simple-life&quot;&gt;Sam @ A Simple Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://asimplelifewithsam.com/2019/04/15/ninja-thought-experiment-5/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentioning MMM advice to see what you are doing on weekends these days
and to expand it to the full week once FI. MMM suggests to think in terms of
the following categories: outdoors, social, physical, generous and challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More time for garden. Growing vegetables all year round.
Selling some produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being much more active member of existing social groups in the village.
Posting more on Twitter and other social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking more. Cycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More direct charity helping work (once a week or once a fortnight).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning French and Italian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doubt whether answered Saving Ninja question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gentlemans-family-finances&quot;&gt;Gentleman’s Family Finances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gentlemansfamilyfinances.wordpress.com/2019/03/15/saving-ninja-thought-experient5-from-gff/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving advice to the readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoying art and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on longevity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having passion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travel, trying new things, have friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DIY,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t ask me exactly what I want to do – I haven’t a clue!
But it will be fun whatever it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;marc--finance-your-fire&quot;&gt;Marc @ Finance Your Fire&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://financeyourfire.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-fire-now-what/amp/?__twitter_impression=true&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially: visiting coffee shops, practicing doing nothing, reading books, travel,
contemplating, donating time (volunteering), smiling to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could one get Olympic depression syndrome after FI?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pledging not to return to earning money after FI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not going to work either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making music (electronic, DJ skills).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing and painting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a book (a novel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t underestimate boredom.
Without it you can’t have its counterpart states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marc is not scared of boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traveling more with his brother
(but not for the traveling sake, rather to relax, enjoy life, do nothing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fire-shrink&quot;&gt;The FIRE Shrink&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thefireshrink.wordpress.com/2019/04/15/thought-experiment-5-the-grid-what-grid/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participating first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably continuing working part time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already started projects.
Learning welding and sheet metal work.
Learning languages.
Overlanding.
More renovation projects in the UK.
Grow more food, keep more animals, experiment with brewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;young-fi-guy&quot;&gt;Young FI Guy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youngfiguy.com/retiring-from-retiring/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already retired.
“Retire from retiring”.
It is important to put up with shit in your life (like vaccinations).
Complete absence of nonsense makes very minor nonsense seem worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at part time jobs (1-2 days a week).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fretful-finance&quot;&gt;Fretful Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fretfulfinance.co.uk/what-are-my-plans-for-retirement/&quot;&gt;Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the first time participating in “thought experiment”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plans to travel, relax, go to theater more and enjoy leisurely lunches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catch up on a lot of TV (series and movies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part time work (a metaphysical supply store).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteering for a charity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rollercoaster and Theme Park blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="overview" /><summary type="html">Let’s see what other people are going to do once they reach FIRE (based on their responses to SavingNinja thought experiment #5).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thought experiment: projects after FIRE’d</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thought experiment: projects after FIRE'd" /><published>2019-04-14T22:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-14T22:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/thought_experiment_projects_when_fire</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/thought-experiment-projects-when-fire">&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you have finally FIRE’d and now you are bored. Which projects would you?
This is the new shiny thought experiment by SavingNinja. And I have a lot to do, indeed…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get to my response, let me introduce the concept, so that you understand all the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preamble&quot;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/category/thought-experiments/&quot;&gt;“Thought experiments”&lt;/a&gt;
is a project by SavingNinja. The idea is that some hypothetical situation is posted every 2 months
and participants must write down their thoughts without any preparation or major editing.
This should uncover their inner views and feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took part last time and the topic was “If You Lost Everything” (&lt;a href=&quot;/post/thought-experiment-losing-everything&quot;&gt;my response&lt;/a&gt;).
Without doubt it was much darker, but nevertheless interesting experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;projects-after-fire-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;“Projects after FIRE” thought experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experiment’s page is &lt;a href=&quot;https://thesavingninja.com/what-will-i-do-when-i-retire&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
(it also contains links to other bloggers’ posts)
and the “problem” statement is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Life is good. You finally did it! You pulled the plug on your day job after reaching financial independence. 
You never have to work for money ever again. But, you’re bored. You need something to do… You need a project! 
You grab a piece of paper and a pen and start thinking. Now that you’re financially free,
what projects do you want to complete? However ambitious, however small,
you now have the time to pursue anything that you like, what will you accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-reply&quot;&gt;My reply&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-reading-the-new-experiment&quot;&gt;Before reading the new experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I am doing the writing in the morning to avoid any scary dreams during the night
(I didn’t have any last time, but just in case).
Let’s see what Savings Ninja prepared for us.
In his tweet he wrote that not everyone will be able to “partake” in this one, so I am curious why.
My guesses are that this could be related to gender (but this would be weird) or perhaps FIRE status
(e.g. a question to already FIRE’d people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-reading-the-new-experiment&quot;&gt;After reading the new experiment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny, this one seems pretty easy.
Basically what I want to do (focusing more on projects side) once I “retire”.
Obviously, I can’t tell precise projects, because I may accomplish some of them before FIRE,
however, I can definitely try to explain the general theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I have plenty of random ideas for projects already today.
These are mostly related to programming, data analysis and making websites.
I would definitely spend more time on these. However, currently almost all of them tend to have some 
money making part and this could go away once I FIRE. I can’t say that I explicitly filter my projects
to make money (I don’t drop ideas, which are unlikely to make money), but I get majority of ideas
like that anyway. So it is probably something inside me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I would probably try doing my projects differently once I FIRE. Currently there is always not enough time
and I can spend only small portion of my time on my projects. As a result they all take multiple weeks.
I would definitely try doing sprinting more (e.g. one week or even entire month for one project full time).
Not sure whether this would work perfectly, because I may then get bored, I like to have many ongoing things at once
and jump back and forth between projects, which interest me the most. However, trying won’t hurt me and having a reasonably
finished project in a reasonable time might feel pleasant too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I probably should explain more what I mean by projects. As I said, there is not much point
to talk about specific ideas, since I will probably address majority of items on my list
before FIRE. However, by projects I don’t mean something large. It can be pretty small.
I also don’t have any specific limitations for my projects. If it looks like a finite chunk of work
not related to other things I am doing and for which I can define an actionable target
and a title, this is already a project in my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have multiple lists in my life, because ideas (sometimes even good) come randomly,
so I try to make it as easy as possible to record them and whenever there is any urgent need,
I don’t have to come up with ideas, but just check my list. In some sense, I precache my ideas
for some topics to save time later when there is a need for that topic. I should write a post
about this (I can call it “Catching ideas”). Here are couple of ideas for the post, so that I
don’t forget: I suspect that the rate with which ideas appear is constant (assuming that you 
don’t have major lifestyle changes). Thus, one should optimize how easy it is to record them
and time for how long one collects them. It is similar to having a net and just catching some
fruits falling from a tree. It is important to write even “bad” ideas, the first impression may be wrong,
deleting an idea later is easy, you may learn something new later, which will change your perspective.
For me ideas usually come as a reaction to something I saw or read. Occasionally this can be a
combination of multiple sources. You actually saw above how I got an idea for the new post. 
Now I have added this to my internal list of ideas for blog posts. As you might have noticed I have
&lt;a href=&quot;/queue/&quot;&gt;a public list of ideas for blog posts&lt;/a&gt; 
as well. Actually I think I have too many blog post ideas and not
enough free time for all of them. As a result, I publish some of them just as ideas (I should definitely publish a new batch)
and then see which ones people visit the most. This helps me to prioritize. Having too many ideas 
(or in other words choosing which ones to pursue) is the next problem you have pretty quickly
once you develop a good idea “catching” approach. You could say that I could choose the ones I like the most,
the issue is that I like almost all of them :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I got derailed badly. Sorry, sorry. Regarding projects, even a larger blog post requiring 
some research is a project. It has an actionable goal - write a blog post about X - and a title e.g. “blogpost X”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I don’t think I would be able to work full-time on my projects, because it is pretty demanding work.
I can’t be sure, but I suspect that I won’t. E.g. currently on weekends I rarely have 8 hours of 
clean “project” work. I definitely won’t force myself, because then I will just hate all my projects and that’s
not my goal. As a result, I would likely do something else in addition to projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense I may now derail into general “life after FIRE” instead of “projects after FIRE”, but the term “project”
is very broad for me, so it is ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would definitely write more in my blog. Probably even somewhat weirder blog posts, which currently I filter out
because it feels like I am the only one interested, but then I could give a try to a couple. I think I would do
more blog posts requiring more background work. Currently, when I have not that much free time, spending entire week
on one blog post feels wasteful. Sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I would try to develop artistic part of me more. Currently, this feels like it is not worth it, because this is
mostly just for myself, but I definitely feel desire to try. One way would be to improve my juggling skills and then
start juggling for other people entertainment. I enjoy combination of juggling and humor very much and I think that
juggling provides a lot of opportunities (failing can be fun) and I would try to develop some small act of mine
involving juggling and trying to be funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am also interested to learn how to draw. However, I am extremely bad at this right now and it feels like this will take
me eternity. So for now it is again not worth it, but when I have more free time I would try for sure. Another similar
area is music (playing music instruments and composing). Here I am probably even worse than with drawing. I would be
interested to moderately develop my skills. Perhaps I am just curious whether I just don’t have ability (which I don’t
believe, but this could be the first example) or just didn’t spend enough time practicing effectively. Currently both drawing
and music look like magic to me. Moving something from “magic” to normal life is a wonderful feeling, which I greatly enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I could do more DIY, e.g. currently sewing interests me as another medium of expression. Making a couple clothing items
looks interesting. Probably now you understand the name of my blog. When I see my lists of things I could do I occasionally
get a feeling that I may be even too curious sometimes. I hope that this does not harm me, but prioritization is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, also cooking. I enjoy cooking. I feel like the result is often multiple times better than the effort involved.
I also like to cook kinds of food, which normally everyone just buys and few people think how to cook it from scratch.
Sometimes cooking such food is extremely
easy, so I end up cooking it every now and then even though everyone else just buys it. One example is bread. After
some practice, baking bread becomes extremely simple and fast (in terms of active time spent - not waiting). After FIRE
I would cook unusual and more time consuming dishes more often. Perhaps even I would cook for other people. 
Currently I often cook something quick, because again - time. I extremely rarely cook for other people these days, but this is
a very important part of cooking in my view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, ok, this is much longer text than I originally expected. It also didn’t go that easy at the beginning, but now
I completely missed how I wrote that much. I feel a bit weird, because Savings Ninja might have meant more
concrete project ideas here, but my concrete planning horizon is not that long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also why would I actually wait until FIRE to do something? It becomes apparent from the text above that I will be doing either
more of or just more intensively stuff I am doing right now. I think that this is how it should be, because you should live a good
life now and not somewhen in future. So if I had some super interesting project, I don’t think I would ever say “oh, cool, let’s wait
until FIRE to do it”. Ok, in some sense I am doing this for my artsy ideas (e.g. juggling with humor), but I juggle these
days as well. So again I will be doing something similar, but in a more time consuming manner after FIRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way stand-up comedy interests me as well, but probably not as much as stuff above since I remembered about it only
now. But I can imagine giving it a try. I would also experiment more with my life and try new things for sure .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would do sport more often (like everyday). This is hard to call a project, but I would love to do more sport
and currently (again) have not much time for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calm down my inner self, I can give you a couple of things I am working right now, which you can use as a basis to extrapolate
what I will be doing after FIRE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger projects:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I am making a FIRE game (it is in some sense a simulator of life with FIRE related bits). This is a very early stage, so
nothing to show yet. I will definitely make a post about it and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I saw an interesting African music instrument in a museum (known as rain-stick) and now I would like to reproduce it at home. 
The original one used some plant parts, which I am going to replace with pistachio shells. Currently I am at “collecting
pistachio shells” stage. Since I don’t eat pistachio that often (even though I avoid expensive 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/crazy-pistachio&quot;&gt;“crazy pistachio”&lt;/a&gt;
I saw recently, they are still pricey enough to be enjoyed moderately), this takes time. This is also an example of a project, which is interesting, but does not have that much of a practical benefit. I should make a blog post about this as well.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pages/calculator.html&quot;&gt;FIRE calculator&lt;/a&gt; which tells how saving or spending X euro affects your FIRE date
(i.e. how many days sooner or later it will be).
I made a rough prototype, but then I got busy with other projects and now this one waits for its golden time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for blog posts you can have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;/queue/&quot;&gt;my public post idea list&lt;/a&gt;.
Every view counts and affects what I will write about next, so
thank you a lot for your help! As I said, prioritization is hard and you help me enormously by somewhat implicitly expressing your interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh and thank you a lot, Savings Ninja, for making me think and even write about all of these. Everyone should do this occasionally,
even people not interested in FIRE. FIRE definitely promotes such thinking and makes “what I want to do with my life” question
much more burning, since you can get more freedom to actually do something with your life. I am pretty sure that my views will
somewhat change by the time I reach FIRE, I don’t think that this will be a major change, but definitely polishing of some details.
I also claim that answering this question can be a game changer for FIRE. I don’t have practical
experience, but I suspect that if you go into FIRE without clear understand what you enjoy and want to do, the free time you will
have will be like a punishment for you. It will be just boring, because there won’t be anything really interesting to do.
So it is better to start thinking about this earlier or even building some version of the life you want already before FIRE 
and then just upscaling this life. I hope that my approach (having a lot of time shortage now and just satisfying this demand
in FIRE) will work. What is also funny, that I have never noticed before that I implicitly cut so many activities due to time shortage.
Without an overview in one place, I noticed that I stopped myself sometimes from doing something time-consuming,
but this felt like rather rare incidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now extremely curious why not everyone may be able to partake in this experiment? Did Saving Ninja mean people who are not
trying to reach FIRE? But they probably won’t read his blog that much. Hm. Something is weird here. I should ask him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I forgot, after the last thought experiment, I thought that it would be cool to compare responses of other people (i.e. 
categorize them and make a table with an overview). This time I am going to do this. Unfortunately, I can’t do this now,
because there is nothing to read yet, so I will have to wait until people start publishing. So if you are curious
to get a general overview, come back in couple days (or perhaps a week to be sure), I will post a link here (and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/merely_curious_&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; as well).
This must be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thought experiment" /><category term="about me" /><summary type="html">Imagine that you have finally FIRE’d and now you are bored. Which projects would you? This is the new shiny thought experiment by SavingNinja. And I have a lot to do, indeed…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What are you actually paying for?</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/what-you-pay-for-or-second-class-apples" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are you actually paying for?" /><published>2019-04-12T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-12T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/what_you_pay_for_or_second_class_apples</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/what-you-pay-for-or-second-class-apples">&lt;p&gt;I’ve accidentally bought second class apples, which were not bad at all.
This made me think that I’ve been paying more for the first class apples without explicitly realizing this.
Let’s see why this is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a “weekly” discount for apples (1 euro for 2 kilos) in Edeka.
I discovered this in their “prospekt” (I wrote about supermarket discounts 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/weekly-discounts-in-german-supermarkets&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
However, once I bought them (actually 6 kilograms), I discovered that they were
“the second class”. Obviously, they did not look terribly bad, otherwise I would have
noticed this earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home I had a more careful look. Indeed there was something unusual with 90% of apples.
They had small damages or imperfections (at most 1 cm^2 in area, but most of them even much smaller than that).
In my life I definitely have seen and even eaten apples, which were in a much worse condition (I can clearly
remember an apple, which was in such a bad state, that I had to cut out almost half of it, but I ate the rest).
If you compare these second class apples to what I had before, they are then rather 99%
perfect. Here you basically cut out one very small piece and you get a perfectly fine apple.
Obviously, you probably can’t store them as long as the first class apples, but I bought only 6 kilograms
(not a tonne).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me this uncovered an interesting issue. Such second class apples is a pretty rare guest in the supermarkets.
I have seen apples for “processing” (Verarbeitung) before, these had no damages, but mostly weird shape instead.
As far as I understood, they were meant for juicing. Obviously I also bought and ate them (and they were just fine).
Apart from that all apples I observed in supermarkets are the first class (i.e. ideal shape and state).
This is probably the first time I explicitly saw second class apples being sold. 
However, when I buy the first class apples, I actually pay premium for them to be the first class.
Since I haven’t thought about this before and never even had a choice, I was doing this implicitly.
And as I learned after buying the second class apples, paying this premium actually makes no sense to me.
I am as happy to consume second class apples as the first class. Basically, someone has made this decision
not to bring second class apples to the market that often and now all buyers are paying more for their
apples to be ideal (due to absence of choice), but without realizing and enjoying this. 
I consider this premium a waste of money from buyer perspective, since without having a reference point
(a concept which I learned during “Science of Wellbeing” course, my summary is 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
of second class apples, they can’t enjoy how the first class apples are better than the second.
For them, these are just normal average boring apples, not “not a second class” apples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I am definitely curious which other premiums I’ve been paying for without realizing.
Unfortunately, identifying them is extremely tricky (unless you accidentally stumble on a product
without this premium feature like these second class apples), so I couldn’t come up with anything yet, but I am
now very vigilant. Perhaps you have encountered some other examples already?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, happy conscious shopping!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="saving" /><category term="expenses" /><summary type="html">I’ve accidentally bought second class apples, which were not bad at all. This made me think that I’ve been paying more for the first class apples without explicitly realizing this. Let’s see why this is bad.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lecture 6)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lecture 6)" /><published>2019-04-07T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lecture_6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lecture-6">&lt;p&gt;Continuing watching and writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”.
Lecture 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-6-behavioral-genetics-i&quot;&gt;Lecture 6: Behavioral Genetics I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how the methodology for studying genetic component of behavior changed with time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;species&quot;&gt;Species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the field started, people assumed that &lt;del&gt;if a trait is universal in a species, it must be genetic&lt;/del&gt;.
This is very limited approach, which works for flies, but does not for more complex organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;families&quot;&gt;Families&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step was to consider families. The closer related two individuals are, the more genes they share.
If you have a behavioral trait that becomes more common the more closely related two individuals are,
it must have genetic component. However, the more related two individuals are, the more they share their environment
as well. Thus, with this approach one cannot distinguish genetic component of behavior from environmental influence.
This was a classic approach 70-80 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;twins&quot;&gt;Twins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then let’s control for environment. Examine relatives in the same environment, but having different genes.
For example, one can consider identical (monozygotic) twins (sharing 100% genes) vs fraternal (dizygotic) twins
(sharing 50% genes). If they all live in the same environment and fraternal twins differ in some way, while
identical twins don’t - this must have genetic basis. Problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sometimes fraternal twins have different sex -&amp;gt; let’s restrict to same sex fraternal twins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;These twins are still treated differently as pairs. As a result, there is more environment differentiation for fraternal twins.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identical twins can have one or two placentas (based on when the split happened - before or after 5 days since fertilization).
In one placenta case, they have same blood flow. With two placentas - there can be differences in blood flow.
As a result, in one placenta case they have much more similar environment.
For example, they are more likely to have similar IQ when having one placenta (when compared to two placenta case).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;different-sexes&quot;&gt;Different sexes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we have everything exactly the same except sex? Does not work either.
1 hour old boys have more arm movement than girls. However, moms already (from the first time 
they hold the child) treat them differently (holding for different duration of time and in different proximity to
their face).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sat-scores-and-gender-study&quot;&gt;SAT scores and gender study&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One loud example of this is a study about 13 year old pupils’ SAT scores in math.
In particular, how they depend on sex. The results were that more boys had higher scores.
The paper was published in Nature and concluded that since they had the same lessons
(there was no school curriculum differentiation yet at that age), this must be a biological difference.
Press quickly called this “the math gene” and it was claimed that boys tended to have it more often.
However, there were differences in their environment. Other studies has shown that even in the first grade
a boy is more likely to be called when raising his hand for a math problem. Boys are also more likely
to be praised for correct answers in elementary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adoption-studies&quot;&gt;Adoption studies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at individuals raised in the same environment, but with different genes (adoption studies).
Consider someone who was adopted as a child. Who are they more likely to share a trait with -
biological parents or adoptive? In animals this can be done by cross-fostering,
i.e. switching newborns (or only 50% of them) across mothers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;biological-component-of-schizophrenia&quot;&gt;Biological component of schizophrenia&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seymour Kety tried to test whether schizophrenia has biologic component
(The significance of genetic factors in the etiology of schizophrenia: Results from the national study of adoptees in Denmark, 1987). 
The study considered adopted individuals who had schizophrenia. Are they more likely to share this trait with their
biological or adoptive parents? Entire database of adoptees in Denmark was researched (Scandinavian countries
record a lot of data). In general population probability to develop schizophrenia is 1%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Probability to develop schizophrenia based on whether biological/adoptive parents have schizophrenia.
Numbers are from the course. The original source: Seymour Kety,
“The significance of genetic factors in the etiology of schizophrenia: Results from the national study of adoptees in Denmark”, 1987&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Biological parents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;!-- schizophrenia --&gt;
&lt;!-- no schizophrenia --&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;no schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;adoptive&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;no schizophrenia&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, having biological parent with schizophrenia increases probability, having both (biological and adoptive) - increases it even further
(non-additive synergisms). This was the first study to show heritable basis for a psychiatric disorder. This became a gold standard for
behavioral genetics studies. People started applying this approach to depression, alcoholism, criminal behavior. They observed similar
results. Problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the adoption does not happen immediately after the birth.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prenatal environment shared with mom (this can be measured by difference of probability to share a trait with mom and dad).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paternity uncertainty - sometimes a person claiming to be a father is not a father.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adoptive family placements are not random (in some countries like US kids are matched across a lot of domains before adoption).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identical-twins-separated-at-birth&quot;&gt;Identical twins separated at birth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best approach so far is to consider identical twins separated at birth (they can be adopted in different households).
This uncovers 50% heritability of IQ, position on introvert-extrovert scale, degree of aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem: non-random placements. To mitigate, compare similarities between monozygotic and dizygotic twins (they both have non-random
placement), but this makes the sample size small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-at-non-learned-traits&quot;&gt;Looking at non-learned traits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we consider traits which happen without learning? 
E.g. smiling (even blind babies smile), beginning to babble at the same age
(even for deaf babies). Random observation - even fetuses smile during third trimester.
Prenatal effects can affect such traits too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;environment-begins-earlier-than-birth&quot;&gt;Environment begins earlier than birth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider some ways which can affect the child before birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharing-blood-with-mom&quot;&gt;Sharing blood with mom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hormones&quot;&gt;Hormones&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats have dozen of fetuses which have more similar blood environment with adjacent sibling fetuses.
As a result, the more male siblings a rat fetus has adjacent to them, the later it will reach puberty 
(local endocrine effects).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Children born to younger or older mothers reach puberty later (due to lower estrogen levels in mothers).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stress in mother propagates to fetus through stress hormones. In rats this causes smaller brain in adulthood,
thinner cortex, less learning abilities, more prone towards anxiety, stronger cognitive decline in old age.
This also decreases brain region responsible for dealing with stress hormones. As a result such offsprings 
have more stress hormones themselves. Their offsprings will be affected even more by this. This environmental effect
can be observed even in grand children (“the grandmother effect”). I.e. this is inheriting of a non-genetic trait
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;non-Mendelian inheritance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nutrients&quot;&gt;Nutrients.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_famine_of_1944%E2%80%9345&quot;&gt;Dutch Hunger Winter&lt;/a&gt; - almost immediate decline in available
food due to war in winter 1944.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Third trimester fetuses learn how many calories are available in the world during a specific time period.
They “study” nutritional profile. Then based on the results they can “choose” how their body should function through metabolic programming.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Individuals who were third trimester fetuses during Dutch Hunger Winter (i.e. built their nutritional profile during the famine) were
trying to store as much nutrients as possible and their kidneys tried to store more salt as well.
When normal diet returned (also almost immediate change) - affected individuals showed 19x increase in incidents of obesity,
diabetes, hypertension, metabolic syndrome. This is a very dramatic difference.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This did not happen to newborns or first trimester fetuses. This is now studied as part of “fetal origins of adult diseases”.
E.g. stress hormones during fetal life cause higher anxiety in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;People in Stalingrad didn’t get this effect, because there the food decrease was steady.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What happens when people affected get pregnant themselves? Their bodies take too much calories from blood,
and as a result fetus is born with mild version of “Dutch Hunger Winter” phenomenon (again non-Mendelian inheritance).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Females (including in humans) can consume different amounts of estrogen (E.g. vitoestrogen from plants).
When consumed more - fetus has consistent increase in estrogen dependent breast cancer in adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In rats one can inject sucrose water with particular taste (fetuses drink amniotic fluid).
 After birth this taste will be preferred when given a choice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mom’s voice in humans. Fetuses hear a lot, but especially moms voice. 
When reading “Cat in hat” a lot out loud vs random collection of sentences (controlled for length and rhytmicity),
newborns prefer “Cat in hat” (they make sucking motion when they like something). When fathers read, this does not work
anymore.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;. Environment does not being at birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember strains of rats with different levels of anxiety mentioned in previous lectures? There was “an adoption” study,
where fetuses were transfered during pregnancy. As a result, it was not a genetic trait, but a prenatal effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;genetic-influence-from-mother&quot;&gt;Genetic influence from mother&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see more shared traits with mother than with father, these can be attributed to prenatal effects.
However, one gets more genetic influence from mother, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when father is not real father&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mitochondria has its own DNA. Sperm does not carry mitochondria, but only DNA. As a result, one inherits all their
mitochondria DNA from mother.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;imprinted genes - work differently based on whom they come from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sperm does not have transcription factors. All transcription factors in a fertilized egg are from mother.
Imagine there is a transcription factor A and it is needed to produce more of A and to activate gene X.
If due to an environmental change, A stops being produced, there will be no A in the egg and
this will disable X for offsprings forever (i.e. genes are inherited, but won’t be expressed due to acquired trait in mother - lamarckian traits).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indirect-genetic-effects&quot;&gt;Indirect genetic effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There can also be indirect genetic effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider 50% heritability of your position on introvert-extrovert scale.
This conclusion held through all the concerns above.
However, height and appearance are highly inheritable.
Taller people are treated better and considered more attractive.
People treated more positively during childhood become more extroverted. Most of introvert-extrovert heritability
is mediated by heritability of physical traits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heritability of rank in turkeys - actually it is due to the color of their feathers, which is inherited.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicks are able to peck for grabs very early. However, newborn chicks have heritable tendency to find their toes very
interesting, as a result they peck at their toes and learn to do proper pecking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;70% heritability of political party affiliation in US. Mediating variable - how people feel about ambiguity. Conservatives
are more ambiguity averse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rats and mouse strains with various levels of aggression. Mediation: aggressive strains have lower threshold for pain sensitivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;epigenetic-effects&quot;&gt;Epigenetic effects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DNA cover can block transcription factors from reaching DNA permanently.
This happened in Dutch Hunger Winter people. 
Another example: pet newborn rat for 3 min/day for 2 weeks after it is born -&amp;gt; larger brain, better learning.
Pet it for 1.5 hours/day instead -&amp;gt; smaller brain, shorter life expectancy.
It is interesting what counts as stimulation (3 min) vs stress (1.5 hours). However, this actually changes mother behavior.
3 min petting causes mom to get excited and to lick and groom the kid more. 1.5 hours causes ignorance for long period of time.
Petting itself does not matter, but only mother reaction.
Licking and grooming by mother causes larger brain and all other possible outcomes mentioned above. 
This can have multi-generational effect - licked and groomed daughters will lick and groom their kids more (
again non-Mendelian inheritance). This changes access of transcription factors, which are related to activating genes for making receptors for
stress hormones. It is also reversible. Cross-fostering after non-grooming mom improves kids state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Continuing watching and writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”. Lecture 6.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“So Good They Can’t Ignore You” - impression and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-so-good-they-cannot-ignore-you" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;So Good They Can't Ignore You&quot; - impression and summary" /><published>2019-04-02T08:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-02T08:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/book_summary_so_good_they_cannot_ignore_you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/book-summary-so-good-they-cannot-ignore-you">&lt;p&gt;I’ve read “So Good They Can’t Ignore You” by Cal Newport.
Here is my impression (pretty mixed and rather on the negative side) and summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book felt weird and very wordy. Basically the author developed their own theory about what makes one to like their job
and how to reach this state. These ideas seemed reasonable and somewhat obvious. However, there was no attempt to prove anything
any only ~10 anecdotes instead, which do illustrate the point, but does not prove it. One could easily ignore all the anecdotes.
Also closer to the end the book started listing somewhat random advice from other books. Overall, the content could have been compressed 10-20x without losing much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 2/5 (this wasn’t a complete waste of time, but quite wasteful, I can’t recommend this book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;follow-your-passion-is-harmful&quot;&gt;“Follow your passion” is harmful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are used to hear “follow your passion” advice from everywhere as a way to choose your career.
However, this is wrong. Even Steve Jobs said the same advice, but his own story was different.
If he had followed his passion, there would have been no Apple. Do what Steve Jobs did, not what he 
said to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Follow your passion” has been started with a book “What Color is Your Parachute?” by Bolles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion advice is dangerous, because it makes you feel that there is a perfect job and that
you will immediately recognize it. This leads to excessive career hoping and unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;great-job&quot;&gt;Great job&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self Determination Theory explains intrinsic work motivation needs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Autonomy - control over your day and feeling that your actions are important&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Competence - feeling that you are good at what you are doing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relatedness - feeling connection to other people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a great work requires creativity, impact and control. 
Jobs with these features are rare and valuable. As a result, due to supply &amp;amp; demand
you have to provide something rare and valuable in return (e.g. good skills).
The author calls such skills “career capital”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mindsets-passion-vs-craftsmanship&quot;&gt;Mindsets: passion vs craftsmanship&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to passion mindset (focusing on what a job offers you), there is craftsmanship mindset
(focusing on what you produce).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the passion mindset - answering “do I really love this?” and “what do I like?” is nearly impossible and leads to unhappiness.
Also this forces you to focus on what you don’t like, but all entry level jobs are not perfect (low autonomy and few challenges).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion mindset claims that you need only courage to start your dream job, which will have creativity, impact and autonomy.
Craftsmanship mindset requires you to build your skills first (“to be come so good they can’t ignore you”) to earn
creativity, impact and autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some jobs are just not good for craftsmanship mindset. The job is like that if it has any of these criteria:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one cannot build skill in it to distinguish themselves from others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one finds the results they produce useless or even harmful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one is forced to work with people they don’t like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deliberate-practice&quot;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are some guitar players not that good, while others are much better even after the same amount of practice?
They’ve practiced differently. If you don’t get out of your comfort level during practice, you won’t develop your
skill that well. Instead you should do deliberate practice - focus on what you do badly and use immediate feedback
to correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps to do deliberate practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the career capital market you are in - winner-takes-all or an auction
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Winner-takes-all - only one skill matters and everyone competes for it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Auction - many skills are important, everyone can propose a combination of skills.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify which career capital you need to pursue (i.e. which skill or skills).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define “good”, i.e. your feedback criteria and clear goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Stretch”. Practice outside of your comfort zone and accept feedback even if it
disagrees with your feelings. You may think that what you did is perfect, but you may
be not the one deciding in the end and then your opinion won’t matter at all.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be patient - improving takes time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use open gates - some opportunities which you happened to have e.g. by chance - to gain
career capital much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gaining-control-at-work&quot;&gt;Gaining control at work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving people control over what and how they do increases their happiness, satisfactions and
fulfillment. Once you have career capital you can use it to gain control in your work.
Gaining control before you have enough career capital is dangerous. I.e. you can start doing
what you really want, but no one will find it valuable (e.g. a startup, which no one finds
interesting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have enough career capital to pursue more control (i.e. become valuable enough),
your current employer will try to prevent you from gaining this control, because
this has negative impact for them (less control of you, possibility to lose you). They would
rather use your career capital further and on the old terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, courage is important to face this resistance. However, you should be valuable enough as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-law-of-financial-viability&quot;&gt;The Law of Financial Viability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to identify whether you have enough career capital to go for more control?
If you have an idea how to gain more control, seek evidence whether people are willing to pay you
for it. If yes, proceed. Otherwise move on.
“Willing to pay” may have different meaning, e.g. they actually pay you or you get a loan or you get hired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Do what people are willing to pay for” Derek Sivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless people are ready to pay you for an idea, it is not an idea you should go after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building career on some mission can make it more fulfilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Adjacent possible” - a set of discoveries that are possible to make from the current state of science.
E.g. discovering oxygen required precise weight scales and thinking about air as something not void.
These 2 inventions moved “oxygen discovery” into “adjacent possible”. This concept is considered 
in greater detail in “Where Good Ideas Come From” by Steven Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explore “adjacent possible” one has to reach the cutting edge. Finding a career mission is like
a scientific breakthrough. Reaching the cutting edge is equivalent to building career capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of going for one large bold idea, one should do small incremental “little bets”, which will
mostly fail and only sometimes succeed. This way one can gather feedback. Each bet should take 
approximately 2 months and be either successful or fail. Each bet should follow your mission idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Career capital helps to identify a good mission, little bets help to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;law-of-remarkability&quot;&gt;Law of remarkability&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mission driven projects need to be remarkable. People who encounter them should want to
“remark” about it, i.e. share. Projects should also be launched in a venue which 
supports such remarks (i.e. allows and promotes sharing). “Purple Cow” by Seth Godin
talks about this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="book" /><category term="summary" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I’ve read “So Good They Can’t Ignore You” by Cal Newport. Here is my impression (pretty mixed and rather on the negative side) and summary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“The science of wellbeing” - brief summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;The science of wellbeing&quot; - brief summary" /><published>2019-03-31T10:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-03-31T10:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/the_science_of_wellbeing_course_brief_summary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-brief-summary">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;My summary&lt;/a&gt;
of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/the-science-of-well-being&quot;&gt;&quot;The science of wellbeing&quot;&lt;/a&gt; course at Coursera happened to be much larger than
I originally expected. Here is a more concise one, so that one can quickly refresh all important details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;important-warning-disclaimer&quot;&gt;Important-warning-disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is my very brief summary of the course. If you are considering taking the course,
don’t read this summary. This will spoil all the fun for you. Just go ahead and do the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t consider taking the course, please think again. It is really an amazing course and both of my
summaries probably miss a lot of details. You will get much more by going through the course
(it is only ~19 hours) and doing all the revirements and seeing all the research. Please do the course,
you will like it and understand what I mean!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This summary is also too brief to make sense on its own. This is rather a cheat-sheet for people who
took the entire course. Taking the course (or at least reading 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;my larger summary&lt;/a&gt;)
would explain a lot of the items below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, now let’s get started with a brief summary. Reading through everything in 
&lt;a href=&quot;/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review&quot;&gt;my “large” summary&lt;/a&gt;
is possible, but takes a lot of time. Thus, I would like to summarize my summary even more and write
something short, which I could quickly reread when I feel like I started to forget the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-are-wrong&quot;&gt;We are wrong&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think that having a good job, high salary, money, awesome stuff, true love, a perfect face/body or good grades will make us happy.
Actually we miswant these (i.e. are mistaken about how much we will like something in the future),
because of annoying features of our minds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our mind strongest intuitions are often totally wrong&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We judge everything relative to (often irrelevant) reference points (e.g. other people or what we had before)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hedonic adaptation - our minds are built to get used to stuff (both positive and negative)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We don’t know about this adaptation and overestimate effects of negative and positive changes in our lives
(due to focalism and immune neglect). You will be fine if you fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-to-do&quot;&gt;What to do?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prefer (non-material) experiences to physical stuff.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anticipate them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Talk about them with others&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Savour - step outside of an experience to review and appreciate it fully while it is still happening.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Laugh, giggle, express energy physically (jumping, yelling)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Think how lucky and proud you are&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Don’t &lt;del&gt;think about future&lt;/del&gt;, don’t &lt;del&gt;remind yourself that experience will be over or could be better or
 will never be so good again&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Express gratitude
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tell other people if you are grateful to them&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Once a week write 5 items from the last week, which you are grateful for (take time to feel it through)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reset your reference points
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After a positive change, re-experience your previous state (either remember or find a real example)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Curate information which you let into your life (e.g. no social media, no TV)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Interrupt your consumption - split awesome things you love (and vice versa - squish all bad things together to use 
 hedonic adaptation)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increase variety and choose proper timing (don’t eat an ice cream 40 seconds after the previous one)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want right things
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Employing signature strengths in your career&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Getting into “flow” both at work and at leisure&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Growth mindset (“I can grow through hard work”) instead of fixed (&lt;del&gt;“talent is fixed”&lt;/del&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Intrinsic motivation (doing something due to enjoying the activity itself) instead of extrinsic (due to external rewards)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Opportunities to do acts of kindness (even small, even to random people)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Social connections (even talking to strangers)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Time affluence (feeling of having enough time to do things you actually want)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Controlling your mind (i.e. decreasing mind-wandering through meditation)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exercise&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enough sleep (and of good quality)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-implement&quot;&gt;How to implement?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just knowing is not sufficient. Strategies for better habits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Situation support (fix bad environments, promote healthy environments)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set specific goals (e.g. quantitative). Specificity gives you a plan how to achieve the goal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visualize goals: positive outcome followed by possible obstacles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementation intention through “if then” plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last 3 can be combined into WOOP method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about your (optionally the most important for now) wish (as specific as possible)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Its best outcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential obstacles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your if/then plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This links the obstacle to the wish together with instruments to overcome it and helps to recognize existence of the obstacle&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><category term="summary" /><summary type="html">My summary of &quot;The science of wellbeing&quot; course at Coursera happened to be much larger than I originally expected. Here is a more concise one, so that one can quickly refresh all important details.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lectures 4-5)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-4-5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lectures 4-5)" /><published>2019-03-26T08:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-26T08:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_4_5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-4-5">&lt;p&gt;Continuing writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”.
Lectures 4 and 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-of-previous-lectures&quot;&gt;Summary of previous lectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3&quot;&gt;1-3 - Intro &amp;amp; Behavioral Evolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-4-molecular-genetics-i&quot;&gt;Lecture 4: Molecular genetics I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dna&quot;&gt;DNA&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protein is a sequence of amino acids.
DNA encodes amino acid.
A sequence of DNA can encode sequence of amino acids, i.e. a protein.
Actually genes (DNA) specify the intermediate form - RNA.
Sequence of genes defines everything else - DNA, RNA, amino acids, protein and its shape.
Protein function is defined by its shape (analogy - protein reception is a lock and protein is its key).
There are 20 amino acids. All of them have different degrees of being attracted or repelled by water.
This relationship with watter defines which shape a string of amino acids (i.e. protein) will have in water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enzymes catalyze reactions. For our purposes they can take 2 things and stick them together or take one thing and break it
apart. Virtually every enzyme is a protein. Protein structure also defines circumstances when
its shape can change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Central dogma of life (information flow): &lt;del&gt;DNA -&amp;gt; RNA -&amp;gt; protein&lt;/del&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counterexamples to the first claim that everything starts with DNA:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;viruses which hijack DNA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RNA viruses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;enzymes which can convert RNA back to DNA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mutations&quot;&gt;Mutations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micromutation - one letter random change in DNA.
Each amino acid is encoded by 3 base pairs (a triplet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single letter mutations can be categorized by their effect as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no effect. There are 4^3 = 64 ways to encode amino acids and only 20 amino acids. The genetic code is redundant.
Thus, the letter change can have no effect on resulting sequence of amino acids. Usually, the middle base pair in amino acid is
less important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;weak effect. Some mutations can change resulting amino acid, but some amino acids are similar, so this may not
change the shape of the protein much.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;major consequences. Some mutations can change the protein function dramatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to single letter mutation, there are single point mutations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deletion. This creates a frame shift and totally changes entire sequence of amino acids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;insertion (e.g. accidental copy). This makes a frame shift in other direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations change how well a protein does its job (i.e. its efficacy) by changing its shape.
Soma changes are minor, i.e. the protein mostly does it function, but a little bit less efficiently
(i.e. the key still fits the lock, but not ideally anymore). This is a microevolutionary change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some changes can be major like knocking the protein completely out of its old business,
which can have dramatic effects overall, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a chemical called phenylalanine, which can cause harm if there is too much of it.
There is an enzyme phenylalanine hydroxylase which converts it into something safer, if this enzyme malfunctions,
this can have extreme effects (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phenylketonuria&quot;&gt;Phenylketonuria disorder&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;testicular feminization syndrome (male looks like completely healthy but infertile female)
caused by mutation in testosterone receptor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;problems with enzymes producing testosterone. 
Mutation changes testosterone production efficiency.
There is not enough testosterone in the childhood and the individual develops as female.
During puberty the level reaches critical threshold and one changes sex.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mutation can change how benzodiazepines interact with their receptors.
This variability explains individual differences in levels of anxiety.
For example, people are breading rats prone to some behavior - alcoholism, smart, high or low anxiety.
The last two breeds differ by shape of their benzodiazepine receptors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Foxp2 gene is related to communication. Its mutation can cause language problems in humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-dna-is-compared&quot;&gt;How DNA is compared&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you share 50% of DNA with your sibling, but 98% with chimpanzee? Genes specify traits.
E.g. we have genes for specific shape of pelvis. Chimps have them too,
but apple trees don’t. 98% of our and chimp genes encode similar traits (like some shape of pelvis).
Each gene can vary. Thus, when talking about your sibling, the question is not
whether you both have genes for pelvis, but whether they are exactly the same (i.e. same shape of pelvis).
Overall, when we compare across species, we take into account only types of genes encoding
types of traits. Inside one species - different versions of a particular gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gradualism-vs-punctuated-equilibrium&quot;&gt;Gradualism vs Punctuated Equilibrium&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 1980s everyone believed in gradualism, 
i.e. that &lt;del&gt;evolution was driven by gradual changes&lt;/del&gt;.
In 1980s a new model called “punctuated equilibrium” emerged. Here periods of stasis (no change) are followed
by very fast and explosive periods of change. It was proposed by a paleontologist.
Consequence of this theory - little changes don’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criticism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paleontology is different from evolutionary biology.
The timescales are very different (100k years is nothing in paleontology and a lot in biology).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evolution of brain, eye color, skin will leave no paleontological record.
Paleontology is about shapes (morphology).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1980s non-gradualists (supporters of punctuated equilibrium) struggled to show molecular mechanisms
which could explain punctuated equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dna-structure&quot;&gt;DNA structure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially people thought that DNA had the following structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;gene A&amp;gt;&amp;lt;stop signal&amp;gt;&amp;lt;gene B&amp;gt;&amp;lt;stop signal&amp;gt;&amp;lt;gene C&amp;gt;...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually genes themselves have modular structure as well&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;       exon        intron          exon
&amp;lt;gene A - part 1&amp;gt;&amp;lt;more data&amp;gt;&amp;lt;gene A - part 2&amp;gt;...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splicing enzymes cut out unrelated parts.
What if a function of a splicing enzyme changes?
If we have a gene with 3 exons (denote them 1, 2, 3), after splicing and gluing back we can get - 123, 12, 13, 23, 1, 2, 3
(i.e. 7 different proteins out of one gene). This allows tissue specific expression of genes.
Same gene will produce different types of proteins in different parts of the body due to different splicing enzymes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are splicing enzymes which can cut inside exons (not in-between). 
I.e. in the example above, after slicing one can get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;some part of &quot;gene A - part 1&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;gene A - part 2&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, even more proteins can be created from one gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another discovery - there is non-coding DNA between genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;       gene A    &amp;gt;  non coding DNA   &amp;lt;      gene B     &amp;gt;
&amp;lt;A1&amp;gt;&amp;lt;more data&amp;gt;&amp;lt;A2&amp;gt;-------------------&amp;lt;B1&amp;gt;&amp;lt;more data&amp;gt;&amp;lt;B2&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;95% of all DNA is non-coding.
Non-coding DNA is an instruction booklet when to activate which genes (i.e. on/off switches).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are proteins (transcription factors) which turn these switches on/off (i.e.
promote or repress some sequences of genes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same promoter can enable more than one gene (i.e. networks of genes). Any gene can 
have multiple different switches (i.e. can belong to different networks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, DNA does not “know” what it is doing, it is just a readout. The one in control is the one
controlling transcription factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, environment can affect genes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in cells there are sensors which activate some transcription factors when energy level is low&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gene expression in the cell can be regulated by environment somewhere else in the body (e.g.
through hormones - testosterone causes your muscles to grow)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or even outside of the body (pheromones).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DNA itself is wrapped in chromatin, which opens up for transcription factors.
I.e. it can regulate which transcription factors can reach DNA at all.
Parts of chromatin can be even permanently closed to silence a specific gene forever.
Epigenetics studies regulation of access to gene sequences.
For example, in rats the way mother behaves can affect stress hormones of her kids permanently
through this mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the most interesting part of DNA is not shape of proteins, but when it is active
(i.e. DNA has if-then clauses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetics is about fertilization, epigenetics is about development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-5-molecular-genetics-ii&quot;&gt;Lecture 5: Molecular genetics II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mutation in a splicing factor can cause very dramatic changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;A1&amp;gt;&amp;lt;more data&amp;gt;&amp;lt;A2&amp;gt;&amp;lt;more data&amp;gt;&amp;lt;A3&amp;gt;
can become
A1|A2' + A2''|A3
instead of
A1|A2|A3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also get a mutation in a promoter. This changes the activated gene network (i.e. completely new
if-then clause). In other words, there are amplifying effects of small changes when they happen in splicing factors or promoters.
In vols one promoter change defines whether they are monogamous or polygamous.
A large share of differences between us and chimps are changes in transcription factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, evolutionary changes are mostly driven by regulatory changes in DNA, not in protein encoding itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dna-shuffling&quot;&gt;DNA shuffling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plants can’t run away, so they have tricks to shuffle their DNA as a response to a stressor.
Immune system in animals does this shuffling too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shuffle DNA&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate antibodies based on obtained DNA sequences&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See whether they work against the pathogen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathogens can do the same to fight antibodies. This is a coevolutionary arm race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process also happens when your neurons are created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By moving parts of DNA around you can have large macro consequences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing “if dehydrated, then wake up kidneys” to “if dehydrated, then also ovulate” 
allows seasonal mating. Mate during dry season to give birth during raining season.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“if smells like me, then don’t mate (incest taboo)” -&amp;gt; “if smells like me, cooperate”
creates kin selection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such shuffling allows to introduce variability in degrees of an effect as well
(e.g. if smells very much like me - cooperate very much, a little bit like me - cooperate a bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can have clauses “if &lt;some hormone=&quot;&quot;&gt;, then&quot;. These can be shuffled as well.
E.g. glucocorticoids suppress immune system. If you swap it with progesterone,
then this is useful during pregnancy (no immune system response to fetus).
But immune system can overshoot after pregnancy and this leads to autoimmune diseases.
I.e. one &quot;small&quot; change (which hormone) has large macro consequences.&lt;/some&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One single base pair change can cause diseases, which will kill at 3 months of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, such macro changes have negative effect. It is just unlikely to stumble on something
positive. Thus, there is stabilizing selection against macro mutational changes, i.e. long periods of stasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;speed-of-evolutionary-changes&quot;&gt;Speed of evolutionary changes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evolution has selective bottlenecks - events through which only individuals with some trait can get through.
Cheetahs has got through one and now they are highly inbreed (you can transplant tissue from one to another
and it won’t be rejected).
Such bottlenecks create circumstances of punctuated radical change. This “rapid” change can still take
thousands of generations (which is a lot for biologists and not that much for paleontologists).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macro mutational changes - invention of new proteins and networks.
Micro mutational changes - changes in function of preexisting proteins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. immune systems in chimps and humans differ only through micro changes,
while development - macro differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of “fast” changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Westernized diet causes diabetes. Populations which get introduced to western diets
get a very high rate of diabetes. With time the most vulnerable don’t pass their genes and
rate of diabetes starts to go down (evolution of resistance). This happened within a century.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Russian Siberian foxes have been bred for only 35 generations for tameness
(calmness around people). They started looking like cute puppies.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/5_fox_ears_like_puppy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fox looking like puppy&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first domesticated fox to have floppy ears, 1969 (source: “The silver fox domestication experiment” Dugatkin, 2018, 
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-018-0090-x&quot;&gt;url&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/5_fox_facial_characters_like_puppy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fox face looking like puppy&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Domesticated foxes have juvenile facial features, including shorter snout (source: “The silver fox domestication experiment” Dugatkin, 2018, 
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://evolution-outreach.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12052-018-0090-x&quot;&gt;url&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In other words, they’ve got dog-like traits - e.g. wagging their tails around people.
  Actually breeding for tameness is equivalent to breeding for acting like a child and
  infantile traits (being dependent on others).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Their fur changed too. Ironically in the process of breeding they became useless economically.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Another example is antibiotic resistance. Bacterias can develop resistance to our drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize, traits evolve as groups. Thus, there are many punctuated changes at the same time.
If you have enough of them, this will look like gradual change (gradualism).
In some sense both models (gradualism and punctuated equilibrium) are correct at the same.
Punctuated equilibrium is observed on individual trait level and gradualism when considering
multiple traits.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">Continuing writing a summary for Robert Sapolsky’s course “Human Behavioral Biology”. Lectures 4 and 5.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">German supermarket discounts for fun and profit</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-discounts-in-german-supermarkets" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="German supermarket discounts for fun and profit" /><published>2019-03-24T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-24T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly_discounts_in_german_supermarkets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/weekly-discounts-in-german-supermarkets">&lt;p&gt;I recently started buying discounted food more and here are my tips &amp;amp; tricks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are sure that you will buy something and there happens to be a discount for it,
you save money by buying with the discount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;expiration-date-discounts&quot;&gt;“Expiration date” discounts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with discounts motivated by a product reaching its expiration date.
Basically all products have some expiration date. After that date supermarkets
can’t sell the product anymore, i.e. they lose the money used to buy the product in the first place.
Thus, they are motivated to incentivize people to buy the product before the expiration date. 
When there is not much time left, they create this incentive by adding a discount.
Usually in German supermarkets it is 30% off and usually it is added 1-2 days before
the expiration date, but occasionally this can happen even 1 week in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, this is a way to save 30% on some of your food. This mostly works for food
with shorter storage time like meat and bread (but not e.g. canned food).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this safe? Yes, the food hasn’t actually expired yet.
I also suspect that food producers actually have some safety margin
in the expiration date. In other words they may set the expiration date much earlier to be extremely sure that the
product won’t go bad before that time. This is just my speculation though. Overall, I am not aware of any safety issues
with this approach. Obviously, you should inspect food you buy using all your senses and trust your self preservation
mechanisms, but this applies to anything you consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, we can’t just store such food in the fridge for long. One example usage is to cook it soonish.
Usually once you cook it, you can store it for a bit longer or you can just consume the cooked food immediately.
To save even more, you can freeze such foods (this works especially well for meat).
This way you can store it for couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such discounts are more frequent on Saturdays. I suspect this is because the shops are closed on Sundays, so on Saturday they have to sell
all food which would otherwise go bad on Sunday and Monday. This works even better before large holidays (e.g. Christmas)
presumably for the same reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weekly-discounts&quot;&gt;Weekly discounts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is the second kind of discounts. Almost all popular shops in Germany have “random” discounts which change each week. 
This time they are not related to the expiration date (i.e. there is nothing unusual about the products).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ways-to-explain-this&quot;&gt;Ways to explain this&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a number of hypotheses why supermarkets do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This brings people to the supermarket itself.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Once a person is there, they can lose their self control and buy more stuff (even non-discounted).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The time spent getting to the shop can be considered as a sunk cost and promote buying more as well.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discount itself may promote buying more of the discounted product, i.e. “I don’t actually need this,
but next week there will be no discount, so I should buy it now to get the discount”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Storing stuff presumably costs money. Occasionally it may be better to sell stuff with a discount than to store it. I.e. the shop may
“pass” you some portion of the money they would otherwise pay for storage, but which they managed to save by you buying the stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ways-to-discover&quot;&gt;Ways to discover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 2 major ways to discover such discounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to the shop itself and look for brightly colored price tags.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check shop’s magazines online (the German keyword is “Prospekt”,
e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lidl.de/de/online-prospekt&quot;&gt;Lidl&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penny.de/angebote/prospekt-der-woche/&quot;&gt;Penny&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netto-online.de/ueber-netto/Online-Prospekte.chtm&quot;&gt;Netto&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely prefer the second approach, since it is much more efficient (takes less time and you don’t look
at non-discounted products at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;possible-pitfalls&quot;&gt;Possible pitfalls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should keep in mind that supermarkets are doing this for a long time and, thus, in the end this must be
profitable for them. As a result you should be careful and make sure that you are actually the one
benefiting from these discounts. I can imagine the following possible pitfalls:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you able to control yourself at the shop itself and stick to buying only what you originally planned?
Lists help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you don’t need something in the first place, you just lose money by buying it (even when it is heavily discounted).
E.g. you never eat rice, there is no point in buying it, even when it costs 50% less this week. Instead you should focus on things you
would buy anyway. However, if your uncle loves rice and consumes 3 kilograms of it during his visits, buying rice with 50% discount
and storing it saves you money.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;There is a neat way in which you can check the magazines to avoid this issue - look only at the
product pictures (but not prices) at first. I.e. if you don’t need something, don’t even check its price. Once you find
something you need, check its price.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discount on a more expensive product may be not a discount for you.
E.g. you use shampoo A, which costs 1 euro per liter, but there is a discounted shampoo B which costs only 2 euro per liter
instead of its normal price of 4 euro. If you buy B, you actually lose 1 euro (i.e. discounted B price minus normal A price) instead of
saving 2 euro as it might have looked at first.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Another variation of this is seasonal food price fluctuations. E.g. in winter watermelons can have a discounted price of 
 only 0.99 per kilo instead of 1.99. However, they cost 0.4 per kilo during the season. So you still in some sense lose
 money when paying discounted 0.99. Obviously, if you consume watermelons all year round, you would actually save, so go for it!&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Another example could be if a shop increases the price right before having a discount. 
 I don’t think this is intentionally done in Germany, but still worth keeping in mind especially in other countries.
 Usually you start remembering normal prices for main staples with time. Alternatively, if you track your expenses 
 in great detail, you could use that info to double check the price (e.g. how much did this cost last time I bought it?).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Different offers in magazines can apply to different dates. Yes, they like to have 5 pages with entire week discounts, 
followed by one page for only e.g. Mon-Wed discounts. I think this is intended, because then people may miss this and
when they buy a lot of stuff in addition to discounted things (but you shouldn’t do this anyway), they will miss that
they are buying without the discount. However, if you don’t buy much, just check the receipt after buying. Normally, there is a paper
magazine in the shop itself, so you can double check the discounted price there (or even show it to the cashier).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There may be no discounted price tags on Monday yet. I’ve got an impression that discounted price tags appear after some time.
So if you go on Monday morning, either take the paper magazine or note down the prices you expect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-much-can-i-save&quot;&gt;How much can I save?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This depends on you and how flexible you are. For example, Jacob from &lt;a href=&quot;http://earlyretirementextreme.com/&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Extreme&lt;/a&gt; suggests to buy &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; discounted food and then decide what to cook out of it. This definitely requires quite some creativity
and may be not that convenient. Alternatively you can go for some middle ground solution. For example, one can buy discounted food
which can be stored for a long time. This mostly includes canned and frozen foods (already frozen vegetables/fruits or self frozen meat).
Canned foods can be easily stored 1-2 years, so it is possible to buy reasonably large discounted batches and just store it and use
whenever there is a need. Already frozen foods also have large lifespan, you just need a freezer and a reliable energy source.
For self frozen there is no clear time bound, but its state may start to become worse after e.g. 3 months, so that’s a good rule of thumb
I use. This way you still have flexibility (you can cook what you want right now), while partially benefiting from discounts available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed 10-30% discounts, so if you manage to buy 100 euro of discounted food, you would save 10-30 euro. 
While this is not a life changing sum of money and you definitely shouldn’t rely on this discount in your
FIRE calculations (otherwise the calculations are too tight, trust me), it is also not that much of an effort and can be
even pleasant if you like optimizing your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people may think here that this is not worth their time, because they earn so much more than that.
I’ve already &lt;a href=&quot;/post/my-time-costs-x-fallacy&quot;&gt;looked into this (“My time costs X” fallacy)&lt;/a&gt;.
In this particular case you can check the magazines literally in 5-10 minutes and you would have to go the shop anyway
(unless you order your food online, but then you have more fruitful ways to save money, for example, by not ordering
food online).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy discounted shopping!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="saving" /><summary type="html">I recently started buying discounted food more and here are my tips &amp;amp; tricks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“The science of wellbeing” - my impression and summary</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;The science of wellbeing&quot; - my impression and summary" /><published>2019-03-19T19:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-19T19:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/the_science_of_wellbeing_course_review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/the-science-of-wellbeing-course-review">&lt;p&gt;I took &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/the-science-of-well-being&quot;&gt;&quot;The science of wellbeing&quot;&lt;/a&gt; course at Coursera.
I absolutely loved it! I would like to share my impression and a not so brief summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impression&quot;&gt;Impression&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon this course accidentally, when I was doing much more popular “Learning how to learn” course.
As I’ve already said in &lt;a href=&quot;/post/learning-how-to-learn-course-review&quot;&gt;my review&lt;/a&gt; of “Learning how to learn”, 
my impression was pretty mixed, but I learned a couple things. “The science of wellbeing” was just amazing and it is surprisingly
much less popular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I have no idea what could have been done better. The course consists of 10 weeks, the last 4 have very little material
and meant for the last large “revirement”. The first 5 weeks or so had weekly “revirements”. A revirement is some task,
which you should do during the week and which is meant to boost your wellbeing. So you do the revirements and in parallel 
learn about happiness and wellbeing and after some time learn the science behind each of the revirements as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The studies were mentioned perfectly. Basically, the teacher makes some claim and then briefly explains results of
2-3 studies supporting this claim. Many of the studies were mind-blowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t recommend it &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt;. It easily can be a life-changing course.
You should take this course, everyone should take this course.
Your mind will be blown away by how wrong we are, when we think about happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Score: 5/5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;important-warning-disclaimer&quot;&gt;Important-warning-disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is my summary of the course. If you are considering taking the course,
don’t read the summary. This will spoil all the fun for you. Just go ahead and do the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t consider taking the course, please think again. It is really an amazing course and my
summary probably misses a lot of details. You will get much more by going through the course
(it is only ~19 hours) and doing all the revirements and seeing all the research. Please do the course,
you will like it and understand what I mean!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I assume that you don’t take the course (but you should) or you are just me rereading the summary
after some time to refresh all the fruitful bits I’ve forgotten. So let’s get started with the summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note I’ve restructured the order of the topics a bit to make the text more coherent. In the real course there was
one week delay between lectures, so giving a hint about the next week topic worked well, but here this feels weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-we-think-will-make-us-happy&quot;&gt;What we think will make us happy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a pretty good picture of what should make us happy.
However, will it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider each popular option. Later we will look why they actually won’t make us happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;good-job&quot;&gt;Good job&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does not getting a job makes us unhappy [Gilbert 1998]?
When people get refused and consider it fair, they predict 2/10 happiness score drop, but actually it is 0.6/10.
When they consider it unfair - 1.9/10 predicted vs 0/10 actual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;high-salary&quot;&gt;High salary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much salary do you need (based on how much you have now) [Lyubomirsky 2008]?
If your current salary is 30k, you need 50k, but if it is 100k, you need 250k.
E.g. you target jumps up with each salary increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random interesting fact: US lottery ticket spending in 2015 was 70B, which is larger than books, music, movie tickets, sport tickets and video games combined. This could mean that people assume that having a lot of money will make them happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correlation between “life satisfaction” and income is 0.1 - 0.15. In poor countries it is stronger, because increasing the income gets you access to clean water, basic health-care. Once your basic needs are met, increase in money has negligible effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does general quality of life increase happiness? In 1940 average happiness was 7.5/10 and in 2015 it is 7.2/10. Living in 1940 was much harder (e.g. no washing machines).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US happiness stops increasing after $75k [Kahneman]. However, our own evaluation of life increases even after 75k.
In other words, high income does not bring you happiness, but does bring a life that you think is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall money do make us happier a little bit, but way less than we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;awesome-stuff&quot;&gt;Awesome stuff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If only I had &lt;em&gt;__&lt;/em&gt; I would be so happy”.
Nope, you wouldn’t and actively seeking it can even make you less happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;true-love&quot;&gt;True love&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Married people are happier in the first 2 years and then there is no difference to non-married.
True love makes us happier only for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;having-a-perfect-facebody&quot;&gt;Having a perfect face/body&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who complete a weight lose program end up with increased depression rate.
Similarly for cosmetic surgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;getting-good-grades&quot;&gt;Getting good grades&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as much as you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-it-doesnt-make-us-happy&quot;&gt;Why it doesn’t make us happy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is considered in more details in “The how of happiness” by Sonja Lyubomirsky.
Her research shows that genes and circumstances are less important for happiness than we think.
Their contributions are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;genetic - 50%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;circumstances (life happens) - 10%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;actions / thoughts - 40% (this we can control)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are things we can do to be happier, but most of the things we are trying to achieve to increase our happiness
won’t make us happier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can think that this is true for others, but you are different. However, all the research suggests otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miswanting - the act of being mistaken about what and how much you will like something in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we miswant? Because of annoying features of our minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feature-1-wrong-intuitions&quot;&gt;Feature 1: Wrong intuitions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our mind’s strongest intuitions are often totally wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feature-2-reference-points&quot;&gt;Feature 2: Reference points&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t think in terms of absolutes. Instead we judge relative to reference points.
A reference point - a salient (but often irrelevant) standard against which all subsequent information
is compared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: [Medvec et al 1995] at Olympics the silver winner thinks “I could have had gold” and feels unhappy,
while bronze medalist thinks “Oh, I could have had no medal at all” and feels happy. They have different reference points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of reference points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We. E.g. our previous salary. Our idea of “good income” goes up with our current income. 
Each 1$ increase increases our target by 1.4$ [Van Praat &amp;amp; Fritjers 1999].&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Others (social comparison). E.g. if your coworkers have higher salary, you are less happy with your job. 
This can take very weird forms. When asked to choose between “you make 50k, others 25k” and “you - 100k, others - 250k”, 56%
have chosen the former [Solnick &amp;amp; Henenway 1998], even though it is half as much money. Unemployed people
have higher wellbeing [Clark 2003] when unemployment rate is high.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Thus, getting extreme social reference points makes you unhappy. 
E.g. [O’Guinn &amp;amp; Schrum 1997] the more people watch TV, the higher they estimate wealth of other people around them (not on TV)
and the lower - their own wealth. The more you watch TV, the more unhappy you become with yourself, because you implicitly 
compare yourself with what you see.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;We just try to keep up with whoever happens to be around. We don’t even try to find reasonable reference points.
E.g. [Kuhn et al 2011] when someone wins a car in a lottery, their neighbors are then more likely to buy a car as well.
[Kenrick et al 1993] Just looking at pictures of fashion models lowers women mood from 2.36/4 to 2.07/4.
This can affect perception of your partner. [Kenrick et all 1989] Men rated attractiveness of their partner 
lower after looking at models (22.1 vs 26.2 in control).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For the new generation this is even worse due to social media.
Correlation between Facebook use &amp;amp; self esteem is -0.2 [Vogel et al 2014].
Looking at people who are doing worse then you have no effect on your self esteem though.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feature-3-adaptation&quot;&gt;Feature 3: Adaptation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds are built to get used to stuff. Hedonic adaptation - the process of becoming accustomed to a positive or negative
stimulus such that the emotional effects of that stimulus are attenuated (weakened) over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wonderful things are especially wonderful the first time they happen, but their wonderfulness fades with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feature-4-we-dont-know-about-adaptation&quot;&gt;Feature 4: We don’t know about adaptation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t realize that our minds are built to get used to stuff.
This works both ways - feeling better about bad stuff as well as feeling worse about good stuff due to getting used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impact bias - the tendency to overestimate the emotional impact of a future event both in terms of intensity and its duration.
It is worse for negative effects - at first we feel like “this is going to destroy our life”. 
For positive - the event ends up being just not as awesome as we predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works even in very surprising situations. [Sieff 1999] People predict their happiness score to be 47.4 the moment they find out that
they have HIV, but their actual score is 59.1. For the case when the test result says “no HIV”, they predict 94.7, but in reality it
is 77.6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we just have not enough experience, because the events are rare? Nope.
[Ayton 2007] When failing driver exam multiple times, every time you fail you still overestimate how bad 
you will feel if you fail next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be explained with two psychological biases (this is considered more deeply in “Stumbling on Happiness” book):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focalism - tendency to think just about one event and forget about other things that happen. When you focus on one thing,
you misspredict. Try to think about stuff around the event. E.g. when thinking about illness, people forget that the 
majority of good things they had in their life won’t go away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Immune neglect - unawareness of our “psychological immune system”, i.e. of the tendency to adapt to and cope with
negative events. Our brains have a lot of resilience to deal with bad things. You have mechanisms to force yourself 
to feel better and you use them more than you realize. E.g. we can rationalize everything (“this bad event was actually good
for me because …”).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible result of these biases is the new generation being scared to take risks. You will be fine if you fail.
You misspredict your own potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-to-do&quot;&gt;So what to do?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are strategies which allow you to boost your happiness. They fix our current miswantings (by helping us to
want right things) and help us to want other unexpected things which actually make us happier, but which we would never
want on our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;awesome-stuff-1&quot;&gt;Awesome stuff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t invest in physical stuff in the first place. It won’t make you as happy as you think, because it sticks around and you get
used to it.
Quote by Gilbert:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Part of us believes the new car is better because it lasts longer. But in fact that’s the worst thing about the new car… It will stay around to disappoint you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead invest in experiences - they don’t stick around. Experience - anything you can pay for (or free) that makes you happy 
but is not a physical thing. You just won’t have time to adapt to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Van Boven &amp;amp; Gilovich 2003] People find that experiences bring happy thoughts (7.51 vs 6.62 for material), contribute to happiness (6.4 vs 5.42) and they consider money spent on experiences spent better (7.3 vs 6.42). This effect gets stronger the larger income
you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about the experience in advance (anticipation), this makes you happier as well.
You feel more excited and better about planned experience purchase vs material (2.64 vs 1.37, 2.58 vs 1.06 respectively) [Kumar et al 2014].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People’s intuition is wrong about this. They predict that material purchase will make them happier than experiential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about your experiences makes you happier as well. This can just be more interesting for others to hear or help
them to resonate with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiences are less susceptible to social comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about things we already have (including marriage, being at Yell [note: this is a Yell course])?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Savoring.&lt;/strong&gt; You can use savoring, i.e. stepping outside of an experience to review and appreciate it fully while it still happens.
This forces you to notice and enjoy the experience and keep your attention on it.
This also helps you to focus on the experience for even longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Jose et al 2012] Activities to enhance savoring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk to another person about how good you felt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look for other people to share the experience with&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about what a lucky person you are&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about sharing (talking) this later with others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show physical expression of energy (jumping around from joy, yelling)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laugh or giggle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tell yourself how proud you are&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think only about the present and be absorbed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities which hurt savoring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focusing on the future (i.e. think about experience being over)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reminding yourself that the experience will be over soon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reminding yourself that nothing lasts forever&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking how it will never be this good again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thinking about ways it could be better [note: I definitely unknowingly experienced this myself]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Telling yourself that you don’t deserve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Kurtz 2008] Taking photos is controversial in terms of savoring.
You can take photos in two ways:
1) Focusing on photos themselves and not being mindful (i.e. photos is the goal)
2) Using your photos to see different aspects of the thing you taking picture of,
learning about new and better properties of it (i.e. as a tool for savoring)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One actionable way to do savoring is [Lyubomirsky et al (2006)] to think about a happy event “as though
you are rewinding a videotape and playing it back” (8 min/day * 3 days). People had sustained increases
in positive emotions 4 weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way is negative visualization - thinking about the reverse that could have happened.
[Koo et al 2008] E.g. couples wrote for 15 minutes about how they might have never met their partner (or about how they met).
In the first case happiness score was 5.67, latter - 4.77.
This helps you to break yourself out of here and now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frame your view as “the experience may be over soon” instead of “I have plenty of time left”.
This way you focus on how it would be without the thing you have and this brings you out of
hedonic adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, advantages of savoring:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fights hedonic adaptation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keeps us in the moment (without mind wandering)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increases gratitude (we become thankful for the experience during the experience itself)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gratitude.&lt;/strong&gt; You can use gratitude. Gratitude - the quality of being thankful and a tendency to show appreciation
for what one has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Emmons &amp;amp; Mc Cullough 2010] Writing once a week 5 things from last week, which you are grateful for, boosts your happiness,
decreases physical symptoms and increases hours of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing gratitude can be extra powerful. Tell other people if you are grateful to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude can help in romantic relationships (e.g. to mitigate bad things in a relationship).
In work context, receiving gratitude from your superior makes you work 50% harder (without additional pay) [Grand &amp;amp; Gino 2010].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, feeling gratitude:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increases mood, lowers stress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improves health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;creates stronger social connections.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reset-your-reference-points&quot;&gt;Reset your reference points&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They affect our happiness judgments all the time (even if we don’t realize it).
E.g. potato chips taste better when they are placed near sardines than when near chocolate [Morewedge et al 2010].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concretely re-experience. The moment you get something (e.g. a dream job) it becomes your new reference point.
Find a way to go back to your previous state and re-experience it. Make a habit to go back and re-experience
the stuff as it was before your current state.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concretely observe. Find a real example of a worse situation (e.g. similar to what you had before) and look at it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid social comparisons.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Stop technique. The moment you notice you are doing social comparisons (browsing Instagram), say “stop” out loud&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gratitude stops social comparison (“gratitude is killer of envy”)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Be conscious of the kinds of social comparisons you are letting in your life. Curate your own info. 
E.g. “Real Beauty” campaign instead of “Victoria Secret” models.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No social media. Otherwise be mindful when using them and use techniques above.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interrupt your consumption. If you force yourself to have an interruption, you set your reference in a very positive way
(absence of the thing). [Nelson &amp;amp; Meyvis 2008] When making people listen to their favorite music with a pause inside the song,
people’s happiness jumps dramatically right after the pause. [Neolson et all 2009] Commercials on TV make you enjoy the thing
you are watching more. Thus, split the awesome things you love in life.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;For bad things, you want hedonic adaptation to kick in quickly. Thus, don’t break them up. Try to squish all of them together 
instead. E.g. do a hard problem at once instead of 15 minute chunks with breaks in between.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase your variety.
If you always eat the same ice cream (A A A A A…) you will adapt and it will get boring.
If you eat different ones and then get back to the one you tried first (A B C D A), it will feel cool again.
This breaks your adaptation and changes your reference point. Timing also matters. Eating an ice cream 40 seconds after
the previous one is boring. Variety is another reason why experiences are better for your happiness than material stuff.
Experiences are dynamic, while stuff is constant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;want-right-things&quot;&gt;Want right things&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we should want to become happier, but don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good job.&lt;/strong&gt; We want high salary. Instead we should seek a career that employs our signature strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Signature strengths - character strengths that are the most essential to who we are.
Character strength properties:
1) Ubiquitous (widely recognized across cultures)
2) Fulfilling (leads to satisfaction and fulfillment)
3) Morally-valued
4) Not able to diminish others
5) The opposite of a negative trait
6) Trait-like (stable individual difference)
7) Measurable
8) Distinctive (not redundant with other strengths)
9) Paragons (some people really have it and it is very strong)
10) Prodigies (some people precociously (from birth) have it)
11) Selective absence (some people don’t have it)
12) Institutionalized (society values it)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 24 character strengths overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Seligman et al 2005] Using your top strengths in new and different ways every day for a week improves happiness and
decreases depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Lavy &amp;amp; Littran-Ovadia 2016] The more you use your strengths at work, the more productive and more satisfied with your job
you become (caused by positive emotions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Harzer &amp;amp; Ruch 2012] Using signature strengths can turn a job into “a true calling”. As a result, you can find ways to use your signature strengths at your job to improve your job satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[VIA Institute on Character][http://www.viacharacter.org/www/] provides a questionnaire (free, but registration is required) 
to estimate your signature strengths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to signature strengths, our good job should bring us into “flow”.
There is a book “Flow” by Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi about this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow - the mental state in which a person performing an activity is fully immersed in feeling of energized focus,
full involvement and enjoyment (aka “the zone”) and loses track of time. E.g. when doing sport, music, work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;challenging but attainable goals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;strong focused concentration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;activity is intrinsically rewarding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;feeling of serenity (the state of being calm, peaceful, and untroubled)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;loss of self-consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;timelessness / losing track of time passing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lack of awareness of physical needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;complete focus on the activity itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve flow, you must have good skills in the activity and it must be challenging enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny fact that even here we miswant. [Lefevre 1988] In work situations we experience high challenge and use our skills, which
brings sense of efficacy and self-confidence. In leisure we instead do low challenge/low skill (e.g. watching TV) and this
causes apathy and boredom. We try to put ourselves in this leisure state assuming that it will make us happier (we would rather
rest and keep resting instead of working). We can choose more challenging leisure activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, a good job = signature strengths + flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good grades.&lt;/strong&gt;
Extrinsic motivation = engaging in a behavior in order to earn external rewards or avoid punishments.
Intrinsic motivation = engaging in a behavior because you enjoy the activity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extrinsic motivation can undermine intrinsic motivation. [Deci 1971] When people were asked to do a puzzle in 3 visits, the ones paid during their second visit (extrinsic motivation) worked much less on it during their third visit (seconds of work during each of the visits for the group, which was paid during the second visit: 248, 314 (paid), 199, control (not paid at all) - 214, 206, 242).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A focus on grades (extrinsic) can undermine intrinsic motivation (you enjoying the subject). It can also undermine growth mindset.
There is a book about growth mindset called “Mindset” by Carol Dweck.
Growth mindset = the belief that intelligence can be trained and that most basic abilities can be developed through dedication
and hard work.
Fixed mindset = the belief that basic qualities like intelligence and talent are fixed traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of grades they can be compared as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;col width=&quot;33%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Fixed&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Growth&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;focus on&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;grades&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;learning, not outcomes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;believing that good performance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;comes naturally&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;takes hard work&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;hard work&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;“if I have to work, then I’m not smart”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;good, that’s how you get better&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;effort&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;bad sign&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;good sign&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;deficiencies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;conceal and hide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;make the most out of them&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;mistakes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;conceal and hide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;capitalize on them&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Grant &amp;amp; Dweck 2003] Students with growth mindset have higher grades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed mindset helps when you already have good skills - “I’m smart, I just need to prove this one more time”,
i.e. when you stay at already high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Mangels et al 2006] Fixed mindset people focus more on feedback (whether their answer was correct),
while growth mindset - on the correct answer (how this should have been done and how I can improve).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you shouldn’t want good grades, but rather a growth mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better wantings.&lt;/strong&gt; There is plenty of stuff you should want to become happier, but you don’t yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Opportunities to do acts of kindness. Doing acts of kindness (even small, even to random people) boosts your
happiness a lot. [Dunn et al 2008] When people are given 5$ or 20$, they predict that spending the money
on themselves will make them happier than as if they spent them on someone else. They also predict that
spending 20$ is much better than 5$. Actually spending money on others makes you much happier
and the effect of spending 5$ is the same as 20$. [Atkin et al 2008] This holds across cultures and income levels.
E.g. in countries where 5$ is a lot of money, spending them on others still makes people happier. 
Possible explanation of why this works - our brain sees the rewards other people get as our own rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social connection. [Myers 2000] People with close social ties are less vulnerable to premature death, more likely to survive
fatal illnesses and less likely to fall prey to stressful events. [Diener &amp;amp; Seligmann 2000] Happy people have more close friends, strong family ties and romantic relationships. Happy people spend more time with family, friends or their lover.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Epley &amp;amp; Schroeder 2014] Even small random connections (e.g. talking to strangers in public transport) boost happiness.
People mispredict this, they choose solitude which makes them unhappy. People you talk to also feel better afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Boothby et al 2014] Same chocolate tastes more delicious and has richer flavor if you happen to be in the same room with 
someone tasting the same chocolate (you don’t see them, you just know that they are there).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Social connection makes the life even richer.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Interesting random quote: “Happiness is like a leaky tire - after a good movie you don’t stay happy forever.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Time affluence. This is a feeling like you have enough time to do the things you actually want to do.
[Whillans et al 2016] Prioritizing time over money was associated with greater happiness.
[Hershfield et al 2016] However, more people (69%) value money over time. Those who value time are happier.
[Mogilner 2010] People, who were primed to think about time, socialized more in a cafe.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Prioritizing time makes you happier and more social (this helps with social connection above as well).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Controlling your own mind. Mind-wandering - a shift in the content of thoughts away from an ongoing task and/or 
from events in the external environment to self-generated thoughts and feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Killingsworth &amp;amp; Gilbert 2010] Our minds wander 46.9% of the time. Why so much? Default network - a network of interacting
brain regions known to activate “by default” when a person is not involved in a task. This network is very fast (activates
in a fraction of a second after a task). It thinks outside here &amp;amp; now (past, future, other people).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Mind-wandering is a cognitive achievement (animals don’t usually think about past or future or can’t do this at all).
It affects all activities (except sex - in this case the degree is smaller) and has negative impact on happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;How to stop mind-wandering? Meditation - a practice of turning your attention away from distracting thoughts toward a single
point of reference (e.g. breath, bodily sensations, compassion, a specific thought). Examples of meditation&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;loving kindness (thinking about the fact that you care about someone and you want them to be happy and healthy)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;focusing on breath&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;choiceless awareness (noticing how thoughts appear in your mind and letting them go instead of following them)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Brewer et al 2011] Meditation practice can curb mind-wandering (even outside of meditation). Thus, meditation can make us happier.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Hölzel et al 2011] Meditation (27 min/day for 8 weeks) causes increase of gray matter content in brain.
[Mrazek et al 2013] Meditation (4 * 45 min during 2 weeks + 10-20 min of mindfulness exercises) boosts GRE performance.
[Hutcherson et al 2008] Loving kindness meditation on some person increases your social kindness to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Overall meditation can make you happier by shutting down mind-wandering, boosting social kindness (and as a result
connections) or just performing better.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exercise. [Babyak et al 2000] Exercise treats depression better than medicine (90% recovery rate for a group doing
30 min 3 times/week for 16 weeks vs 60% for anti-depressant Zoloff group). [Hillman et al 2008] Exercise improves
cognitive function. There is a connection between academic achievement and physical fitness scores.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sleep. Sleeping not enough (~5 hours) [Dinges et al 1997] affects your mood and increases physical and emotional complaints.
Good sleep also has other benefits [Walker et al 2002, Wagner at al 2004].&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-apply&quot;&gt;How to apply?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just knowing about all of these is not enough to put this into practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gi-joe-fallacy&quot;&gt;G.I. Joe Fallacy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently there is a cartoon, which everyone in the US knows and not many outside do.
The cartoon was meant to teach kids and the main hero (G.I. Joe) often said “Knowing is half the battle”.
However, this is not true. Just knowing is not enough to change how you think and behave.
One needs to change their habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to get beyond just knowing that we should want these things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategies for creating better habits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;situation-support&quot;&gt;Situation support&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Situation affects us more than we think (e.g. having food around promotes eating, having someone typing on their phone 
makes you check your social networks). Situations can cause unhealthy behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a book “Slim by Design” by Brian Wansink which considers situation support in the context of losing weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Painter et al 2002] Proximity of a candy jar (either on the desk or two meters away) increases candy consumption by 48%.
Having a candy jar in drawer (not immediately visible) causes 25% smaller consumption. Thus, visibility and convenience in which
you can engage in your habits both matter. You can do this in negative ways (keeping candies visible) or in positive ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Wansink et al 2016] Having cookies, chips, cereal and soda visible on your kitchen counter increases average weight by 10 kg.
Fresh fruit and vegetables - decreases by 5 kg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should fix bad environments (get rid of stuff that is tempting you, e.g. delete a social media app from the phone). This way
you will have fewer bad cues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should promote healthy environments (e.g. having physical notes and reminders around you). Social context (having others doing 
a positive habit around you) promotes the habit and increases kindness and social connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;goal-setting&quot;&gt;Goal setting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about goals in very specific ways can help you achieve them better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal specificity.&lt;/strong&gt; The degree of quantitative precision with which a goal is specified (i.e. “lose weight” vs “lose 1 kg during April”, “meditate” vs “when, how frequently, how long”). Specificity seems to give you a plan how to achieve the task.
[Klein et al 1990] With goal specificity people naturally develop task strategy, which boosts their performance. Specificity forces 
you to think how you are going to do the task.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Thus, whatever goals you have - make them incredibly specific.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal visualization.&lt;/strong&gt; Mental contrasting = a visualization technique involving thinking of a positive future outcome followed
by thinking of obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you just think about positive outcome, then you don’t get closer to the goal, you just feel better. If you think only about 
obstacles, then you will be demotivated to do anything.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Stadler et al 2010] Mental contrasting had positive effect even after 24 months when taught to women trying to eat more fruits/vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Thus, don’t just visualize the good part of the outcome, but take time to consider obstacles as well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal planning.&lt;/strong&gt; When you are in a particular situation, it will implicitly affect you (thinking “grab the pizza” when seeing pizza
in the canteen). How to intervene even though this happens implicitly? There is a way to have an implicit plan as well. It
allows you to get through situations like this automatically (without having to apply much willpower).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Implementation intention - a self regulatory strategy in the form of an “if then” plan that can lead to better goal attainment.
During preparation you can visualize “if I’m in the dining hall and I see pizza, I will turn back and grab the orange”. Our
automatic system can pay attention to this “if then” plan if you put in that level of specificity. Peter Gollwitzer researches
this topic in more details.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This can also be used to remember stuff (e.g. “when I grab the door knob, think about keys”).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;[Gollwitzer and Brandstaetter 1997] For easy goals implementation helps a little bit, for hard - a lot (success rate of achieving
the goal increases from 25% to 65%).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Putting all goal strategies above together.&lt;/strong&gt;
WOOP method (wish, outcome, obstacle, plan):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about your wish (as specific as possible)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best outcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Potential obstacles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your if/then plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a book “Rethinking Positive Thinking” by Oettingen about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider each step in more details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wish. What is my most important wish (for a given time-frame)? What do I want today? What do I want next week?
Isolate one important wish, formulate it with 3-4 words and put it in front of your mind. At this stage you just search for the right wish.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would be the best outcome if I fulfill that wish? Search for the best outcome and formulate it in 3-4 works. Again put
it in front of your mind. Then imagine the best outcome - just let your mind go. This is not a search anymore, but imagining and
experiencing. Take at most 1 minute to really feel the outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead of dreaming about the outcome all the time, you now switch gears. What is my main [inner] obstacle? What is it in me?
This can be emotion, irrational belief, bad habit, something someone had said. Formulate it with 3-4 words and put it in from of
your mind. Now imagine the obstacle and experience it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What could I do to overcome that obstacle? Formulate this in 3-4 words and put in front of your mind. Make a simple if-then plan. If &lt;obstacle&gt;, &lt;my action=&quot;&quot;&gt;.&lt;/my&gt;&lt;/obstacle&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that WOOP can be used to overcome inner obstacles and to understand yourself better. The example above is about
understanding yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes more mental effort than just indulging in fantasies. However, this mental effort triggers your unconscious which
does a lot of work for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also use WOOP to find out whether something is feasible or even to let go less feasible wishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise links the obstacle to the wish together with instruments to overcome the obstacle. It also changes the meaning
of the reality - you now recognize that there is an obstacle. This allows you later to do automatically what you want to do.
Recognizing the obstacle is the most important part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do WOOP at the same place and time to establish a ritual. You don’t need to it perfectly. WOOP changes with life,
because positive fantasies come from our needs (deficiencies) and they change with time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important: don’t switch o’s. Once you think about obstacle first, it won’t work anymore, because you can discover the real obstacle
only in the framework of the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I took &quot;The science of wellbeing&quot; course at Coursera. I absolutely loved it! I would like to share my impression and a not so brief summary.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“Human Behavioral Biology” - course summary (lectures 1-3)</title><link href="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="&quot;Human Behavioral Biology&quot; - course summary (lectures 1-3)" /><published>2019-03-17T12:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-17T12:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://merelycurious.me/post/human_behavioral_biology_sapolsky_course_summary_lectures_1_3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://merelycurious.me/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-1-3">&lt;p&gt;I watch “Human Behavioral Biology” course by Robert Sapolsky (from Stanford) on Youtube.
It is very interesting. Here is my summary of the first three lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-1-introduction-to-human-behavioral-biology&quot;&gt;Lecture 1: “Introduction to Human Behavioral Biology”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-the-course-is-about&quot;&gt;What the course is about&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is common between “having a period”, “having a brain tumor”, “eating a lot of junk food” and “taking anabolic steroids”?
All have been successfully used in courts as a defense for a murderer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Points of the course:
1) Sometimes what happens in your body can dramatically influence what happens in your brain (examples above).
2) Sometimes something in your head can affect your entire body (e.g. when one imagines that they will die
their heart starts beating faster).
In other words, the course is about the connection between physiology and behavior, emotions, memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;categorical-thinking&quot;&gt;Categorical thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We divide everything into categories, because this makes it easier to store information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/post_resources/human_behavioral_biology_summary/1_spectrum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of spectrum divided into categories&quot; width=&quot;500px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E.g. it is much easier to remember whether you saw a triangle, a square or a circle than some weird shape,
because we don’t have a word (i.e. a category) for latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disadvantages of categorical thinking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can’t differentiate two facts that fall in the same category (b &amp;amp; p in Finnish or two similar colors) - you underestimate their difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have trouble seeing how similar things are right across the category boundaries (e.g. 65% on the test leads to fail and 66% to pass) - we overestimate the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you pay attention to boundaries, you miss the big picture (e.g. phone numbers are supposed to be 3 digits followed by 4).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoiding-categorical-thinking&quot;&gt;Avoiding categorical thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the course is to think about biology of behavior without falling into categorical thinking.
The category (bucket) you are in affects how you explain the world. We want to avoid this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 main challenges - recognizing when we:
1) just like other animals and accepting that. E.g. ovulation synchronization in females living together.
2) we appear to be like any other organism, but do something very different.
Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chess master capturing a piece feeling like a baboon who won a fight&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we get stressed when reading something bad happening to a character in a novel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can feel compassionate about other species. This is the same physiology as in other animals, but we use it in unrecognizable ways.
3) do something that no other animal even remotely does (e.g. non-reproductive sex, language use).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the course we will overview various buckets first - evolution, molecular genetics.
Then we will look at behaviors and consider them through each bucket separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-2-behavioral-evolution-i&quot;&gt;Lecture 2: Behavioral Evolution I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darwin didn’t discover evolution. He came up with a mechanism for it - natural selection.
Darwinian evolution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are heritable traits (i.e. genetic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is variability among those traits (ways in which they can occur)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some versions of those traits are more adaptive (work better for you) then others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is not about survival, but reproduction.
When you have all of these, you get evolution and populations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you add mutations - you can get large changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies well to physiology, but how to apply this to behavior? Exactly the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are heritable behaviors (i.e. behaviors have genetic components, this is an important assumption)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;types/classes of behaviors have variation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some are more adaptive than others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a false belief that &lt;del&gt;“animals behave for the good of the species”&lt;/del&gt;.
Actually animals behave to pass as many copies of their genes as possible (reproduction of the fittest).
Sometimes this may look like behavior for the good of the species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ways to pass your genes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Individual selection - maximize number of times you reproduce through natural selection (useful traits improving
adaptability) and sexual selection (arbitrary traits).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kin selection - helping out relatives to reproduce (cooperate with relatives to a different degree, which depends on how
closely they are related to you) by decreasing your own reproductive success.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reciprocal altruism - cooperation among non-relatives, but it must be reciprocal (you must get something out of it and not
more than you put it), e.g. group hunting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prisoner-dilemma&quot;&gt;Prisoner Dilemma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reciprocal altruism leads to cheating and being good at detecting cheating against you. When to cheat and when to cooperate is studied in game theory. The basic “model” is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisoner%27s_dilemma&quot;&gt;Prisoner Dilemma&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tit-for-tat-strategy&quot;&gt;“Tit for Tat” strategy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You cooperate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next time:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If they cooperated last time, you cooperate&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Otherwise you cheat&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nice (kind)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retaliates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forgiving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deterministic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This drives other strategies into extinction when multiple agents play multiples games with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a vulnerability - signal error. 
What if there is a possibility of a mistake (noise in the signal),
e.g. cooperation looks like cheating.
This wipes out 50% of cooperation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  ++-+-+...
  +++-+-...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;forgiving-tit-for-tat-ftft&quot;&gt;Forgiving Tit for Tat (fTfT)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Improved version of TfT. 
Like normal TfT but after “saw pattern” for 5 rounds - forgive and cooperate.
fTfT outcompetes TfT when you can have signal error.
It has another vulnerability - it can be exploited by strategies without forgiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tft---ftft&quot;&gt;“Tft -&amp;gt; fTfT”&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start off with pure TfT. If for N rounds the other party didn’t cheat, switch to fTfT.
I.e. you begin to “trust” someone and this protects you from signal error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;pavlov&quot;&gt;Pavlov&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I do something and I get rewarded, do it again next time. If I lose, I switch.
This allows you to exploit someone, who is forgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random mention: “The political uses of madness” - an article by Daniel Ellsburg on the optimal benefits of perceived madness 
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/ThePoliticalUsesOfMadness&quot;&gt;source1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia600102.us.archive.org/20/items/ThePoliticalUsesOfMadness/ELS005-001.pdf&quot;&gt;source2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;examples-in-nature&quot;&gt;Examples in nature&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vampire bats. Females share their nest with non-relatives. Everyone feeds all babies.
When they think that one female cheats on them, they stop feeding her kids.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;black hamlet fish. They can change their gender. Pair of them flip their gender back and forth. Being female
is more “expensive”. If one fish ends up being a male too many times, other fish will stop cooperating with them
(TfT).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exceptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lion. Non-relatives in a pride. If you fake a sound of other lion in the bush, in many prides one lion
stays behind the group, while all other go to check and risk by doing this. However, this lion is not punished.
In real world you can have many ongoing games at the same time or others just don’t pay attention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;naked mole-rat. Big cooperative colonies (possibly non-relatives). 1-2 animals don’t do any work, but no 
one punishes them. They are even larger, because they eat more. However, when the rainy season comes
they plug the entry to the tunnel with their bodies (example of another ongoing “game” and role
diversification).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;application-to-behavior-analysis&quot;&gt;Application to behavior analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to use the fact that species maximize copies of their genes to analyze behavior? 
Imagine that we have two skulls - one male and one female.
Just by their relative size to each other we can conclude a lot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;col /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&quot;header&quot;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Males much larger&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Males the same&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;male aggression&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (their body is built for this and females select for this)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;variability in male reproductive success&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (5% males do 95% of reproduction)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low (every male gets 1-2 kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;what females want&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;large body size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;“good personality” - parental behavior (e.g. male birds bring food to females as
evidence that they can feed kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;parental behavior in males&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;low (not interested in kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high (care about kids)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;life span&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;high variation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;no difference by gender&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;twinning&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rare (impossible to feed on your own)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more frequent (male helps to feed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;kids abandonment by females&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;rare (kids will die for sure, male won’t take care)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more frequent (male will feed them anyway)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;species kind&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;tournament&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;pair bonding monogamous&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;example&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;peacock (feathers show that you can waste a lot of energy)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;tamarin monkey (one can’t distinguish males and females visually)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt; 
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could see this only by ratio of male and female skull sizes.
Humans fall in between these two kinds of species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lecture-3-behavioral-evolution-ii&quot;&gt;Lecture 3: Behavioral Evolution II&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s use “individual maximizes number of copies of their genes” to explain more behaviors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;explaining-infanticide&quot;&gt;Explaining infanticide&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babies are cute - they are trying to reduce aggression by this. There are species with infanticide (e.g. lions).
Patterns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adult male is the one killing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infants who are most likely to be offsprings of other males are killed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;average interbirth interval in females is larger than the average tenure of high ranking male.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the new alpha male e.g. just killed the previous one, but all females won’t ovulate
for 2.5 years, while you will be alpha male only for 1.5 years. Thus, by killing kids:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reproductive success of other males is decreased&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;females will start ovulating sooner (by stopping nursing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates that individuals optimize number of copies of their genes instead of doing good for the species.
Another example is mountain gorilla. They have infanticide even though they are at risk of extinction. 
In other words, they even endanger their species more to increase their own reproductive success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peculiarly infanticide does not happen if previous alpha was a relative.
Two male lions can even share a pride of they are brothers (adelphic polyandry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Females have developed number of adaptations due to this as well.
In some species females have spontaneous abortion due to smell of the new male
(there is no point to invest more resources into the kid, since it will be killed anyway).
Females can also try to protect their kids. If they are older, they will risk their life more
(they are less likely to have another kid). Maternal grandmothers defend even more (they won’t
reproduce at all).
Another strategy is to have pseudo estrous (i.e. fake ovulation) during pregnancy.
The new male mates and thinks that the kid is his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons do blackmail kidnaping of kids. If alpha attacks an individual, they can grab
alpha’s kid implying “attack me and I will kill the kid”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gender-ratio-fluctuations&quot;&gt;Gender ratio fluctuations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tournament species having a son is a volatile way (gamble) to pass your genes (may work out
very well, but most likely won’t). Having a daughter is a conservative way (they will have few kids,
but with high probability). However, giving birth to a male requires more energy. Higher 
ranking females have more sons (can take the risks). During environment distress (e.g. famine)
more daughters are born. This can produce sex ratio fluctuations (having sons is better
when there are few males).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intrasexual-competition&quot;&gt;Intrasexual competition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Males and females can have different reproductive goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be achieved by means of imprinted genes - their effect depends on which parent they come from.
There is a genetic mechanism to achieve this. Examples of such genes and their usage in intrasexual competition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Imprinted genes coming from father tend to improve fetal growth (i.e. the kid should get as much energy from
the female as possible, males in migratory species do not care about future reproduction of a particular female,
but only about their kid).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From mother - slow down fetal development (this particular kid is less important to a female than their overall
reproductive life).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mechanism malfunctions if one of the genes gets disabled due to a mutation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are imprinted genes, which work only after birth. E.g. from male one can get “suck more milk” (i.e.
get more calories from female). You only see this in tournament species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have imprinted genes. By their quantity we are again in between pair bonding and tournament species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sperm competition in polyandrous species.
In some fly species sperm makes toxins that kill sperm of other males.
However, they cause harm to females too.
This makes no sense for the good of species,
but does for individual success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direction-of-male-aggression&quot;&gt;Direction of male aggression&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are species (e.g. chimpanzee) with exogamy (individuals leaving the group after puberty to avoid
interbreading). If males leave the group - you get high aggression inside the group among males (they 
are not relatives). If females - among groups (chimpanzee genocide and border patrols). Human military tries
to create this kinship artificially, chimpanzees have it by nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cooperation&quot;&gt;Cooperation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start cooperation by reintroducing highly interbread group (close relatives) into general population.
This small group can outcompete others (due to their kinship) and others are forced to start cooperating as well.
This is a push towards group selection (highly interbread group with kinship cooperation can drive others who don’t cooperate
to extinction). In humans - trust in business or low interest loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be the case that strategy A dominates B when there is only one individual in each group,
but A is dominated by B when there are many individuals in each group. E.g. a group of aggressive chickens would
injure each other. However, when there are only two chickens, an aggressive one will outperform non-aggressive.
This is a group selection as well (but due to personal benefit in the end).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, we observe multilevel selection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;single gene level&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;individual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criticism of applying Darwinian principles to behavior:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heritability of behavior - what are the molecular principles driving this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adaptiveness - everything you see has an adaptive explanation for
why it emerged evolutionarily - there are non-adaptive traits. 
Why do humans have chins? Otherwise you can’t get a flat face. These are so called
spandrel traits, they are just an inevitable result of other traits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gradualism - evolutionary change occurs in gradual incremental steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also political criticism - founding social biologists were white south American males (i.e. 
they could just be justifying male domination because this is positive for them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary-of-following-lectures&quot;&gt;Summary of following lectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/post/human-behavioral-biology-sapolsky-course-summary-lectures-4-5&quot;&gt;4 &amp;amp; 5 - Molecular genetics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="courses" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html">I watch “Human Behavioral Biology” course by Robert Sapolsky (from Stanford) on Youtube. It is very interesting. Here is my summary of the first three lectures.</summary></entry></feed>